在1994年九月，日本任天堂開始製作超級馬力歐64。
從最一開始，任天堂就已經做好了一個打算:
把馬力歐從2D變成3D開啟許多令人興奮的可能性，而其中
最重要的是他最具標誌性的能力:他的跳躍能力
馬64的跳躍系統做得非常好。
遊戲在1996年發售的時候一炮而紅，馬上就取得
了巨大的成功。
圍繞在3D遊戲中前所未見的緊湊且靈敏的操作上，
馬力歐在馬64能使用A鍵做出非常多種動作:
跳，二段跳，三段跳，帶有星星的三段跳，側空翻，
長跳，蹬牆跳，後空翻，上踢，跳撲!
所以玩家很自然地就會想:
如果這些動作我們都不用會怎樣?
(譯者註:為避免疑惑，關卡名會用《》標註，星星名子用【】標註，某些敵人名子不會特別做翻譯)
(0xA代表不使用A鍵，1xA代表這個星星或關卡使用一次A鍵，依此類推)
(不按)A鍵挑戰的完整歷史
(目前努力翻譯中，目前進度為32分鐘，之後的字幕是英文，有發現錯字請找M99#7944)
網路世界在90年代末與2000年初是一個神奇的地方，
有如童話故事中那個很遠很遠的王國一樣。
那個時期大部分的內容已經消失或是被整合進現代的網頁了。
但有時候還是可以找到一些被保存起來的網頁，供後人參考。
其中之一是Walton Dell的網站，裡面記錄著各種他
發現或是其他人電郵給他的64主機遊戲小技巧。
這些之中一些是bug，一些是給讀者的有趣挑戰，
還有一些就比較無厘頭，像是想像地板上有一張臉，
或是找到12個維京炸彈(bully)??
直到2000年10月16號，一位匿名的讀者發了一封很長的郵件，
他不會想到這會在接下來的20年掀起多大的熱潮。
其中有一個挑戰他稱為「不按A鍵挑戰」:
嘗試按最少次A鍵拿到《炸彈戰場》所有的星星。
雖然郵件裡講得很清楚，因為某些原因，Walton Dell
對要不要把使用大砲的A鍵算進去感到有些困惑。
他覺得不使用A鍵對【射向空島】來說是不可能的，
因為使用大砲至少一定要按一次A鍵。
所以他決定把這個A鍵當成一定要按的來算，
於是【射向空島】在他的網站上變成了名義上的0xA。
然而在郵件中，拿到這個星星的策略寫的很詳細:
跑到這座橋然後跳下來，使用砸地打開裝有羽毛帽的箱子
拿到羽毛帽之後，使用大砲(A)往天空發射。
飛到裝有星星的箱子用砸地打開並拿到星星。
這樣用1xA來射大砲就可以完成【射向空島】。
有趣的是，郵件中提到一個叫做Myles的人，
但在Walton Dell的網站上這個挑戰被稱為"Alex的挑戰"。
所以這位匿名讀者到底是誰?
後來發現是傳奇人物Alex Penev，當時最高產的N64遊戲玩家之一。
他在馬力歐賽車64的前十年創下了數以百計的世界紀錄，
並且直到今天還活躍在馬車社群中。
在1999年，社群中的一部分人在使用IRC討論捷徑跟策略。
雖然大部分的主題圍繞在馬車64，但偶爾也會提到其他遊戲。
Penev跟Myles Bukrim, Jason Whalls和David Wonn
(David Wonn也有自己的網頁關於N64遊戲的技巧跟bug)
他們一起創造了許多馬力歐64挑戰，像是:
不吃硬幣，帽子拿星星，不使用大砲拿星星，
當然其中最重要的就是A鍵挑戰。
(手動校正字幕到這邊)
Alex的郵件有許多令人驚嘆的細節，
最後都被放上了Walton Dell的網站
網站也收到了許多跨時代的A鍵挑戰解法。
舉個例子，在《雪山》中，【雪山八紅幣】在那個時候就已經0xA了。
其中這個紅幣特別難搞，Jason Whalls發現一個拿到它的聰明策略:
首先觸發底下的移動平台使它往上。
然後趕快跑到傳送點讓馬力歐上去山上，
往下跳收集硬幣，前撲並趕上移動平台往下的時間。
另一個例子，一樣在《雪山》中，【蹬牆跳有用】
策略是彈到這個spindrift上並按1次A鍵來跳到它的上面，
並且一直按著它不放。
在空中旋轉時按著A鍵會讓馬力歐下落速度較慢。
使用這個緩降策略，馬力歐可以只用1xA就收集到這個星星。
時間不太確定，但是網站收到了另一位讀者的A鍵挑戰。
《雪人島》中，【雪人島八紅幣】
Dell認為只要騎上龜殼之後一切就很簡單了，但他找不到騎上去的方法。
所以Dell在網站說0xA是不可能的。
然而在Penev的郵件中，有詳細提到【旋轉到冰凍池塘】的0xA策略，
所以很有可能Nathan使用了類似的方法來拿到【雪人島八紅幣】。
出於某些個人原因，Walton Dell沒有發布更多
Penev在郵件中提到的更多A鍵挑戰。
這一整年間，這是A鍵挑戰在網路上唯一的紀錄
但在2001年，一切都改變了。
Chris Oldfield，也叫做humantree，在GameFAQs上發布了
第一個專門紀錄A鍵挑戰的網頁。
他在網路上記錄了他自己的最少A鍵紀錄。
而其中一些Alex Penev已經有更好的紀錄，
於是他們就一起在ICQ上交換不同的策略。
但從一開始大家都忘了一件事:
A鍵挑戰的紀錄都一直以個別星星為單位來計算。
其中包含每個關卡的【100硬幣星星】。
Humantree是第一個打破這個規定的人，
他提出了一個問題:
在一個全新的存檔能夠完全不按A鍵收集有多少星星?
他全力的使用了當時已知的所有策略，結果他拿到了10顆星星。
不幸的是，《黑暗世界庫巴(第一個王)》需要1xA才能通關，
所以Humantree無法到達城堡的其他部分。
另外《鬼屋》要12個星星才會開啟，
也差一點點就能去了。
於是在只能到4個關卡的前提下，
他收集了【山頂上的炸彈王】【烏龜賽跑】【射向藍天】
《雪山》除了【蹬牆跳真的有用】的所有星星，
以及21秒內完成【公主的秘密滑道】。
當然這些成就到今天只剩下文字紀錄而已。
Humantree的網站後來就下架了，也沒有頁面存檔可以看。
這份歷史存在於被遺忘的邊緣，只被少數人記得。
然後，A鍵挑戰就這樣了。
在完成了大約30顆星星以及從新存檔拿到10顆星星之後，
沒有人去研究遊戲其他關卡的A鍵挑戰。
沒有人想過那個最關鍵的問題:
要通關馬力歐64到底最少需要按幾次A鍵?
許多年過去了，這個問題都沒人解答。
同一時間，馬力歐64的許多資源仍然持續被產出
2002年11月，一名GameFAQs活躍用戶用戶，高中學生Curtis Bright
架設了一個網站sm64.com。該網站直至今日都還存在。
這個網站詳細列出了遊戲中所有硬幣，加命蘑菇，傳送點，秘密道具的位置。
它也記錄了遊戲中許多限時挑戰的世界紀錄影片，這在當時是前所未見的。
其中兩個人擁有大部分的紀錄。
他們的名子? Myles Bukrim跟Alex Penev。
2003年某天，Penev在AIM上寄了一則訊息給Bright。
Penev想要把《雪山》的A鍵挑戰延伸為
使用1xA拿到關卡中所有的星星。
這激發了Bright的興趣:
於是他順便研究了其他關卡，包含《炸彈戰場》《Whomp的堡壘》
《海盜灣》《鬼屋》《火山》《高高山》。
最終結果是使用了48xA收集了45顆星星。
後來在2005年底，他就在他的網頁開設一個A鍵挑戰專區，
專門發布他的成績。
可惜，他孤軍奮戰。
多年來，A鍵挑戰已經山窮水盡，
直到命運中的那天:2007年7月13日。
在GameFAQs論壇上，一名叫做Kirbymuncher的用戶開了一個新的貼文
專門討論A鍵挑戰。
Curtis Bright是前幾個參與討論的人。
他提到了另一個巴西玩家有開設一個自己的紀錄網站。
網站上研究了更多星星的A鍵數量。
這個巴西玩家叫做Thiago Trujillo。
他們發現Thiago嘗試了非常多的星星。
事實上，在該貼文發布的兩個月前，他就已經
用244xA收集了112顆星星。
然而許多他的紀錄不是最佳的:
Curtis Bright在6個星星上比Thiago做的更好，
兩人紀錄合併起來使用了230xA收集了112顆星星。
這個時候，N64模擬器已經越來越流行，
由於可以隨時存檔的功能，許多人更少的A鍵
在容易失誤的地方拿到星星。
Bright覺得他應該要做兩個世界紀錄列表，把RTA(人類玩家)
與TAS(電腦輔助)的紀錄分開，這樣才公平。
其中一名TAS玩家是bobmario511，他發現了許多聰明的
方法來減少許多星星的A鍵使用數量。
其中最讓人印象深刻的點是他14年前貼的影片到現在還看的到。
事實上他貼了超過100個影片。
現在只剩少數幾個星星還沒被研究過，
主要在《時鐘塔》《彩虹毯》
《天上的庫巴(第三隻王)》以及【可怕的港口100硬幣】
這些星星被認為實在是過於困難，至少要10xA才能拿到。
在此同時，Curtis Bright實現了他的想法。
他更新了他的網站，
加入了另一個紀錄表，把RTA跟TAS分開。
人們可以把自己的影片紀錄傳給他。
在這些紀錄中有Bright自己的，bobmario511
Thiago Trujillo，也有許多較不知名的玩家像是
EnNopp112, SilentSlayers, sonicpacker以及Robert Z等等。
非常可惜的是這些人之後就再也沒做出什麼重要的貢獻。
(這句是一個玩笑,sonicpacker是TAS界的大佬)
最早的遊戲總A鍵使用量便是從Curtis Bright的網站來的。
在2008年6月12日，總共需要用到217xA來收集全部120顆星星。
但這邊有兩個要注意的點。
首先，好消息:所有星星都是分開計算的。
然後是壞消息:所有星星都是分開計算的。
因為拿到每一關的【100硬幣星星】不會把馬力歐給踢出關卡，
如果把它跟關卡裡的其他星星一起收集，
就可以合計省下更多A鍵使用量。
這邊稍微估計一下，大約可以省下12到15個A。
但是那個時後，沒人考慮過完整的120星星路線，
並且在不完整的資料下，
要客觀的給出一個明確的A鍵使用量數字是不可能的。
所以我們現在先把這些應該可以省下來的A鍵加回來。
然而這個數字並不包含在城堡裡移動以及進入關卡所需的A鍵。
《秘密水族箱》《迷宮洞窟》《鋼鐵帽》各需要1xA進入。
《彩虹飛毯》《飛越彩虹的馬力歐》《消失帽》跟《天上的庫巴》各需要2xA。
最後《大小島》《時鐘塔》每次進去都需要1xA，
總共需要多按23次A鍵。
於是最早的完整紀錄是240xA。
在2008年6月，另一名TAS玩家alkhdaniel
在時鐘塔裡面省了6個A鍵，
把總A鍵數減到了234，
他的影片沒有多少人發現，
像是這個關於【時鐘塔100硬幣】的影片只有一個
來自這個無知玩家的留言。(你是怎麼不按A上踢的?)
有了紀錄版，一篇反應熱烈的GameFAQs貼文
工具輔助紀錄的出現，以及有關每一個星星A鍵的紀錄，
A鍵挑戰終於進入了黃金時期。
減少通關遊戲所需的A鍵數量--任務正式開始了。
隨後的進展簡直不可思議(...?)
Curtis Bright的網頁從未真正流行起來。
接下來3年，有大約30個不同的人發布到網站上，
但是其實紀錄沒有任何進展。
那篇GameFAQs的貼文在幾個月之後就沒人回復了，停在了300個回復。
玩家沒有繼續減少A鍵的使用量，大家都覺得這個挑戰已經被解決了。
過了整整三年才終於有了新的進展。
這個進展來自出乎意料的地方，取得了光榮的成就。
不按20A鍵拿到20顆星星。
同樣的，因為《黑暗世界的庫巴》需要1xA，
所以去不了城堡的其他地方。
這個TAS是由一群日本TAS玩家在2011創造的。
當它在3月發布到YouTube的時候，引發了軒然大波:
6天就達成了7萬8000次觀看。
許多文章記錄了它的成就。
不幸的是，這個TAS的生產過程並不清楚，因為作者們
現在也不記得它的細節了。
但這個確實啟發了另一個日本TAS玩家，
他找到了《海盜灣》【掠奪沈船】的進展，不按A收集它以及
《海盜灣》第二個星星，把全新存檔的不按A星星數量提升到22。
然後，就這樣了。
A鍵挑戰在接下來的兩年半中被世人遺忘了
但是這個沉寂期是特別的:
這是最後一個。
在2013年8月25日，一名意想不到的人重新出現了。
還記得那個五年前出現的無知玩家嗎?
他是pannenkoek2012。
在接下來的幾年之後，他的成就是如此地具有革命性，如此的
令人難以置信，只憑他一個人就把A鍵挑戰昇華到了無人能想像的高度。
這裡是當時收集所有120顆星星所需最少的A鍵數量。
總共有208xA。
某些早期的關卡已經幾乎不需要A了，但是後面的關卡
尤其是垂直高度很大的《時鐘塔》，簡直是完全的噩夢。
但是這一切都即將改變，一場革命即將發生。
在短短的兩年之中，幾乎所有的A鍵使用都將消失。
Pannenkoek2012原本只是這個遊戲影片的觀眾，
但他從2010年開始製作一些拿到關卡內所有金幣的影片，
獲得了一些關注。
但在一些關卡中，他拿到的金幣數量是遊戲的顯示上限255個，
比關卡中原本的金幣總量多很多。
他使用了一種當時連他都還不太了解的複雜技巧。
不幸的是，那些影片的畫質相當地低:
當時他是用一些免費試用版的螢幕錄製軟體錄影Project 64(N64模擬器)。
這讓影片畫質非常糟糕，但跟當時其他的影片比起來還算好的了。
時間是2013年，他覺得他已經把每一關的最大硬幣量弄清楚了，
所以他決定研究新的議題。
他開始研究遊戲中各種的bug，
用影片紀錄他的各種發現。
直到某天，他感覺到他的知識量足夠嘗試A鍵挑戰了。
從8月25號開始，他發布了一連串的影片，紀錄遊戲中
拿到每一個星星的所需A鍵數量。
最一開始的幾個影片包括兩個《炸彈戰場》的星星，
【射向天空】跟【8紅幣】。
這兩個星星的要解決的主要問題在如何不按A到空島上，
而他使用的策略可以是前所未見的。
當其他人都在玩沙的時候，Pannenkoek已經在蓋大樓了。
他一出手就驚天動地，天才的程度甚至讓他有了自己的維基百科條目。
這是名為「克隆」的藝術。
很自然地，Pannenkoek第一個技術突破是使用
他花了很多年在刷金幣精通的bug。
在我們看他變魔術以前，需要先了解「克隆」，也就是複製物品，這個bug
到底是怎麼運作的。
各位做好準備，現在是上一堂遊戲物理課的時間了。
注意事項；這邊會有一點長，但我不推薦跳過這段。
「克隆」可能是A鍵挑戰直至今日為止最最重要的一個技巧，
如果不了解它的運作原理可能會讓你後面很大一部分搞不懂。
那麼請翻開課本，我們開始上課吧。
在開始以前，我要說一下其實Pannenkoek的頻道已經
有很詳細的影片教學了
事實上，這個影片幾乎所有的遊戲運作原理都是
從他的影片整理出來的。
我會在影片畫面下方做編號註記，提供一些更完整的解釋。
在影片的說明欄裡面有所有的註解跟專有名詞列表。
並且如果提到一些先前講過的機制，會有時間註記
讓你忘記的話可以回去複習一下。
「克隆」源自於馬力歐在拿起物品的時候，他手中你看到的物品
其實是原本物品的複製品。
原本的物品在馬力歐放開它以前都會是隱形且通常無法接觸。
讓我們稱呼它們為「原物」跟「手中物」。
因為原物其實還存在並且有被載入，
它只是沒辦法跟馬力歐互動，我們稱它處於「停滯」狀態。
遊戲還是會更新它的動畫資料，只是不會顯示它。
在此同時，手中物的影像會根據三個資料產生:
遊戲會追蹤它的位置；
手中物的旋轉角度跟馬力歐的角度一樣；
而它的動畫則隨原物的狀態變化。
根據原物的不同，它的位置也可能改變。
有些會留在原處；有些會跟著馬力歐移動或跟在他附近。
一個有趣的例子是炸彈:
馬力歐拿起炸彈的時候引線會被點燃，
於是我們可以看到冒煙的特效。
因為手中物只是複製影像而已，它其實不會產生冒煙的特效。
我們看得的煙霧是從原物來的:
原本(隱形的)炸彈的位置會跟著複製影像一起移動
使得煙霧看起來像是從複製影像冒出來的。
另外，炸彈是原物在被抓住的時候，
馬力歐還是能跟它接觸的一個少數例外。
這造成了膨脹炸彈的bug。
在炸彈爆炸的幾幀前，
炸彈會明顯的膨脹。
如果馬力歐在對的時間抓住它，
他就可以抓住一顆膨脹的炸彈。
馬力歐就會被膨脹的炸彈往後推動，
並且只要馬力歐不放開它，那顆炸彈就會一直跟著他移動。
但是如果馬力歐在炸彈爆炸的同時抓住它會怎樣?
這裡就是事情開始變好玩的地方了。
但在那之前，我們要先講講抓住跟放開物品到底是怎麼運作的。
當馬力歐抓住一個物品，遊戲會檢查一些東西。
首先，遊戲會把那個物品標記為馬力歐要抓的對象。
然後馬力歐會被設定成有拿著東西的狀態，
並且那個物品會被設定成被拿著的狀態。
在多數情況下，同時把原物改成隱形且無法接觸的狀態。
為了讓整個過程可以正常運作，馬力歐必須要能跟
原物有某種聯繫，不然在停滯狀態的原物就永遠沒辦法被拿回來了。
遊戲使用一種非常簡單的系統來處理這個過程。
每個物品在載入的時候
都會占用240個物品欄中第一個空位。
雖然事實上物品欄的記憶體位置看起來像這樣，
為了讓事情簡單一點，我們直接給每個物品
1到240的編號。
當馬力歐抓起一個物品，原物會被改成停滯狀態，
馬力歐則會拿到連結到原物的物品編號。
那個物品編號存在馬力歐的手中物，
也就是原物的複製影像。
手中物只要有原物的物品編號，遊戲就可以運作。
而只要馬力歐拿著手中物，原物就會維持載入(雖然是停滯狀態)。
當馬力歐放開物品，不管是丟出還是放下，
遊戲會檢查物品編號，然後把停滯狀態的原物叫出來。
但是要記得，遊戲不會更新原物在停滯狀態的位置，
所以它跟被馬力歐拿著到處跑的手中物的位置基本上不一樣了。
當原物從停滯被叫回來，它的位置必須更新到手中物最後的位置。
這個用三個參數XYZ儲存的位置剛好就叫做手中物最後的位置，或簡稱HOLP。
當馬力歐拿著一個物品，HOLP會隨時更新到馬力歐手的座標，
而當馬力歐放開物品，原物會馬上被傳送到HOLP，
並且複製影像消失。
這邊有一個小但關鍵的細節:
為了讓整個過程看起來順暢，原物並不會剛好被傳送到HOLP。
根據馬力歐的位置而定，像是如果馬力歐在地上放開物品，
原物會被送到HOLP的水平位置，
但是垂直位置則是使用馬力歐的位置，
看起來就像是馬力歐把東西放在地上。
多數時候，這整個過程都很順暢且沒什麼問題。
但它並非滴水不漏，並且裡面的小漏洞剛好大到讓一些
聰明細心的玩家把它整個玩壞。
還記得當馬力歐抓住一個物品，馬力歐跟物品會分別切換狀態，
並且由手中物的編號做連結。
在前撲抓跟手中抓物品的時候，所有事情都會同時發生。
但如果是站抓物品，遊戲會在實際切換狀態前兩幀發出切換的訊號。
假如原物這兩幀的空檔取消載入，我們就可以做一些有趣的事。
有幾個方法可以讓這件事發生:
最常見的方法是把一個箱子放置30秒
並在它取消載入前的最後兩幀抓住它，
或是在炸彈爆炸的同時抓住它。
任何能讓原物在馬力歐站抓的那兩幀取消載入的方法都可以達成這個效果，
像是通過載入點，
一個遊戲負責取消載入部分地圖並載入新地圖的觸發點。
遊戲不會更新取消載入的物品，代表原物不會進入停滯狀態。
(不會被標記成被抓的狀態)
但是馬力歐還是會由手中物拿到一個物品編號，
而這個手中物現在連結到一個空的物品欄位，
它可以載入任何新的物品。
由於空的物品欄位裡面沒有東西，
馬力歐的手中物看起來便是隱形或是凍結的，
這反應了原物在被取消載入前的最後狀態。
當新的物品被載入到那個物品欄，
手中物便連結到一個全新的物品，跟原本抓的東西完全沒關係。
這看起來像是我們成功「克隆」了那個新的物品，
但其實還沒成功。
馬力歐只是拿著那個物品的編號(複製影像)
而因為原物沒被設成停滯狀態(隱形的)，
看起來才會像是同時有這兩個物品。
但如果馬力歐把拿著的物品丟出去，
我們可以看到複製影像就會消失，並且原物被傳送到馬力歐附近。
但如果那個新的物品是不能被丟出去的，像是蘑菇，會發生什麼事情?
每一個可以抓的物品都有一段程式處理它被抓，放下跟丟出去的反應。
如果新的那個物品沒有這段程式，它被丟出去的時候什麼都不會做。
原物的行為程式會被刪除，使它的功能再也不能正常運作。
基本上它會卡在同一個地方不動。
當被克隆的物品有產生器的時候這會有很重要的作用。
產生器是用來管理一群物品載入跟取消載入的東西，
這些物品包括一線硬幣，一圈硬幣，蘑菇三人組等等。
當馬力歐離那個壞掉的蘑菇一段距離，它還是會被載入，
但是產生器不會收到訊號，
所以雖然舊的蘑菇還在，
產生器還是會正常載入新的蘑菇，
這樣就成功克隆這個蘑菇了。
因為這個過程會把被克隆物品的行為程式刪除，
克隆有一些限制。
首先，被克隆的物品必須要有產生器，不然它就只能被搬運。
這還是很有用，並且就算那個物品最後沒有被複製，
我們通常還是會把這個技巧叫做克隆。
但最大的限制便是克隆出來的物品沒辦法像原物一樣移動或是做它應該做的事。
幸運的是，馬力歐跟物品的互動跟它的行為程式不直接相關，
所以馬力歐還是可以跟克隆出來的物品互動。
不幸的是，互動過後的物品會經由它的行為程式處理，
所以馬力歐跟克隆出來的物品接觸一次後，
處理跟它互動的程式就會壞掉。
所以雖然馬力歐可以接觸克隆出來的物品，但他只能接觸他一次。
舉個例子，丟出一個硬幣克隆會讓馬力歐收集它，但同時也會
讓它卡在空中，無法再次收集。
丟出一個蘑菇克隆會讓馬力歐馬上被它擊退，
之後它就會凍結在空中且無法接觸，讓這個蘑菇克隆
變得完全沒有用處。
還好還是有變通辦法。如果馬力歐在掉落地夠快時丟出
蘑菇克隆，馬力歐會在他放開克隆時離開它的互動範圍，
他們就不會撞在一起。
之後馬力歐就可以回來在踩他一次，就一次。
所以Pannenkoek其實只要克隆一些蘑菇，掉落時把它們丟出，
之後再回來踩在它們身上彈跳到空島上就好了?
沒那麼簡單。還有一個大問題，
丟出物品克隆的時候，被克隆的物品必須要離馬力歐丟出時的距離
足夠地近，讓那個物品保持載入。
不像停滯狀態的物品，只要馬力歐還抓著它就會被強制維持載入狀態，
克隆物不會被強制維持載入，所以馬力歐離開它的產生器一段距離後，
克隆物就會被取消載入。
雖然在這裡蘑菇三人組可以維持載入，
但在那裏就不能了。
這邊就需要另外一個新的技術:遠端釋放。
感覺像兩個小時前我有提到手中物的最後位置會
根據馬力歐的位置更新，但其實有方法可以防止它更新。
有一些方法可以做到這件事，但是這邊
我們要提的是手中帽子bug。
馬力歐戴上帽子的動畫有兩個階段:
在第一階段，馬力歐把帽子拿在它的手上，
第二階段帽子就會到他的頭上。
馬力歐撿到帽子的時候就會觸發第一階段:
馬力歐拿著帽子，同時播放動畫。
這個時候如果馬力歐檢到第二個帽子，
動畫第一階段播完的時候就會開始播第二階段，但是動畫的時間不會被重設。
結果就是第二階段會被打斷，馬力歐最後則會拿著帽子在手上。
要短時間內戴上兩次帽子可以用傳送點複製帽子，
或是在舊的帽子消失之前再使用一次帽子箱。
這個bug對HOLP有重要的影響，如果馬力歐在手中帽的狀態下
抓住一個物品，那個物品還是會被正常的抓住，
但馬力歐看起來只會抓著他的帽子。
因為馬力歐手中物的動畫沒有顯示，HOLP的位置就不會正常更新。
這就造成HOLP的位置跟馬力歐的位置分開來了，而HOLP的位置
就停在最後它被更新的位置。
舉例，馬力歐在這邊放開一個箱子，然後使用手中帽bug丟出一個炸彈，
那個炸彈會被送到馬力歐放開箱子的那個位置，
因為遊戲認為HOLP在那個地方。
這就是遠端釋放。
雖然有很多複雜的操作跟問題，但這就是Pannenkoek不使用A鍵
就到《炸彈戰場》的空島上去的方法。
首先，他抓住一個爆炸中的炸彈，
拿到一個空的物品欄位。
然後他拿著這個欄位一直到這個位置
放開它把HOLP設定在半空中。
然後他用手中帽bug跟另一個炸彈
從蘑菇三人組複製一個蘑菇。
用遠端釋放，他把蘑菇傳送到HOLP，
然後他就可以過去在踩它。
但是一個蘑菇彈跳不夠，
他需要更多蘑菇來蓋一座到空島的橋。
問題就在這裡，為了把蘑菇放到更遠的地方，
HOLP必須要在更遠的地方，代表馬力歐先要能到那個地方，
所以他要先踩這個蘑菇彈跳過去才能放新的蘑菇。
但要記得，蘑菇克隆只能互動一次，所以馬力歐在上面彈跳放第二個蘑菇的時候，
第一個蘑菇就沒辦法用了。
所以放完第二個蘑菇後，
馬力歐要回來在第一個蘑菇旁邊放第三個蘑菇才能彈到第二個蘑菇上。
這個過程在橋越來越長的時候會指數成長。
這有點像是用二進位數數，1是你放的蘑菇，0是準備要放蘑菇的位置。
橋的長度是所需的1的長度。
所以一個蘑菇長的橋需要一個蘑菇。
兩個蘑菇長的需要3個，三個蘑菇長的需要7個,四個蘑菇長的需要15個。
n個蘑菇長橋的就需要二的n次方-1個蘑菇。
這會造成一些問題，
因為畫面上如果有超過大概40個蘑菇遊戲就會閃退。
所以最長能蓋出的蘑菇橋大約只有5個蘑菇長。
在空島的例子，Pannen用3個蘑菇長的橋，也就是7個蘑菇，
來彈跳過去空島。要拿到紅幣到空島上就好了，
但這個星星還要做一些事情才能拿到。
如果能用蘑菇彈上去就能拿到星星。
有兩個方法可以做到這件事:
第一個是用同樣的策略:
把HOLP放到星星下面，在其他地方遠端釋放蘑菇再用踩它。
但這有一個問題。
因為空島上的飛行帽箱沒辦法用來做手中帽bug，
克隆要空島以外的地方完成，同時HOLP要已經在星星底下。
蘑菇橋只能用一次，所以去空島兩次需要兩座蘑菇橋。
第二個策略是直接在星星下面丟出蘑菇克隆。
幸運的是，空島的這個位置離這群蘑菇夠近，讓它們可以在島上被克隆。
但是不幸的是，馬力歐沒辦法在不被蘑菇撞到的
同時把蘑菇克隆放到星星底下，讓他之後就沒辦法踩它。
在空島上沒辦法用掉落的方式避免撞到蘑菇，但是其實還有另一個方法
可以避免馬力歐撞到克隆物品。
如果馬力歐不能被蘑菇擊退，那能不能讓他先被其他東西擊退?
馬力歐被擊退的時候會強制讓他放開任何他拿著的東西，
同時避免馬力歐撞到這樣放開的蘑菇克隆，所以這個方法聽起來很棒。
但這還是有一個問題:馬力歐需要有東西穰他受傷擊退。
這邊如果你還記得我兩億年前有提到放下物品跟丟出去有一點點不同，
放下物品會把它傳送到HOLP的水平位置跟馬力歐的垂直位置。
通常HOLP會在馬力歐的手附近，這看起來就像是馬力歐把東西
放到它前面的地板上。
但如果HOLP不在馬力歐手的位置，就會有神奇的效果。
遠端放下一個物品會把它放到HOLP的水平位置跟馬力歐的垂直位置，
這個位置可能是一個新的，馬力歐根本到不了的地方。
回到那個炸彈的例子，把炸彈放下會讓它被放到那邊去。
回到【射向空島】，那個星星的位置在一個水平位置跟垂直位置很好分別到達的地方，
但要同時到達就很難了。
Pannenkoek在星星的垂直位置下方放下箱子，
使用手中帽bug，藉由在這裡把炮彈克隆放下，可以把炮彈
傳送到HOLP的水平位置，但在馬力歐的高度。
雖然馬力歐沒有去過空島，但這樣就讓砲彈克隆被傳送到空島上了。
最後馬力歐再克隆一個蘑菇，他可以藉由被砲彈擊退把這個克隆丟出，
同時不會跟這個蘑菇接觸。
然後他就可以踩在蘑菇上彈跳來收集這個星星，
這整個過程沒有用到任何一次A鍵。
你可能會覺得為什麼Pannen不直接遠端釋放一個蘑菇到島上，
而是用了一個砲彈。
因為他沒有辦法可以離克隆蘑菇的位置夠近，同時處在正確的高度位置。
唯一離這個位置夠近的蘑菇是這些蘑菇克隆，
但因為克隆不會取消載入，它們也不會載入，
所以克隆一個克隆是不可能的。
另外，我略過了要怎麼把蘑菇跟砲彈剛好載入到馬力歐
手中的空物品欄位編號。這個問題可以另外拍一部影片來解答。
其實Pannenkoek已經有一部影片講解這件事了。
簡單來說，如果有好幾個物品在同一幀取消載入，
如硬幣圈，蘑菇三人組或是其他物體群，
它們取消載入的順序會是它們載入順序的相反。
只要深入了解物品載入的行為模式跟仔細規劃動作，
就能夠控制是什麼東西載入到馬力歐的手中。
這裡Pannen用的方法其實是反覆嘗試直到他得到想要的結果。
多年以來他一直都是這麼做的，但最後經過長時間的研究，
他終於精通了克隆的技巧。
(後面待翻譯...)
這破天荒的策略是Pannenkoek在A鍵挑戰的前幾個貢獻之一。
不幸的是，雖然這個策略聽起來很扯，但是其實它沒有省下任何A鍵。
Pannenkoek不知道的是，在兩年前，一些日本TAS玩家就已經知道
可以使用龜殼跟很斜的斜坡來獲得很大的向後移動速度，然後直接飛到島上。
實際上Pannenkoek一開始的影片大多數最後的A鍵使用量都跟其他先驅的一樣。
但他還是有推動一些進展。
其中第一個是
《大小島》【Wiggler的紅幣】，受到另一位TAS玩家Plush的啟發，
用一個滑鏟彈跳到這個平台上。
這使得總A鍵使用量降到了207。
另外提一下，之前說2011年的A鍵用量是228，而在2013年是208。
就像我先前提到的，我們很難精準定量早期的A鍵用量，
所以我給了一個最保守的估計。
但是208這個數字是一個可靠的統計數字。
因為那時候已經針對全遊戲的星星做統計，
並且可以溯源到當時已知的所有策略。
228到208的主要進步來源是
《時鐘塔》的【100硬幣星星】跟【時鐘塔頂樓】合起來省了14xA,
以及其他星星的一些小進步。
在【Wiggler的紅幣】之後，Pannenkoek去看了
【彩虹毯紅幣】的舊策略。這個5xA的路線包含
用1xA搭乘這個飛毯到這個平台，
然後用剩下4xA來跑迷宮。
但是Pannen發現可以
重複利用飛毯，只需要這個A就能進迷宮。
經過精巧的路線規劃，這個新的策略只需要2xA就能拿到星星。
又過了幾個沒有進展的星星，這次pannenkoek在
《Whomp的堡壘》有了新進步。
【石板王】是一個相對簡單的星星，
要不用A到堡壘的最上面的最上面蠻簡單的，
但是打王的過程需要在石板王的背上用砸地三次，也就是需要3xA
(砸地要有一定高度，動作本身不用按A)
直到pannen想到把石板王引到升降台那邊，
用升降台來上升到他背上，這樣就可以不使用A來砸地。
不幸的是，以前只要在砸地的第三次同時就可以馬上拿到星星，
用這個策略代表需要找另一個方法不用A拿星星。
Pannen找不到，所以這個星星就先以1xA收場，省了2個A鍵。
再來他來到了《高高山》，但他很快地去《大小島》一趟來
丟這個Chuckya，然後才去《高高山》的【登山】省了兩個A鍵。
首先他用傳點複製帽子，觸發手中帽bug
複製一隻蘑菇，然後把他丟出去。
我們可以看到，蘑菇消失了，但它去了哪裡?
這個嘛，它直接出現在星星下面了!
這就是Pannen先去《大小島》一趟的原因。
HOLP只會在遊戲開始的時後被初始化一次。
在那之後，HOLP只會在
馬力歐拿著物品的時候更新，其他時候都不會變動，
包含切換關卡的時候。
馬力歐在丟《大小島》丟Chuckya的時候就把HOLP設在這個位置了。
同樣的座標在《高高山》對應到山頂，星星正下方。
所以用遠端釋放，Pannen可以在下面把蘑菇放到上面那個地方。
有一個細節我剛才略過去了。
馬力歐是怎麼不用A上去山上這個地方的?
用一種叫做「單幀行走」的新技巧。
馬力歐可以跑上一些斜坡，但有些斜坡會讓他不斷減速直到速度變成負的，
這時候他就會趴著滑下來。
但是如果馬力歐的速度夠慢，只要把搖桿從
中立位置向前推，即使在很斜的斜坡上，馬力歐也會在第一幀加速。
所以只要快速的前後移動搖桿就可以走上斜坡。
這個方法省了一個A鍵，而山頂的蘑菇克隆省了另一個A。
另外《高高山》還有其他三個星星需要經過這裡，
【猴子籠的秘密】【橋邊美景】跟
【高高山100硬幣】。
單幀行走可以三個星星各省下一個A。
這個發現使得《高高山》成為第二個0xA拿到全部星星的關卡。
不久後，Pannen研究了各種星星，主要集中在地下室的關卡,
並對一些既有策略做了小改進。
首先他在鋼鐵帽關
從一個水晶前撲受身讓馬力歐可以0xA上到按鈕上，
然後他在《沙漠》裡找到了一些聰明的策略。
他用龍捲風跟fly guy來拿到紅幣,
然後他在岩手上彈跳來拿到星星。
他還是得在這裡跳一次
才能離開升降台進入戰鬥。
再來他改進了《海盜灣》
把【海盜灣紅幣】跟【海盜灣100硬幣】一起收集，
以及只用B鍵游到
地下洞窟藍幣的位置。
然後回到《沙漠》，他複製一個箱子。
使用遠端釋放把他放在另一個箱子的邊邊，讓它在
取消載入的同時爆炸，這樣箱子就會無限噴金幣。
接著是《鬼屋》，他用一個策略在四個星星各省下1xA。
他把這些飛書引誘到他想要的地方，
然後踩在兩個飛書上，省下一個到樓頂的A鍵。
這在【陽台的大鬼】跟【秘密房間的眼球】都能省下1xA。
另外他使用大鬼來幫助他到這個箱子上，然後拿到星星，
全程不需要按A。
踩在飛書上彈跳也讓他可以不用A拿到這個紅幣，
這讓【鬼屋紅幣】省了1xA，同時也
讓不按A能拿到的硬幣數量從99到101，
代表【鬼屋100硬幣】也能0xA拿到了。
在《迷宮洞窟》可以用一個類似的方法來在【迷宮洞窟100硬幣】省下1xA。
但這裡改成是踩蝙蝠來打死snifit。
在這一堆小改進之後，Pannenkoek覺得是時候來另一場革新了。
這次不是在遊戲上，而是技術上的革新。
他從Project 64改為使用Mupen。
他終於可以告別破爛的免費試用版
螢幕錄影軟體，使用Mupen 64的AVI軟體內擷取。
但最大的改進是在軟體的TAS方便性。
Project 64只有隨時存檔功能，
所以Pannenkoek到現在為止的影片都是實時錄製的，
需要的時候暫停存檔。
Mupen 64則可以每幀播放，監控參數，跟其他一些
製作TAS時很關鍵的功能。
同時他也開始把影片跟輸入按鍵一起存下來，
這樣他就能隨時回去改進，跟他的同好分享，以及讓8年後的歷史學家
回顧並記錄這段這些歷史。
於是繼日本TAS玩家之後，
清晰的30FPS A鍵挑戰影片第二次出現了。
有了這個高品質的配置，他感覺可以來挑戰遊戲中
最聞風喪膽的關卡了，《時鐘塔》。
首先他把【搭乘指針】降到0xA，
他找到了用爬上這堆旋轉平台的方法，
用砸地撞上牆讓馬力歐暈眩。
在撞牆動畫播放的時候馬力歐不會從旋轉平台上滑下來,
動畫時間足夠讓平台轉夠多使馬力歐可以站在上面。
Alkhdaniel使用一個類似的策略，先用1xA
來獲得一點高度，但是Pannen的新方法可以完全不用A鍵上去。
這個新策略不只在【搭乘指針】省A鍵，同時也
是對關卡裡每個星星的改進。
這讓【時鐘塔紅幣】從1xA變成0xA。
他把【跳進籠子】從7xA減到4xA，
【移動平台】從11xA減到7xA，
以上配合精準的Heave-ho上拋來達成。
用以上所有策略搭配更精準的平台移動把
【時鐘塔100硬幣星星】加上【時鐘塔頂樓】從15xA減到9xA。
最後，【洞與鐘擺】也從6xA減到了4xA，
搭配紅幣旋轉平台與更好的跳躍方式來節省另一個A。
在他拆除《時鐘塔》的同時，Pannen也順便在研究《天上的庫巴》。
原本13x的紀錄已經相當不錯了，但Pannen發現有三個地方可以改進。
首先，這裡精準的滑鏟可以讓馬力歐
繞過障礙物。再來另一個精準的前撲受身
讓他可以越過這些平台，最後他引誘蘑菇
讓它下來被踩來省下第三個A鍵,總共剩10xA。
Pannenkoek的下一站是《可怕的港口》，
這裡他的第一個改進就是一個大的:
這裡他把【可怕的港口紅幣】，A鍵挑戰的惡夢
從10xA減到了3.5xA。
等等，這到底是什麼意思?
這裡可以簡單的解釋一下。
請讓我介紹0.5A鍵的意思。
有水的關卡對A鍵挑戰來說帶來了一個特別的問題，
因為要游泳需要一直不斷按A。
如果不按A，馬力歐的水下移動方式就非常受限。
他只能慢慢下沉，或是在接近表面的時候慢慢上浮。
他可以按B抓東西，這讓他可以稍微向前移動。
或是如果他抓到一個龜殼
他就能一段時間內稍微動的快一些。
但是有時馬力歐可以拿著物品游泳，
等等就會需要這個情況。
這樣B鍵就不能用來游泳，
因為馬力歐會把東西丟掉而不是游泳。
有一個解決辦法:
如果按著A，馬力歐就會像這樣游泳，拿著東西的時候也一樣。
但這需要A鍵被按住，所以這需要1xA，對嗎?
假設只看當下情況，對，這需要1xA。
但假設現在是從全遊戲的角度來看，
你可以在其他需要按A的星星按A，然後就按著不放。
這樣這兩個A鍵就會合併成一個很長的A鍵，
達成許多不同的功能。
所以他為什麼叫做3.5xA呢?
這個點五的表記法代表一個狀況的兩面性。
假如只看這個星星，我們就把A鍵使用量進位成4xA，
假如是把整個遊戲的星星串聯就捨去成3xA。
因為它可以使用前一個星星的A鍵。
3.5xA在全遊戲比4xA鍵好，
但在單顆星星比3xA爛，所以放.5在中間感覺蠻有道理的。
現在解釋清楚.5的部分了，那麼Pannen是怎麼把這個星星改進這麼多的呢?
首先他先從底部抓一個龜殼，然後把它帶到水面。
如果馬力歐拿著龜殼游泳的時候龜殼的使用時間到了，或是他上岸，
龜殼就會消失。
這段時間沒有很長，讓龜殼在正常遊戲中沒什麼用。
但是這邊是有趣的地方:龜殼只會在馬力歐帶著他游泳時消失，
但瑪力歐還是可以把它丟掉。
馬力歐把龜殼丟掉的幾個幀內時候，他其實還是拿著它，
但他不算拿著龜殼游泳。所以只要把龜殼丟掉的同時上浮把動作中斷，
馬力歐就不會把龜殼摧毀，然後就可以拿著他直到永遠。
現在他就可以帶龜殼到任何地方。
然而，這個龜殼現在的功能消失，變成一個普通的物品了。
為了帶著這個龜殼去其他地方，馬力歐需要按著A來游泳。
這裡就是為什麼需要額外的0.5xA。
所以他到底要帶著龜殼去哪裡?
《可怕的港口》被中間的隧道分成兩個大房間。
隧道中間有一個載入點，馬力歐跨過的時候會切換房間。
這個切換的動作包含取消載入第一個房間所有物品然後載入第二個房間，
來省遊戲記憶體。
所以這邊馬力歐如果跨過載入點時拿著
會被取消載入的物品，像是龜殼，能做什麼?
當然是克隆!
取消載入龜殼之後，馬力歐拿著空物品欄位，現在可以載入
一些奇怪的物品。一樣經過一些計畫，
Pannenkoek把一根爬竿載入到馬力歐手中，
這樣他就可以拿著他並丟到某個地方。
因為這邊爬竿沒有載入器，所以這是一個克隆不會複製東西的例子。
只是把爬竿帶去別的地方。
所以Pannen要注意他帶走的是哪根爬竿，
確定他不是拿到之後需要爬的那根。
把爬竿放掉之後，他就可以用1xA爬到上面的平台。
從這裡開始就是要不按A繞過爬竿，
搭配一些簡單的前撲跟抓取。
另一個A是用來到最遠的那根爬竿，
拿到紅幣後在掉回水中。
還有一個A跟第二個爬竿克隆用來拿到最後一個紅幣。
helped by the fact that these poles are actually
longer than their visual model suggests. All that
was left was the star, which unfortunately
wasn’t easy to reach either. But thankfully,
just like any other object, stars can also be
cloned! Remember that releasing an object clone
physically moves that object to the new location.
Clones aren’t just broken copies of an object,
they are the actual object. They only become
a copy if a spawner spawns the original object
again. So, the star that Mario is collecting is
absolutely real. He’s able to collect it remotely
without any additional A presses, for a total
of 3, plus having to hold A at the beginning.
For the rest of Dire, Dire Docks, the
half A press shell swimming strategy
to clone a star was relevant for most
stars, aside from Manta Ray’s Reward,
which didn’t require any A presses, and the
100-coin star, which, for now, Pannen left
alone. Also, Chests in the Current did require
A swimming as well, not because of cloning,
but because of the whirlpool forcing Mario to
swim at least a little bit more efficiently.
This brought down the total A press count by
4, because 4 stars that were previously listed
as needing one A press could now be completed
simply by leeching off a previous A press instead.
But the half A press was not going to be limited
only to Dire, Dire Docks. It proved useful in
Wing Mario over the Rainbow as well. Holding A has
more benefits, like falling slower while twirling,
which, remember, was already known
over a decade earlier. But also,
holding A allows Mario to fall slower with the
wing cap, and to kick by tapping the B button.
Kicking can help Mario get up steep slopes,
although frame-walking obsoletes that one. Here,
however, falling slower with the wing cap allows
Mario to reach the bottom platform to shoot out
from the cannon. Because this star still requires
two cannon shots, the A press count was now 2.5.
At this point, aside from a few stray stars,
the only levels left for Pannenkoek to explore
were Snowman’s Land and Wet-Dry World. Snowman’s
Land was already nearly figured out before Pannen
even touched it, but Wet-Dry world totalled 18
A presses, nearly half of which were for the red
coins star alone. So, there was a lot of potential
for improvement. Pannen started with Secrets in
the Shallows & Sky. Note that because entering
levels is also an implicit part of the challenge,
you can’t just enter Wet-Dry World any way you
want. The initial water level depends on the
height at which Mario enters the painting, so with
no jumps, the only available initial water level
is the lowest one. Thankfully, there is a warp
to the cannon platform at the top of the stage,
and there are Heave-hos that can
flip Mario up to higher levels.
Pannen used a combination of those to get
most of the secrets, but the last one was
a bit trickier. The previous strategy
was to use a cannon shot to reach it,
but instead, he got a helping hand from
Chuckya. He manipulated the random number
generated by the game, or RNG value, to be
favourable so that Chuckya would throw Mario
directly onto the wooden bridge, which let
him access the final secret in 0 A presses.
He used the same strategy to save an A
press in Express Elevator - Hurry Up!,
and the 100-coin star. Top o’ the Town was
still problematic because despite being able
to get all the way to breaking the box in 0 A
presses, he had to jump to get the star. The
old strategy from 2008 was to use a cannon shot to
go directly on top of the box and ground pound it,
which also took one A press. But since
activating the cannon took an additional
A press that was not counted at the time,
this new method was an indirect improvement.
But the real problematic stars were Quick Race
through Downtown, and the red coin star. Those
were sitting at 5 and 8 A presses respectively
before Pannenkoek had a crack at them.
The solution he found for each
of them is pretty complex,
so let’s start with Quick Race through Downtown.
When Mario throws Chuckya, it will explode into
5 coins upon landing. This explosion happens
based on Chuckya’s state of being thrown. Here,
Mario throws Chuckya and falls off the ledge at
the same time, which lets him catch up to it and
intercept it while it’s falling down. Chuckya then
grabs Mario in mid-air, which changes its state
from being thrown to holding Mario. Therefore,
when it lands on the ground, it no longer
wants to explode, which effectively brings
Chuckya down to this level. From there, Pannen
abuses object collision priority and uses Chuckya
to push Mario inside of the block and throw
Chuckya through the wall. Immediately after,
he gets caught by Chuckya again, and both
of them fall down into the pipe below,
where Mario can retrieve Chuckya and
carry it around in the water. There are
other ways to bring Chuckya here, but this
clever method uses no A presses to do so.
Once Mario is holding Chuckya underwater, he needs
to swim. He could do that simply by holding A,
but unfortunately, that doesn’t work
after pressing B to grab an object,
so he actually needs to press the A button
once. But from there, he has a hold of an
object and the tunnel contains a loading zone
that switches between the main area and the
downtown part of Wet-Dry World, and so he can
clone the Quick Race through Downtown star. Note
that the cloning of a star can only be done if
the star is already out there and collectable,
so the same can’t be done for
something like the red coins,
for instance. But just like that, he managed to
get that star from 5 down to only one A press.
The Red coin star was definitely the most
challenging because it posed multiple problems
at once. To access most red coins, Mario needs
to break a box, which he can only do out of the
water. However, if the water level is low, then
he needs a lot of A presses to reach the higher
platforms. So, he both needs the water level to
be high so that he can navigate without using A,
but also to be low, so that he can break the
boxes the coins are in. If he lowers the water
to break a box, he needs a way to raise it back
up, and the only crystal that raises the water
is way up there, inaccessible on low water
without jumping a bunch of times. This web of
restrictions is nearly impossible to navigate. But
if it’s nearly impossible, it’s not impossible.
But there was a price to pay. In his
own words, that star was a total pain
to record and edit. And you know what? I
believe him: the strategy takes 14 hours
to execute. Breaking down how all of it works
would be too gigantic of a task. So let’s do it.
The water in Wet-Dry World can be raised or
lowered using these crystals, but it’s not
the only way in which it moves. If you pay close
attention, you can see that even when it’s at a
fixed height, the water level bobs up and down by
a significant amount. This is not purely visual:
the actual water level follows a sinusoidal
function with an amplitude of 20 units and a
period of 128 frames. In other words,
the water has a median level and it
deviates from that median by up 20 units on
a cycle that repeats every 4 seconds or so.
The downtown area’s water level is independent
from the main area. When Mario goes from downtown
to the main area, the water level is preserved
for when he comes back. But here’s the key thing:
the current water level is saved, and then used
as the median water level when Mario comes back.
Therefore, if Mario loads the downtown area, and
unloads it when the water is above the median,
when he comes back, the new median
will be here, and the water level
will rise and dip 20 units around that
new line. If you repeat this process,
you can raise the water level arbitrarily
high, 20 units at a time. If you do the
opposite and leave when it’s below the
median, you can lower it the same way.
However, this is easier said than done. The
loading zone is in the middle of an underwater
tunnel, which means Mario cannot simply stay
here and swim in circles around the loading
zone to raise or lower the water as he pleases.
He needs to get some air from time to time. So,
the water in the main area needs to be at
its lowest level. To access this corner,
you can simply slide along this ledge, carefully
keeping Mario on with a precise angle and stick
movement. And now, Mario has just barely enough
time to lower the water level once before he has
to rush back and get some air. So, this process is
extremely tedious. To get this part done without
actually repeating all of this work over and over
for days, Pannenkoek figured out a way to make
a sequence of inputs that would be loopable, and
repeated it for however many iterations he needed.
After lowering the water 26 times, he could
finally enter downtown. By now, the water
was low enough that he could get some air inside
the tunnel itself, and he could go and break this
first box. But as you can see, this grate prevents
him from lowering the water any more than that,
because it would block access to downtown if he
did. So, Pannen has to raise the water instead.
He does so for 4 hours. In that time,
the water level is raised 398 times. Now,
the water level is far above the top of
the stage. At this point, it’s so high up,
that when Mario touches the low crystal, he
has time to swim up to a higher platform before
the water level catches up. Or at least, he
would, if he had enough air. Unfortunately,
B swimming is so slow that Mario would
drown before he got there. But thankfully,
coins restore energy. By grabbing
a few coins along the way, Pannen
was able to extend his underwater time just
enough to make this genius route possible.
After this high anxiety swim up to the
top, Mario is now high up in 0 A presses,
while the water is low, which lets him break
boxes, and he has access to the high crystal, so
he can raise the water back up and go back to the
main area if needed. He activates the high crystal
and dives down to one of the boxes to break it
just before the water catches up. From there,
he only needs to get some air and he can go back
and repeat this process again to break more boxes.
And that’s what he does. For another 4 hours,
he raises the water 366 times and repeats the
same process. However, coins are limited, so he
has to become more and more creative with how
he uses them to buy himself more underwater time.
The longer he has to go out of his way to get more
coins, the more coins he needs to get to offset
that extra time. This time, he has just barely
enough time to break this second box. Then, he
goes back and raises the water another 376 times,
uses up the last few yellow coins he has
to his disposal, and breaks one more box.
In one final trip, he raises the water 154 times,
and then, with almost no coins left to keep him
alive, collects all the red coins that he left
behind specifically for this moment, and he
breaks off the last few boxes and gets the star.
All of that in 0 A presses, and only 14 hours.
Even among all the cloning he had done, this
single star was probably the most intense strategy
Pannenkoek had pulled off up to this point.
It also saved an astonishing 8 A presses in
a single go, making it to this day the largest
single improvement in the challenge’s history.
And he wasn’t even done yet.
But he was almost done. He took a look at the
red coin stars in the first two Bowser stages
and found some improvements in them. In Bowser
in the Dark World, he lured a Goomba down here
so he could bounce on it, and used framewalking
to tilt a bridge 90º and go up to a red coin,
saving three A presses in total to bring
it down to 2. In Bowser in the Fire Sea,
he was able to use a Bob-omb to clone the star,
saving the two A presses normally
required to get up to it and grab it.
In the final level he still had to go through,
Snowman’s Land, only two A presses remained,
and he was able to save one of them. He got
In the Deep Freeze from 1 to 0 A presses,
using Koopa shell hyperspeed. This
had already been used before by the
Japanese TASers, but I glossed over
it until now. Here’s how it works.
The way speed on slopes is handled is fairly
simple. When Mario is moving on a slope,
his speed is calculated in such a way that
he moves the same distance along that slope
than if he were on flat ground. So, with
a speed of 30 on flat ground, Mario will
move 30 units forward. But on a 30º slope,
Mario will move by 30 units along the slope,
which translates to 15 units up and 26 units
forward. The way the game does this is that
it factors Mario’s speed by the cosine of the
slope he’s on to determine his lateral movement,
and then moves him up or down to match the
new height of the floor. This effective speed,
which is always equal to or lower than Mario’s
real speed, is called the de facto speed.
Now, this method works flawlessly when Mario
is running parallel to the direction of the
slope. But if he’s moving perpendicularly
to it, this speed reduction no longer makes
sense. Nonetheless, it is still applied, no
matter which direction Mario is moving in.
This is why he appears to slow down when
going from flat ground to sloped ground,
despite keeping a similar speed. And this is the
mechanic that makes shell hyperspeed possible.
Mario rides the shell up a very steep slope
and angles himself sideways. When Mario tries
to ride up a steep slope, he’ll rapidly lose
speed and even slide back down the slope. But
if he’s angled right, something interesting can
happen. The backwards acceleration is the same,
so long as Mario is facing up the slope, even
if he barely is. Because the slope is so steep,
his de facto speed is a tiny fraction of his
real speed, so he basically stays in place,
despite his increasingly high speed. So, by
facing ever so slightly up very steep slopes,
he can accumulate over 200 negative speed,
about 7 times more than regular walking speed.
All he needs to do next is to redirect that speed
to propel himself to the star in 0 A presses.
There were only a few stars left. Rainbow
Ride 100 coins was moderately easy with
the techniques Pannen had developed.
After one A press to reach the cruiser,
he was able to get a hold of an exploding
bob-omb and clone 51 coins to reach 100
without having to go around the whole
course. By the way, a quick detail:
while there are other bob-ombs in Rainbow Ride,
only the one on the cruiser is close enough to
coins to clone them. The ones at the bottom
of the maze are too far away from any coins.
Dire, Dire Docks 100 coins was a little
more complicated. Using the shell method
that he used to clone poles and a star,
he could clone coins, but there is a more
efficient method. Instead of cloning coins one
by one, he could clone an entire ring of coins!
Like we’ve seen before, rings of
coins are handled by an intangible,
invisible object called a spawner. On top of
deciding when to load or unload a group of coins,
it also keeps track of which of
its coins have been collected,
so it can stay consistent when you load
the coins in and out of memory. However,
just like every other object, coin ring spawners
can be cloned. Here’s how the process works.
The cloning part works exactly the same. But
to clone an object, you need to be holding a
vacant slot for it to load into. The problem with
spawners is that they are loaded when you enter
the level, and they always stay loaded no matter
how far Mario is from them. There is, however,
one exception. If a level has multiple segments
separated by a loading zone, such as Wet-Dry World
or Dire, Dire Docks, then it is possible to load
and unload a spawner. When a spawner is cloned,
it will simply look like an invisible object.
Just like any other object not meant to be thrown,
once the clone is released, it will cease to
function properly. So, it will also stop handling
the loading and unloading of the coin ring. If
a coin spawner clone is released, its associated
coin ring will no longer load when Mario goes
near it. But if the spawner clone is released
while the coins are already loaded, then they
will no longer unload when Mario goes far away.
Also, when a coin from a coin ring is
cloned, because its behaviour is broken,
it will be unable to send a signal to its
spawner to indicate that it’s been collected,
so the spawner will spawn it again when Mario
goes near, thus duplicating the coin. This
works exactly the same way if the spawner is
the one being cloned. The coins in the ring
can be collected, and they will send a signal
to the spawner that they no longer should be
loaded the next time the ring is loaded, but the
spawner will be unable to receive the message. So,
when Mario reloads the area through the
loading zone, the reloaded spawner will have
no memory of the coins being collected,
and it will spawn them all over again.
This method can be used specifically in Dire,
Dire Docks to duplicate whole rings of coins
at once instead of one at a time, significantly
speeding up the process. This is what Pannen did:
he got 56 extra coins from 7 coin ring spawner
clones and got the 100-coin star in 0.5 A presses.
In Tiny-Huge Island, Pannen got Make
Wiggler Squirm from 1 down to 0 A presses,
by riding a shell up the mountain
and clipping in using Chuckya.
Around this time, he also found an improvement
in Wet-Dry World, in Express Elevator - Hurry
up! He found that by raising the water level,
he was able to hold A and swim onto the elevator
instead of jumping to it. The timing for it
is very tight, but it is indeed possible.
This reduced the A press count from 1 to 0.5,
because he needed A to be held and not pressed.
At this point, Pannenkoek was nearing the end of
his journey through every star in the game. He
realized that he also needed to account for all
the A presses necessary to navigate the castle
between all the levels. So, he dedicated a video
to all of them. Most of it is pretty trivial,
and like I discussed before, the total
comes up to 23 if you’re being efficient.
He found one precise sideflip to grab
the ledge to Rainbow Ride on one side,
and Wing Mario over the Rainbow on the other,
which brought the total down to 21. He proved
that the 5 stars available inside the castle
itself were all obtainable in 0 A presses.
And he completed his meticulous run through the
complete A Button Challenge in Whomp’s Fortress,
by doing Fall Onto the Caged Island the same way
the Japanese TASers did it a few years prior.
Finally, after all this work, Pannenkoek,
with some help from Plush, managed to cut
the 120-star A press count nearly in half,
from 208 to 116. But we lost track of time
during this epic journey. How many years have
passed? 3 years, 4 years? Maybe even 5 years?
How about two months. That’s
right. This entire revolution
of the Super Mario 64 A Button
Challenge took two months from
beginning to end. And the best part?
Pannenkoek was only getting started.
From August 25th to October 26th, 2013,
Pannenkoek2012 completely reinvented the A
Button Challenge, almost entirely by himself. His
unprecedented dedication and endless creativity,
further enabled by a deep knowledge
of the game and its infinite quirks,
allowed him to come up with ideas and
strategies far more advanced than anything
that had been done before. Such stellar work
was bound to be noticed. And sure enough,
it was noticed. By pretty much the entire
speedrunning community at the time. Some people
were interested in more than just watching. From
this point on, Pannenkoek was no longer alone.
As soon as he completed his pass
through every star in the game,
Pannen moved on to other challenges, such as
no buttons allowed, and no joystick allowed,
where the only easy movement option is punching
and jumping to slowly inch forward. The A Button
Challenge project cooled down a bit, since there
was little incentive to go back to it unless
something new had been discovered. He didn’t
revisit the challenge until late March 2014,
when he found that enemy luring strategies,
which had been used to some extent before,
had more potential than he
had given them credit for.
In Hazy Maze Cave, swoopers fly on a
perfectly horizontal plane after their
initial takeoff. He used that to his advantage
by luring a swooper all the way to this slope,
which raised it enough that he could bounce on it
and reach this ledge to A-Maze-ing Emergency Exit,
cutting one A press in the process. The same could
be done for Navigating the Toxic Maze, which is
just the other alcove to the right, but that one
was a bit more involved. Because there’s no mole
here, he instead had to align three swoopers at
three increasing heights, all set up by luring
them to various slopes, so he could reach the
higher ledge. This posed a very interesting
logistical issue. Pannenkoek used his buddy, pen
and paper, to solve and illustrate the puzzle.
Enemy luring could also be applied with boos.
While he did use a bookend bounce to reach
this red coin before, the other red coin in this
room still required an A press. But with clever
manipulation, Pannen got Boos to line up under it
and bounced on them to reach the coin. However,
because he needed kicks to get a bit of starting
height, which require A to be held, he was only
able to get Big Boo’s Haunt red coins from 2 down
to 1.5 A presses. But remember, because full game
runs round down half A presses, this was still
good to lower the total A press count to 113.
In the meantime, Pannenkoek also made a brand
new glitch discovery: Transport cloning.
Objects that can move around,
like goombas and bob-ombs,
have collision detection amongst
themselves. We’ve already seen
how this can lead to strange behaviour
while holding a bob-omb. The function
that handles the result of these collisions
is the key to understand transport cloning.
Two goombas run into each other. Their respective
positions cause their hitboxes to overlap,
so the game attempts to reposition them. First,
it finds the relative distance between them. Then,
it finds the midpoint on this line, and
finally, it moves each goomba along the
line from that point by their radius,
so their hitboxes end up tangential to
each other. In the more generic case of two
objects with different radii, the line is
divided with the same ratio as the radii of the
objects. When the two objects are repositioned,
their hitboxes will always be tangential
at that point along the line. While such
a scenario is technically possible, by far
the most common case involves two goombas,
so they are placed at the exact halfway
point between their original positions.
The transport cloning glitch happens when a
goomba clone is released while the original
is currently colliding with another goomba. The
key reason why it happens is that the goomba is
warped to the HOLP after the collision
is detected, but before the collision
handling function is run. When the function
finds the relative distance between them,
what should be a small distance ends up being
arbitrarily large. After that, the game finds
the midpoint and places each goomba one radius
away in each direction, so the result is that
both goombas are warped to the point halfway
between their original positions and the HOLP.
Another important detail is that
this repositioning is only done
along the horizontal plane. The vertical
position is completely unaffected. So,
if the HOLP is at a different vertical position,
both goombas will end up halfway to the HOLP in
the X and Z coordinates, but while the goomba
clone ends up at the HOLP’s Y coordinate, the
other goomba remains at its original Y position.
This glitch allowed for two major breakthroughs
in cloning capabilities. It was now possible,
albeit very restrictive and convoluted, to release
a clone at a location otherwise inaccessible,
without the situational hat in hand glitch.
Although, because Mario needs to be close
enough to the goomba trio for them
to be loaded in the first place,
there would be very few situations where
transport cloning actually enabled new
clone locations. The most valuable
benefit was the ability to release
the clone just far enough away from Mario
that he doesn’t immediately bump into it.
Pannenkoek figured that this new technique
would prove useful in Bowser in the Sky. Despite
Pannen’s hard work, that stage was still sitting
at 10 A presses. First, he found that luring a
goomba to the edge of this bridge barely allowed
him to skip past that gap without using A. Next,
he found a use for transport cloning. He released
a clone here while these two goombas over there
were running into each other. This warped both
goombas halfway to Mario, with the clone partly
in the ground because of Mario’s lower position.
Afterwards, he used the fact that goomba clones do
still have collision with other goombas. He guided
a goomba to push the clone all the way to the
other side, where Mario could bounce on it after
getting the final red coin, saving an A press.
Pannen was not done in this level. His next
endeavour was to save the A press needed to
jump into the pipe to the Bowser fight. The main
issue here was that to bring a goomba clone all
the way to the pipe, he would need to be able to
get there while holding an object. The closest
bob-omb to clone with is all the way down there,
and because holding an object severely hinders
Mario’s movement options, that meant Pannen
needed many more clones to cross small gaps
that would otherwise be trivial. So, while he
only needed a single goomba clone at the pipe,
the many gaps along the way basically acted as
one big deconstructed goomba bridge of length
7. At 127 goombas, that’s way too much to make
this a viable strategy. And that’s before even
considering the fact that without the hat in
hand glitch and remote release, there was no
way he could release all of these clones without
interacting with them. It seemed impossible.
Until he found something new. As
it turns out, on any given frame,
Mario can only interact with a single object at
a time. If Mario is colliding with more than one
goomba at the same time, whichever comes first in
the processing order is the one that is handled,
and the other collisions will be
ignored. And here’s the key part:
when a clone’s interaction status
is broken and it becomes intangible,
Mario still technically interacts with it
when they collide, even if nothing happens.
The processing order of a group of clones is
the same as the order they were generated in.
So, if Mario releases a goomba clone and bumps
into it, he can then come back and release a new
clone inside of the first clone’s hitbox.
Because Mario is touching the first clone,
this is the interaction that is being handled.
But because that clone is now in a broken state,
nothing comes out of this interaction. Although
he is also colliding with the second clone,
this collision is ignored. So, he
can come back and bounce on the
part of the second clone’s hitbox that
doesn’t overlap with the first clone,
and he has successfully released a useable clone
without remote release nor transport cloning.
There are two caveats. First, this
method does require one clone to
use as a sacrifice to place another clone.
But once the blood tribute has been paid,
older broken clones that were productive
can allow Mario to release newer clones at
no additional cost. Second, the interaction
priority goes both ways: Mario can’t bounce
on a goomba if he’s busy interacting with
another goomba. He needs to release that
second goomba in such a way that there’s a
portion of its hitbox that’s sticking out of
the first goomba’s hitbox. This tiny section
becomes the second goomba’s effective hitbox.
So, this new find was great to place clones at
arbitrary locations, but what about the problem
of having to clone over a hundred goombas when the
game can only render about 40 at once? That one
was solved thanks to transport cloning and clone
pushing. Goombas needed for the fourth step of the
bridge could be released remotely, then pushed
into position by other goombas. This cut the
use of the second and third steps of the bridge by
half. Finally, the last step of the bridge was the
goomba next to the pipe, and it could be bounced
on without having to go and rebuild the rest of
the goomba bridge again, cutting the total number
of clones in half once more. Pannen’s complex plan
balanced convenience and minimizing the number
of clones used. In total, 61 goomba clones ended
up being used for this A press save, plus two
more for the final red coin. This stretched
the game to its very limit, and he ran into
many crashes while TASing this stage, but with
the right camera angles to minimize the amount of
goombas on screen at once, it was indeed possible.
Finally, one last improvement was made in Bowser
in the Sky. But this time, there was something
different. It was not made by Pannenkoek,
but by someone new. His name was Gaehne D.
Gaehne D. started watching Pannen’s
videos even before the A Button Challenge,
and he had grown fascinated by them. He messaged
Pannenkoek through the YouTube inbox system,
and after some back and forth, they started
bouncing ideas for improving the A Button
Challenge. One of those ideas Gaehne D. brought
to the table was a very precise double jump
kick to clear the first two platforms in a
single A press instead of two. After a lot
of testing helped by another guy by the name of
Wizdoodle, this A press save was proven possible,
bringing down Bowser in the Sky from 10 A
presses down to 6 over the course of a few weeks.
Around that same time, another A press was saved,
this time in Jolly Roger Bay. Through the Jet
Stream had always been fairly straightforward:
one A press to break the metal cap box,
and one A press to jump into the star with the
metal cap. But Pannen found that the first one
could be skipped thanks to an old technique
that I haven’t discussed yet: pause buffering.
When Mario dives with B, as soon as he hits the
ground, he can do a dive recover, either with B or
A. If he’s on a steep enough slope, he actually
hits the ground on the very next frame after
he dives. As soon as he does, though, he very
quickly loses forward momentum. So, each frame
spent sliding after a dive takes out a big chunk
of speed. In normal circumstances, you could dive
with B on one frame, and press A to recover on the
next, that’s not a particularly alluring strategy
here. Because both the dive and the dive recover
have to be done with B, there has to be at least
one frame where B is released between them, which
causes Mario to lose part of his speed. But while
the game is paused, the physics engine doesn’t
advance, yet controller inputs are still being
read. So, by pausing the game while B is released,
Mario can dive on one frame, pause and release B,
unpause and repress B, and recover on the next
frame. This let him keep all of his forward speed,
which was just enough to make it onto
the metal cap box and save an A press.
In Hazy Maze Cave, for Metal Head Mario Can
Move, Gaehne D. came up with another enemy lure,
this time with a scuttlebug to skip
one of the gaps and save an A press.
Meanwhile though, Pannenkoek was working on
something far more advanced. He theorized
something quite insane, in Tick Tock Clock: what
if you could skip the final A press of Timed
Jumps on Moving Bars? This would be incredibly
challenging, because while there are bob-ombs at
the very bottom of the stage, there is nothing
useful to clone with them. The star is encased
in a solid cage, with no features around it
that could be used to- wait, what? You can
simply dive recover into it? Oops, well I guess
that one slipped through the cracks somehow.
The date is now May 2014. Pannen’s next target
is Bowser in the Fire Sea. When getting the red
coins, Mario has to climb the pole twice, because
this coin forces him to fall back down. The only
way to get off the pole and onto the higher
platform is to jump off of it. Or is it? In
the first round trip, yes, definitely, there’s no
possible way around it. But after getting up once,
the entire level is unlocked, which contains
bob-ombs! Pannen carried an unloaded bob-omb
all the way back down here, where he could clone
one of the lower goombas. Using transport cloning,
he was able to safely release a clone right
next to the pole. So that would allow him to
drop off from the pole using Z and bounce to the
platform, right? If only it were that simple.
When Mario drops off from a pole, he has barely
any horizontal momentum. So little, in fact,
that one goomba bounce isn’t even enough to
cross this minuscule distance. Using more
clones didn’t help either because he couldn’t
even place them low enough for it to work. He
had to resort to something better: setting
Mario on fire. Burning Mario actually has a
very useful component to it: it makes him
do a little hop forward. This is actually
enough to reach the platform from the pole.
The only problem is finding a way to burn
Mario at the top of the pole. Luckily,
fire spitters are there to save the day.
These fire bars are made up of 15 individual
flames, each taking up one object slot. When the
fire comes out, all of these flames are loaded,
then unloaded as they stop burning. If Mario is
holding a vacant object slot when the flames
come out, he can end up holding a flame clone.
To release it, however, Pannenkoek couldn’t use
transport cloning, because nothing can push fire,
so he had to use the old knockback strategy by
positioning a goomba at the right spot. Finally,
he also had to place more goomba clones so that
he could bounce from the elevator to this spot,
so that the flame would be placed high
enough for this strategy to work. After
falling down to get the red coin, he
dismounted the pole by getting burned,
and he managed to get back up without an
A press. This meant the only A press left
in this level was the one required to
get off the pole the first time around.
The next A press to be saved wasn’t tied to any
star in particular: it was the A press required
to enter Cavern of the Metal Cap. This one was
simple, but quite precise to pull off. After
getting Dorrie in the right spot, Mario can reach
the platform with a run up and a dive recover.
Coincidentally, the very next day,
Pannenkoek found another improvement,
again in castle movement. This time,
it was pounding the pillars to lower
the water and access the Vanish
Cap course. After catching MIPS,
Pannen carried it all the way to the pillars.
Here, he got off the pillar holding MIPS but
ground pounded. This instantly releases
MIPS, which in turn pushes Mario back
onto the pillar. Rinse and repeat for the other
pillar, and two more A presses had been saved.
At the same time, Pannen also found a way
to get Secret of the Haunted Books from 2
down to only 1 A press. The A press to get
to the second floor was still unavoidable,
but the second one to jump into the star
wasn’t. Here though, it wasn’t as simple
as a dive recover. Instead, he had to dive
recover onto the railing, which has a tiny
slippery slope on top of it. Immediately after
sliding off, he clips back in and ground pounds,
having just enough height to touch the star.
But how did he manage to clip back in like that?
Well, the answer is complicated. Not complicated
enough to make a fascinating 2-hour documentary
about- oh of course it is. So, we’re
gonna simplify things for the time being.
The railing’s cross section looks like this.
This is the inside wall, the outside wall,
and the slippery slope on top. Now, wall hitboxes
have multiple interesting properties. They extend
laterally by 50 units on each side of the wall.
In the case of a thin railing like this one,
the hitboxes can stick out of
the other side like this. Also,
wall hitboxes only extend vertically up to
30 units below the top of the wall. Because
the inside wall extends higher than the outside
one, this section of inside wall hitbox sticks
out and ends up pushing Mario back in from the
other side. This is the spot Pannenkoek hit to
make this A press save work. At the time, he
wasn’t fully aware of all of these mechanics,
and simply referred to it as glitching
to the other side of the railing.
Another level that saw an improvement around
this time is Rainbow Ride. The red coin star
was already down to 2 A presses, one
for each of the two trips to the maze.
An obvious way to improve that would be to
cut it down to a single trip to the maze
that somehow gets all 8 red coins in one go.
And that’s what Pannen did. He managed to do
it by activating the elevator and taking it
back up, and with this precise dive recover.
But then, he found something bigger. The carpet
trip to the top of the maze was essential,
but the A press needed in it seemed very
close to being skippable. He figured that
if he could have just one small bounce, he
could have the height needed to grab this
ledge without an A press. And he solved it with
the most advanced enemy luring strategy yet:
the Lakitu lure. He led Lakitu far away while he
was still low, then deactivated it until the last
moment. Deactivation works differently than
unloading does. When Mario is too far away,
Lakitu is no longer rendered and updated,
but it remains at the same position until
Mario gets near it again. Because Lakitu
takes a while to rise up to Mario’s height,
Pannen was able to get it to fly up into him just
in time to get enough height to grab the ledge.
As it turns out, the Lakitu lure saved
the final A press in the red coin star,
but it also saved one of the four A presses
for Big House in the Sky, which also shares
this carpet ride. And just like that, the total A
press count for all 120 stars was now under 100.
But there was no time for celebration: there
were more A presses to save. In Dire Dire Docks,
the convoluted red coin star went
from 3.5 to 2.5 when Pannen found
that he could activate the boxes switch,
and drop from the pole clone onto a box
instead of jumping off. This one was
actually more precise than it looks,
again because Mario has almost zero horizontal
momentum when he drops off from a pole.
Following the theme of improving upon already
complex stars, Pannen then came up with an insane
idea to improve the downtown stars of Wet-Dry
World. This was perhaps the most creative and
bizarre looking strategy yet. Thanks to
its 14-hour water level manipulation epic,
the red coin star was already at 0 A presses, but
Quick race through Downtown still required one A
press to complete. That is until Pannenkoek
somehow thought of raising the water level
so much, for so long, that it would reach
a value too large for the game to handle.
The water level is stored as a 16-bit
signed integer. In other words, it can
only be a whole number from negative 32 thousand
to positive 32 thousand. If it goes beyond 32767,
the water level quite literally overflows. So it
wraps around to negative 32 thousand, essentially
making the downtown area go from completely filled
with water to completely dry instantly. And now,
the genius part: because the water level bob
up and down, if the median is right around the
overflow limit, the water level can switch back
and forth between its maximum and minimum values,
overflowing and underflowing every two
seconds. Now that’s a Wet-Dry World.
The result looks very weird: Mario swims for a
bit, then starts falling, then becomes underwater
again, over and over. And this double state is
exactly what Pannen needed to bypass the need
for an A press in Quick Race through Downtown.
Also, although time is very much a secondary
concern in this challenge, this solution
saved about 3 hours for the red coin star.
After this string of improvements, Pannenkoek took
a bit of a break until mid-June. In the meantime,
though, he worked on a project dear to him since
his very beginnings with this game: a video on the
255 coin limit. Over the years, Pannen had made
dozens of videos about glitches and other Mario
science, but this one was special. For the very
first time, the whole world could hear his voice.
[Pannenkoek: Hey guys! It’s-a me, pannenkoek2012;
bringing you Dutch pancakes since 2010.]
This video didn’t bring anything new
for the A Button Challenge specifically,
although it did show the lengths he was ready
to go to just to get one extra coin in Tick
Tock Clock. The response from the community was so
positive that he decided that from this point on,
glitch explanations and other science videos would
become commentated. But because A Button Challenge
videos were mostly demonstrations of a strategy,
he felt little incentive to provide additional
commentary other than the video description,
and kept them in the same format as before.
When Pannen came back to the A Button Challenge,
he found an A press save to go to Bowser in the
Sky, which always required two A presses to get
up the steps. After exiting either Rainbow Ride
or Wing Mario over the Rainbow, it could be done
in only one with a slidekick bounce and a dive
grind double jump kick up three steps at once.
How does that skateboard trick sounding move work?
To first understand why dive grinding works, we
need to understand why grinding in general works.
If you’ve played this game before, you’ve
probably encountered this situation. This
happens because ground movement and air movement
are fundamentally different. On the ground,
Mario is pretty much always moving in the
direction that he’s facing. In the air,
Mario’s movement is defined by his speed and
facing angle as well, but it is also influenced
by the direction of the control stick. If Mario is
facing slightly away from a ledge, but the control
stick is held towards the platform, he will
move off of it while on the ground, and back on
to it once he’s in the air. This results in Mario
oscillating between being on and off the platform.
It doesn’t look like it here, but Mario is facing
ever so slightly away from the platform. When
he walks off, he enters a freefall state. In
freefall, Mario can dive no matter his speed.
He dives, but the joystick is held towards the
step, so on the very next frame, he moves back
onto the step. But now, because he’s facing away,
he slides back off the platform and into freefall
again. Each time Mario dives, it adds a flat 15
to his speed, up to a maximum of 48, which is 50%
more than running speed. So, with four consecutive
dives, he gets his speed up to 48. Then, he enters
freefall for a frame, and lands again. When Mario
lands from a freefall, he can immediately double
jump. Because the vertical speed of a jump is
influenced by the horizontal speed, and because
a double jump has a higher vertical speed than
a single jump, a 48 speed double jump kick gives
him just enough height and distance to make it
all the way up the stairs in a single A press.
Next, Pannenkoek looked at the 100-coin star in
Hazy Maze Cave. It took one A press to ground
pound the switch for blue coins, but with
clever swooper bounces, he could reach 100
different coins with only that one A press.
That is until he found a way to ground pound
the switch without having to jump. How could
he do that? Again, the answer was swoopers.
However, using swoopers to ground pound
the blue switch meant that he no longer
could use them to reach the Navigating
the Toxic Maze alcove. Because of that,
he missed out on too many coins to get 100 without
an A press. But thankfully, he could still combine
it with the red coin star and get both of them
for one A press total, instead of one for each.
Next up was Chip Off Whomp’s
Block. If you remember,
this star was left at one A press last
time because Pannenkoek couldn’t find a
way to get Mario to the star without jumping.
Well, if he couldn’t bring Mario to the star,
why not bring the star to Mario? That’s
right: he could do it via cloning!
Now, it’s easy to say, just clone the star, but
it’s actually not that simple. Up until this
point, the only way Pannen managed to clone a star
was by carrying objects through loading zones,
but Dire Dire Docks and Wet-Dry World are the
only two levels in the game that have a loading
zone. The issue is that without a loading zone,
stars are always loaded no matter how far Mario
is from them, so they can’t load into an object
slot that he’s currently holding. But here,
because the star appears after the fight with
King Whomp, it could theoretically load into
Mario’s hands if he was holding the correct
vacant object slot right at that moment.
As far as holding a vacant object slot goes,
Pannen knew it was possible to get a hold of
an unloaded cork box by bringing it all the way
up to the top, and having King Whomp break the
box while grabbing it at the right time. There’s
a major problem with keeping that unloaded box,
though. To end the fight, Mario
needs to ground pound King Whomp,
which is incompatible with holding an object.
It was time for new technology to step in.
This strategy was actually months in the making.
Back in 2013, Pannenkoek had discovered hands
free holding, a state in which Mario is no
longer in the action of holding an object,
but he still has a held object with him. It
can be triggered by a few specific actions,
like diving into a downwards slope, or bonking
into a ceiling. This is a volatile state with
many restrictions: in short, Mario is trying
to get rid of the object, so he has to be kept
constantly busy to keep him from dropping it.
This is usually done by jumping repeatedly,
but that’s not an option here. I’ll leave figuring
out why as an exercise for the viewer. Instead,
Pannen had to get creative. First, he triggers
the hands free holding glitch by bonking into
the bottom of King Whomp, which, at
this moment, acts as a ceiling. Then,
he punches repeatedly to avoid dropping the
unloaded box until he’s in the right position
to ground pound King Whomp while holding
a specific vacant slot, which the star
loads into. And this finally brought down
Chip Off Whomp’s Block to zero A presses.
Around the same time, Pannenkoek also
posted a video about trying to clone
blue coins. While he tried very hard
to make it happen, he just couldn’t
get it to work. [Pannenkoek: It doesn’t really
work. I just get stuck in some sort of limbo
world.] This goes to show that even though
so many breakthroughs were made in that era,
a lot of the research still ended up in
a dead end with nothing useful gained.
Also, Pannen started posting some lower effort
videos for testing ideas and documenting
strategies over on a secondary channel,
aptly named Pannenkeok2012. I’m
sure that’s not gonna be confusing.
July 2014. It had been a good
two weeks since Whomp’s Fortress,
so it was time for more breakthroughs. The
ascent up the rotating red coin platforms
in Tick Tock Clock, which was
done in 0 A presses before,
was now found to be possible in 0 A presses. But
this time, while holding an unloaded bob-omb!
Pannenkoek found that by entering the clock on
the random setting and by manipulating the RNG,
he was able to get all the way up these platforms
safely while holding an unloaded object. This let
him clone a bob-omb up here. The old strategy
for Roll into the Cage was a sideflip wallkick
from down here to get up in two A presses.
But with a bob-omb and a single A press,
Pannen was able to use the bloated bob-omb glitch
to get up the cogs without using A again. The
strategy involves hands free holding, triggered
here by being pushed off the platform while belly
sliding and holding the bob-omb, and a lot of
ground pounding, which, during its animation,
temporarily disables collision checks with floors
and most of its checks against walls. This is
usually fine, when Mario isn’t being pushed around
during the ground pound. But here, it allows him
to clip inside the cogs and pop up on top of
them when the ground pound animation is over.
This route involved some seriously crazy movement
because Mario can’t hold on to the bloated bob-omb
for more than a few frames at once. Thanks to
the bob-omb having four different bloated sizes,
he could grab it at slightly different
intervals and have it be smaller if he
wanted to position Mario, and larger if he
wanted a stronger push to cross large gaps.
This allowed him to get all the way
to the star and save an A press,
but he still needed one more to jump
into the star itself. Or did he?
Five days after posting this video, it was already
outdated. It turns out that the bob-omb can still
be useful even here. In its most bloated
state, it displaces Mario by so much that
it’s possible to clip outside of the cage, and
with a ground pound, onto this ramp. From there,
he was able to clip back in, but high enough
to grab the star without jumping into it. But
this new find was bigger than that. Reaching this
ramp had only been done in two A presses before.
Therefore, this new bob-omb strategy saved an
A press in three more Tick Tock Clock stars.
The next new technical development was for
Metal Head Mario can Move. Three months prior,
a scuttlebug had been used to save an
A press and bring it down to 2. Well,
it was time for that little bug to put in more
work and take out the rest of the A presses!
The first step was to make the scuttlebug jump
out of the pit. But then, Mario goes back out.
As Mario leaves the room, the scuttlebug
is deactivated, but not unloaded. Again,
this means that it remains where it is, but it’s
no longer being updated or drawn. When Mario goes
near it again, it will reappear in exactly
the same spot. This will be useful later.
The main development that made this improvement
possible was found by Plush. It’s similar to shell
hyperspeed. When pressing C-up while facing
slightly downwards on a steep slope, Mario is
trying to come to a stop, but the downwards slope
accelerates him straight ahead instead. Again,
because the slope is so steep, his de facto
speed is a small fraction of his real speed. Now,
when Mario enters water, he loses all of
that speed. Except, he actually doesn’t.
Horizontal speed in Super Mario 64
is handled in two different ways:
the regular speed and the sliding speed. The
regular speed is a single value that is applied
to Mario’s current facing angle to move him. It’s
used in most scenarios: running, jumping, falling,
taking damage, and many more. The sliding
speed is fundamentally different: it’s a
vector with an X and a Z component. The resulting
direction isn’t necessarily Mario’s facing angle.
As its name suggests, the sliding speed is used
while Mario is sliding, no matter where or how.
Even though only one type of speed is
used at a time, in most circumstances,
the unused speed is always updated to reflect the
one that’s being used. When Mario is not sliding,
the sliding speed vector is updated to reflect
Mario’s regular speed and angle, and when he is
sliding, the regular speed is updated to reflect
the amplitude of the sliding speed vector.
But there are situations where the regular
speed is updated while the sliding speed
isn’t. As it turns out, swimming is one of
them. While Mario is moving down the slope,
his sliding speed increases, and his normal
speed follows. When he falls in the water,
his normal speed drops back to 0, but his
sliding speed doesn’t update to match it,
so it stays high. Now, he can go back on
the slope and immediately start sliding,
which uses the sliding speed. That speed is still
high from the previous slide, and it goes even
higher. Pannen repeats this until the sliding
speed goes all the way up to 496. At this point,
Mario has so much speed that he can bypass the
entire wall hitbox without even colliding with it.
That threshold is 400 speed in most cases. Now,
all he needs to do is wait for Dorrie to show up,
and use it to instantly start sliding out of the
water, as well as to gain some precious height.
And this is where the scuttlebug comes
into play. As soon as it is reactivated,
Mario goes buttsliding onto it with so much
speed that one single bounce gets him all the
way across to the star. And that is how Metal
Head Mario Can Move was dropped to 0 A presses.
While all of this was happening,
another level was being worked on:
the eternal Bowser in the Sky. It had
been left at 6 A presses back in April,
but Pannen had been slowly chipping away at
it with incremental improvements for 6 weeks,
from late June to August 3rd. This is
everything he accomplished in that period.
First, one A press was saved using black
magic. What’s going on here is actually
not new. In his first run through the challenge,
Pannen had already abused this mechanic
to save an A press in a higher elevator,
perhaps without even realizing it. But how does
that work? Simply because this thing is stupid.
Have you ever run into weird wonkiness on one of
these elevators before? Have you ever bumped into
nothingness, or been squished out of nowhere?
Here’s why: the axle rotates around its center,
but its hitbox is incorrectly anchored
at one of its tips instead. And that is
the reason behind all of this weird behaviour,
including both of these A press-saving moves.
The second A press save came in the middle of
the level. This red coin always required an A
press to grab, but theoretically, Mario could also
collect it by falling from above. Unfortunately,
because getting off this pole also requires
an A press, it wasn’t any better to do so. But
Pannenkoek figured out that using goomba clones,
it would be possible to dismount the pole without
using A. Because the cloning had to be done over
here, which is past the pole, he did have to use
A once to dismount it the first time. But then,
he could clone goombas, drop down to the red coin,
and climb back up, using the goomba clones
to dismount the pole without using A again.
After some testing, he quickly realized
that because Mario’s momentum is so low
when dropping off from the pole, his best course
of action was to take damage instead. He managed
to do it by manipulating another goomba to
push the clone under Mario to damage him,
while falling into position so that
Mario could bounce on it during the
damage knockback. That worked, and so Bowser
in the Sky was down to only 4 A presses:
two at the start, one to get this red coin, and
one to get off the pole the first time around.
But that also wouldn’t last, thanks to a
brand new development in goomba engineering:
the goomba ladder. This is essentially
like a goomba bridge, except this time,
the bounces are mostly vertical instead. This let
him bypass the pole entirely, at the cost of many,
many clones. Long story short, this process
took him 46 goomba clones. One interesting
detail to consider is how Pannen managed to
clone from this bob-omb in the first place.
Vacant object slot manipulation
is something that I’ve avoided
talking about in detail because while it is a
crucial element of anything involving cloning,
one doesn’t need to know all of its intricacies
in detail to appreciate the incredible work
that goes behind these cloning strategies.
Here, though, I wanted to give a glimpse
of the kind of effort that sometimes has
to be made just to start cloning objects.
The main sources for all of these clones are this
bob-omb and that goomba trio. If you remember, on
a flat surface like this, it’s extremely
difficult to clone with a bob-omb. The
only real option Pannenkoek had was
to hold it off the edge as it blew up.
Grabbing it this way will give Mario
the vacant object slot number 9,
because of all the smoke particles and
the explosion happening at the same time.
Now, because a goomba trio is made up
of three goombas, they will load into
the first 3 vacant slots. This is a problem.
To get a goomba to show up in Mario’s hands,
Pannen needs to lower that vacant object
slot number from 9 to between 1 and 3,
which means he has to load at least 9 temporary
objects that would unload in a different order,
giving him a new vacant slot number. The
best he could do by kicking up dust was only
up to 8 dust particles, so he paired it with
collecting the bob-omb’s coin to add sparkles
to the object count. So, a temporary particle
loaded into Mario’s hands and then unloaded,
which lowered his vacant slot number enough
that he was able to clone a goomba from there.
But because the coin from a bob-omb is a one
time thing, this method could not be reused. So,
he used that first goomba clone to get easier
future cloning. Bob-ombs immediately explode
when they come in contact with other
bob-ombs, goombas or other enemies.
With the goomba clone just off the edge like
this, when the bob-omb runs off the edge,
it falls on the goomba and instantly
explodes. Mario is then able to grab an
unloaded bob-omb in vacant slot 2 instead of
9. From there, cloning more goombas is easy.
Alright, that was pretty crazy, but there
was one more major problem. Pannen needed
46 clones to get past the pole here, four
more clones to get the red coin here,
two to get the final red coin, and 61 more
clones to bounce into the pipe. The game was
never going to handle this many goomba clones at
once. The solution for that was twofold. First,
the disjointed axle hitbox let him skip one
step of the upper goomba bridge, and second,
he found that he could bring a bob-omb to
the pipe and skip the last few steps of
the goomba bridge. This brought down the
total amount of goombas from 113 to 63.
Nonetheless, because most of these
goombas were close together over there,
the additional clones Pannen needed to get
this red coin would invariably crash the
game. How he solved that seems absolutely
insane, because it is absolutely insane:
he got up the entire course,
without getting any red coins,
entered the Bowser fight, and then, he
purposely fell off to his death. But why?
Because this puts Mario back here,
at the very top of the stage,
but it resets the entire level so that
all the clones are now gone. From there,
he was able to set up all the clones again. But
this time, because he started from above, he only
needed a few clones to get back up the pole once,
instead of using 46 to build a goomba ladder to
bypass it. And that made all the difference
to enable this crazy A press save to happen.
But wait! There’s more! Three days later,
Pannenkoek figured out a way to save the very last
A press past the beginning platforms. He did it
by carrying Chuckya all the way there. In short,
the two main challenges were getting past
this gap, and getting from holding Chuckya
here to having it throw Mario into the
coin without killing it in the process.
Both of these were solved by dive grinding.
Basically, that gives Mario enough speed in
a short enough time that he has time to catch
up to Chuckya and get caught before it lands,
similarly to what he had done in Wet-Dry
World before. And with that improvement,
what was once a 13 A press stage was now
down to only two, both at the very beginning.
After this crazy adventure, Pannenkoek’s ideas
dried up a bit. College had started again, and
he stepped away from the A Button Challenge for a
while. But in the meantime, someone posted a very
bold claim on the Castle Movement A presses video.
“I figured out how to go to Hazy Maze Cave without
pressing the A button once!” Naturally, Pannen was
skeptical. What are the chances that some random
YouTube commenter had genuinely found a way to
improve upon one of the most basic A presses in
the entire challenge? After all, he’d been getting
dozens of these empty claims for well over a year
now. Well, obviously, if I’m talking about it, you
already know the answer. And Pannenkoek would soon
find out as well. The probability is zero. Because
this is no random YouTube commenter. This is Tyler
Kehne. The great mind behind the discovery of
parallel universes. Showing up out of the blue
one day, he annihilated every expectation and
took the A Button Challenge to the next level.
While everybody was focused on the 120-star A
Button Challenge, Tyler Kehne actually had a
different outlook: his primary goal was to make
it possible to beat the game in 0 A presses,
no matter the star count. Now, Super Mario
64 is very famous for its 0-star speedrun,
but there’s a bit of a problem with it. Most
of the star door skips require speed-generating
techniques that make heavy use of the A button,
like Backwards Long Jumping, or Hyperspeed Wall
Kicking. A 0-star, or even a 16-star run, would
automatically incur at least a dozen A presses
to skip the 50 and 70 star doors. So, the only
reasonable method would be to find 70 different
stars that could be collected in 0 A presses, and
beat all three Bowser stages without the A button.
When he first looked at it, Tyler found that
the lowest possible count was 9 A presses. Those
included two A presses to beat Bowser in the Dark
World, a half A press for Board Bowser’s Sub in
Dire Dire Docks, as well as five other stars, one
in Bowser in the Fire Sea, one to reach Bowser in
the Sky, two within Bowser in the Sky, and because
only 65 stars were attainable in 0 A presses,
three additional A presses to get the required
70 stars. The half A press is important here
because in the event that the A presses
to reach 70 stars and to beat Bowser in
the Dark World were all saved, there would no
longer be a prior A press to leech off from.
So, from this starting point,
Tyler made it his mission to lower that
A press count all the way down to 0.
His first discovery in that direction was a
huge breakthrough, because it allowed him to
go to Hazy Maze Cave in 0 A presses,
unlocking a whole level that already
had three stars at 0 A presses. Because
Pannenkoek was busy with college finals,
Tyler took it upon himself to make a
video about it. The crucial development
is the Star dance clip, which is made possible
thanks to Mario’s ability to grab onto ledges.
During most kinds of jumps or in freefall,
Mario can grab onto a ledge that he doesn’t
quite have enough height to land on. This
allows him to reach a floor up to 150
units higher than his own position, up from 30
with a direct landing. A regular dive recover
doesn’t allow Mario to grab onto ledges,
no matter how high, because that specific
action type prevents Mario from grabbing
the ledge. But when Mario collects a star,
this unique falling action type called the
star fall does allow him to grab a ledge.
Normally, during a ledge grab, Mario is
technically on top of the ledge while his
visual model hangs off. This is the
key mechanic that makes cannonless
possible. In this case, because the star
dance overrides the ledge grab animation,
Mario instantly pops up onto the
higher ledge and starts dancing.
The star dance clip was revolutionary, in
that it allowed Mario to reach a ledge as
high as about 280 units, up from the 158
that a simple dive recover can achieve.
There was only one simple problem:
it required a star. Not only that,
but a star in a very specific location.
This was a major hurdle for two reasons.
First, no stars are by default located
somewhere that they can be useful to reach
a higher ledge. But most importantly,
in any one of the 15 main courses,
collecting a star will automatically
exit the stage. But there is one
exception that conveniently sidesteps both
of these key problems: the 100-coin star.
This star appears precisely 245 units
above where the 100th coin was collected,
so its location can be pretty much anywhere
that a coin can be collected at. But also,
other than some castle secret stars,
this is the only type of star that
keeps Mario in the level after collecting
it. Therefore, with clever manipulation,
the 100th coin could be collected just beneath
a high ledge, and the star fall action could
make Mario grab the ledge and save an A press.
And then, because this is the 100-coin star,
he would be able to stay in the level afterwards.
This is the magic of the Star Dance Clip.
Tyler immediately used it in Stand Tall on
Four Pillars. A goomba knockback bounce into
the star is just enough to pop Mario up on the
grate, which has a warp that takes him further
up the pyramid. This is now high enough to
reach the miniboss fight without using A.
A month later, still on his own,
Tyler Kehne discovered a massive
new technique that he named the 207 Dive Recover.
A regular dive recover can get Mario on platforms
up to 158 units higher, but this special trick
gets him up to 207 units higher. This is made
possible because of the wall and floor hitboxes.
If you remember, I said before that wall hitboxes
extend up to 30 units below the top of the wall.
A dive recover gives Mario 128 units of height,
so on a platform that is up to 158 units higher,
Mario can dive recover just above the
wall hitbox and onto the platform. If
the platform is any higher, the wall will
prevent Mario from reaching the floor.
The floor hitbox, however, extends 78
units under the floor. If Mario finds
himself somewhere in this region, he’ll
snap up onto the floor. Theoretically,
Mario could dive recover into the bottom of this
region and snap up to the floor, gaining up to,
but not including, 207 units of height. In
practice though, a platform is almost always
surrounded by walls that prevent Mario from
reaching this zone. But what if that wasn’t
always the case? This is the key discovery
behind this new technique: misalignments.
Super Mario 64 tracks Mario’s position using
32-bit floating point numbers. So, Mario’s
position on each axis can be virtually anything,
including 8 million numbers just between 1 and 2
alone. The game physics calculation that checks
the height of the floor Mario is on or above has
a built-in shortcut. Instead of using the 32-bit
floating point number for Mario’s position,
the programmers decided to convert it into
a 16-bit integer. This lost some precision,
sure, because any fraction would be rounded
down to a whole number, but because one unit
is such a small distance, a fraction of
a unit would be completely insignificant.
Well, it turns out that it’s not that
insignificant when the wall collision
check does not make the same shortcut. This
leads to a very specific, literal corner case
scenario where Mario can be on a floor but
beyond its bounding walls at the same time.
This 1 by 1 unit square is beyond each of
the wall hitboxes, but if Mario ends up here,
his position will be rounded down for floor
calculations, putting him on the floor. So,
for all practical purposes, in the direction
away from the origin, floors extend 1 unit
further than their associated walls, leaving
a tiny exposed square at the outside corners.
This means that any platform which has
a corner pointing away from the origin
in both axes has a 1x1 misalignment
that can be used to bypass the wall
hitbox and snap up onto the floor from 78
units below it instead of the usual 30.
It seems rather small, but there are
actually numerous instances where
that makes all the difference. First,
these platforms in Bowser in the Sky,
where Tyler discovered the trick in
the first place. As it turns out,
all of these gaps that were just out of reach
with a regular dive recover were now reachable
using misalignments! All of them, except
the last one, unfortunately. But he was
undeterred. He was determined to make Bowser
in the Sky fully completable in 0 A presses.
Despite his already impressive track record
of two major discoveries in a month, nothing
would truly showcase Tyler Kehne’s creativity
and mastery of the game like the Chuckya drop.
From all the way down here, Mario is just on the
edge of Chuckya’s activation radius. When Chuckya
is deactivated, it stops moving and isn’t being
rendered, but it is still loaded. But there’s one
crucial function that still works: turning towards
Mario. Chuckya has two main behaviour modes:
chasing and turning. In chase mode, it
charges forwards until Mario is behind
it. This is what the white line demarcates.
Then, it stops for about a second and a half,
and goes into turning mode. In turning mode,
it turns until Mario is in the yellow cone,
then starts chasing again. If Mario quickly
goes from behind to in front of Chuckya,
he can already be in the yellow cone when
Chuckya starts turning. In that case,
it turns by about 5 and a half degrees
or until it faces Mario directly before
it starts chasing. This is important because
of the geometry of the platform Chuckya is on.
Chuckya has a built in mechanism that prevents
it from running off a ledge. If its next intended
position is more than 50 units above the
floor, that means it’s about to fall off,
so it will stop on the edge of the platform.
This check is only made if Chuckya is
currently on the ground. If it’s already
airborne, this no longer matters. But how
can Chuckya be airborne if it can’t fall
off in the first place? Because of slopes!
Chuckya has a constant gravity of 4 units
per frame squared, the same as Mario. On
any given frame, if, after falling down by 4
units, Chuckya is on or just below a floor,
it bounces. If it’s still in the floor,
then it’s popped back up on the ground,
but if it isn’t, it becomes airborne. So, if
Chuckya moves onto a floor that is between 2.7
and 50 units lower than its current height, it
will become airborne, and once it’s airborne,
the 50 unit limit no longer applies, so
it can now fall off from much higher.
There’s one last potential hurdle: Chuckya
can’t just run around entire levels. It
has a point called its home, and it can
only chase Mario up to a certain distance
away from that home. But thankfully,
the distance is strictly horizontal,
and by a stroke of pure luck, it happens to be
just big enough to allow this strategy to work.
Every piece of the puzzle can now fall into
place. Mario performs a complex mating dance
down at the bottom, on the edge of Chuckya’s
activation radius. He makes Chuckya turn to
face him here, then moves back behind it to
activate the stopping period. In that time,
he quickly goes back within the yellow cone
to have Chuckya turn just a little more
counter-clockwise. He repeats this until Chuckya
faces in this direction as much as possible. Then,
he activates Chuckya by entering the radius, and
makes it run up against the edge and onto the
sloped ground here. At this point, he can only
activate Chuckya with dive recovers and ground
pounds. Once Chuckya runs onto the slope,
it becomes airborne and can now fall off,
but it’s headed in the wrong direction. So
Mario falls back out of the activation radius,
freezing Chuckya in midair. Then, he moves
back behind it to make it turn towards him,
and reactivates it so it now falls down towards
him. Again, he moves back behind it to make it
stop before it falls off the course altogether.
And from there, he’s able to be grabbed and
chucked on the upper platform, and the final A
press in Bowser in the Sky had finally been saved.
It’s impossible to overstate how unlikely this
strategy really is. Every aspect of it just
barely works. This wall allows Chuckya to run up
against it instead of getting stuck on the edge,
at precisely the right angle to allow Chuckya to
reach all the way to the slope while Mario is down
below. The slope is just steep enough to cause
Chuckya to become airborne, the perfect placement
of the edge of the activation radius allows
for activating and deactivating it on command,
and the perfect size of the area around its
home allows it to move all the way to this
point. It’s even crazier when you consider
that Tyler was working with very rudimentary
tools and little understanding of all the
mechanics I just described. The fact that
this A press save is possible at all is nothing
short of a miracle, but the fact that it was
discovered over 7 years ago is indescribably
unlikely. You just can’t make that story up.
Again in October, and again on his own, Tyler
Kehne found yet another groundbreaking trick
to gain precious height in specific scenarios:
vertical speed conservation, or VSC for short.
Mario’s vertical speed is a variable
that’s almost entirely independent
from his horizontal speed. This is mostly
a major hurdle for the A Button Challenge,
but it can sometimes be useful. In certain
circumstances, when Mario lands on the ground,
his vertical speed isn’t automatically set to
0. It remains what it was at the last moment
where Mario was in the air. This means that if
Mario was somehow able to land on a platform
while he’s moving up, he could get off of it later
and retain his upwards speed, potentially gaining
more height than ever possible before. There are
two reasons why this can’t work, though. First,
Mario can’t really land on anything if he’s
moving up, and second, vertical speed is reset
to 0 as soon as Mario starts moving. But what if I
told you that Mario doesn’t need to move to move?
The action of throwing a punch makes
Mario inch forward a little bit,
but it doesn’t require moving the control stick.
It also doesn’t reset the vertical speed. So,
if Mario lands with a non-zero vertical
speed, then punches repeatedly until he
falls off from the platform he’s
on, he will conserve that speed.
But this doesn’t fix the problem that
Mario needs to fall onto something,
therefore have negative vertical speed, in order
to actually land on it. Well, it turns out this
isn’t strictly true. There are some cases where
it’s possible to move up onto a platform, but
they’re relatively rare. For example, a platform
that doesn’t have any walls, like a magic carpet,
can work. Also, if the platform itself is moving
up, like an elevator, it can move onto Mario. So,
it is indeed possible to land on a
platform with positive vertical speed,
and there are some very specific cases where
this trick could actually come in handy.
At the end of October, Pannenkoek finally had
enough time to come back to the challenge and
he was immediately met with this revolutionary
work. He instantly recognized Tyler Kehne’s
potential and invited him on the ABC crew, but
he also saw the potential of these three new
key discoveries. The floodgates were officially
open and improvements could start flowing again.
First came The Big House in the Sky, where
a dive recover onto the magic carpet allowed
Pannenkoek to conserve its vertical speed.
Then, by getting pushed off the carpet,
Mario enters freefall, but gains height like a
dive recover. Being in freefall means that he
can ledge grab, allowing him to get onto
these blocks without an A press. Sadly,
the last one is higher than the others, and
one A press was therefore still required.
Next up was Big Boo’s Haunt, where this A press
was proving problematic for the four stars that
required going up to the second floor. Again
with VSC, but this time done using the stairs
raising onto Mario, Pannen was able to cut this
A press out, saving four at once. The red coin
star also required getting rid of that half
A press for kicking onto boos in this room,
but Pannen was able to figure it
out using a dive recover instead.
Then, in Dire Dire Docks, he found that
these cork boxes can be climbed on using
misalignments. This allowed him to reach this high
platform in 0 A presses and without a pole clone,
which, again, revolutionized 4 different
stars. Board Bowser’s Sub was now down to
0 A presses. Both Through the Jet Stream
and Collect the Caps were also down to 0 A
presses because the special caps could now
be obtained without jumping. And finally,
Pole-Jumping for Red Coins could get rid of the
initial half A press and go down to a clean 2.
In Bowser in the Dark World, three
TASers, Tyler, Pannen and Plush,
and two new techniques combined to
save the remaining two A presses. Here,
Mario does a dive recover into the crystal,
which is made up of tiny walls in an interesting
arrangement. By entering two wall hitboxes at
once, Mario gets pushed all the way to here.
Because the floor slopes up, this is enough
to land immediately after the dive recover,
allowing him to preserve the vertical speed
all the way to here with repeated punches.
The A press to enter the pipe was solved
using a misalignment. Specifically,
this corner points outwards from the
origin, so Tyler Kehne was able to
dive recover into the misalignment and
save the final A press in this stage.
Now in Rainbow Ride, Pannenkoek found another
multi-purpose A press save. This time, it was
to reach the cruiser at the top of the stage.
He used vertical speed conservation, combined
with a very precise, complex Lakitu lure to get
it to fly up precisely into that corner. The VSC
was achieved by making this block start falling,
then dive recovering, and landing one frame later
on this block. Mario doesn’t dip low enough to
start being affected by the walls of that block,
making this maneuver possible. Then, one punch
gets him off the platform with vertical speed,
and the Lakitu bounce gets him just high enough to
grab this ledge. This brought Cruiser Crossing the
Rainbow to 0 A presses, and Somewhere Over the
Rainbow down to 1 because of the cannon shot.
With the 120-star A press count down
to 71, Pannenkoek and the ABC crew,
including three more people, Kaze Emanuar of
romhacking fame, Ryan Strobach, and Pedro Viktor,
decided to make a prediction: how low would
the A press count be 6 months into the future,
on May 13th, 2015? Everyone made guesses roughly
around 60. Tyler Kehne was the most optimistic
of them all with 54, predicting that 17 A
presses would be cut down before 6 months
had passed. Needless to say, every single one of
these predictions would turn out way off base.
Meanwhile, Tyler Kehne, who was more focused
on Any%, tried to get rid of the A press to
enter Bowser in the Sky. He found that on the
Rainbow Ride side of the room, he was able to
use misalignments to ascend some of the steps,
but two of them were being difficult. This one,
and the final step. The ramp on the top step
complicated things a bit, but using a ground
pound and some slide grinding, Tyler was able
to make it up. The first step’s problem is that
it doesn’t line up right for a misalignment
to exist. Tyler could have used a slidekick
bounce from Rainbow Ride, but because he was
concerned with Any%, where Rainbow Ride was not
gonna be entered, he had to find another
method. He found the glitchy ledge grab.
When Mario hits a wall, a check is made to see
if he can grab the ledge. In short, the game
checks for a wall hitbox at two points: 30 units
above Mario’s position, and 150 units above,
which is about the size of Mario’s model.
If it finds a wall hitbox at this point,
but not the other, it will try to find a ledge to
grab onto by looking for a floor hitbox from 160
units to 100 units above Mario’s position.
Because floor hitboxes are 78 units high,
this means that Mario can theoretically
grab a ledge up to 238 units above his
position. But if there is a ledge
that high, wouldn’t there be a wall
below that ledge that the wall check would
detect? Yes, but not always. Here’s why.
Wall hitboxes are 50 units wide perpendicularly
to the wall, but at the edge of the wall,
they don’t necessarily extend perpendicularly.
They actually extend along the closest axis,
either X or Z. So, if a wall isn’t aligned
exactly along one of the axes, its hitbox
will have a slanted shape along its edges. In
this corner, both walls extend along the X axis,
creating this shape. When Mario is in this
zone, he’s in the low wall hitbox, but not the
high one. So, the game detects a wall 30 units
above Mario, but not 150 above him. Therefore,
the floor check is triggered. Now, because Mario
is colliding with the low wall, the game uses the
line perpendicular to that wall to check for a
floor. Because of the lower wall’s orientation,
the perpendicular line is angled towards
the higher floor, so the floor check finds
that one and Mario grabs the higher ledge. If
the walls extended perpendicularly instead of
along the closest axis, this would not have been
possible. Also, there was finally only a single
A press absolutely required to beat the game,
to jump off the pole in Bowser in the Fire Sea.
In these frantic two weeks, vertical speed
conservation had proven to be a key asset to
gain height by preserving positive vertical
momentum. But what about negative vertical
momentum? Well, yes, negative vertical
speed can be preserved, but obviously,
in a challenge where height is precious, falling
even faster than usual is crazy to even consider.
But the closest thing to crazy is genius. Plush
figured out that for Express Elevator - Hurry Up!,
he could conserve negative vertical speed to
fall down faster after activating the elevator,
making it possible to reach the
platform using only B swimming,
and cutting the half A press
that was left in this star.
Plush was a relatively rare contributor, but
this time, he came up with another A press save
in the same month, in Jolly Roger Bay. Through
the Jet Stream’s A press to jump into the star
could be skipped by positioning Mario in the
center of the jet stream so that it would push
Mario up into the star once the metal cap
expired. This seems obvious in hindsight,
but it’s actually extremely precise, to the
point where it had been tried before and
discarded. The stream pushes Mario up, but also
outwards, so he has to stand on the exact center,
give or take a tiny fraction of a
unit, in order to not miss the star.
Plush was on a hot streak. He struck again,
this time in Dire Dire Docks. He found that
the underwater shell’s higher speed could
be partially preserved with frame perfect
B swimming. Normally, B swimming has a speed
cap of 7 units per frame, but with this method,
it could hold a speed of 16 units per frame.
This is enough to do Chests in the Current
without being sucked into the whirlpool, so
another half A press was taken out of the game.
The next improvement came a whole month
later, at the very end of 2014. Pannenkoek,
not to be outdone, was still busy
concocting absurd routes that no one
else could have even remotely considered.
And this time, it was one of his best.
Swingin’ in the Breeze in
0 A presses, down from 1.
The key new glitch in this route
was hands free teleport. Usually,
when Mario is holding an object, he cannot use a
warp. But when he’s holding an object hands free,
he can. The result is that the
original object remains in limbo,
but the held object is discarded. This means
the original object cannot be retrieved from
limbo and is stuck there forever. But of
course, there’s one exception: bob-ombs.
After a hands free teleport with a bob-omb,
Mario will no longer be holding anything,
which gives him back his wide range of actions,
but he’ll still have the original bob-omb hovering
in front of him at all times, invisible but still
tangible. He can recover that bob-omb by grabbing
it straight out of limbo. Now, what happens
if that bob-omb is also in a bloated state?
Well, because it’s larger than
usual, it pushes Mario backwards,
again by a varying amount depending on the
exact frame it was grabbed on. And this is
the reason behind the behaviour that Pannenkoek
exploits in this star. Let’s go through the route.
First, he goes up to the cruiser using VSC and
the Lakitu bounce, like in the other stars. Once
there, he grabs a bloated bob-omb hands free by
being pushed off the edge as he grabs it. Then,
he carefully navigates to the top of the red
coin maze while preserving the hands free
state. In order to reach the warp while
hands free holding a bloated bob-omb, he
needs it to be bloated enough to give him
a large push. But after taking the warp,
the large push becomes a little cumbersome,
so he regrabs the bob-omb and uses this thin
ledge to get hands free holding again, but
this time, with a smaller bloated bob-omb.
Back onto the maze, he now has a bob-omb that
gives him a slight backwards push. He makes his
way to here, where he lures the Fly Guy up and
bounces onto it to twirl over to this platform.
Then, he pushes the goomba up the slope using
the hitbox of the invisible bloated bob-omb in
front of him. But because the bob-omb pushes
Mario backwards, he can’t get enough forward
momentum to climb the slippery slope.
But that’s no problem for Pannenkoek,
because this is what he does instead. From there,
he can push the goomba all the way to the star,
get rid of the bob-omb, and use a damage knockback
bounce to reach the star and save an A press.
The year was now 2015. Pannenkoek went back to
Pole Jumping for Red Coins. The new misalignment
allowed him to reach the cap box, and using
the surrounding walls, perform the hat in
hand glitch. This in turn allowed him to release a
pole clone remotely by setting the HOLP in another
level beforehand, namely Whomp’s Fortress. With
the preset HOLP, he was able to release a pole
clone here, in-between these two poles, and use
it to navigate to and back from the red coin.
Pole clones are an exception to the one
interaction rule. Mario can actually
reuse them as many times as he wants, because
the interaction with a pole does absolutely
nothing to the pole’s interaction status,
as opposed to enemies or coins. This let
him save an A press, but reintroduced
the half A press entering the level,
bringing the star down from 2 to 1.5 A
presses and saving one A press overall.
Shortly after, he also revisited Big House in
the Sky, which was left at one A press for this
blue box, too high for VSC and not oriented
properly for a misalignment. Of course,
that doesn’t mean it was impervious to
Pannen magic. He figured out that an
exploding bob-omb could push Mario through the
wall, and because the carpet would be inside,
he would have ground to stand on while inside
the box. And because there are no inside walls,
he could get pushed back out
easily on the other side.
But he was facing a pretty peculiar problem.
In short, he wanted to bring a bob-omb to this
place while also having the carpet be active.
This makes things a little complicated because
the carpet ride involves uses of VSC and those
involve a dive recover, but diving with a bob-omb
in limbo automatically causes Mario to grab
the bob-omb instead. This meant he needed to
somehow bring a bob-omb here, but also be able
to perform VSC on the box immediately before.
Also, because cloning bob-ombs involved reaching
the cruiser, he had to use Lakitu to get there,
which prevents the other Lakitu bounce used
in this route. So, now, he had to figure out
a way to use two different bob-ombs to clip inside
those two different boxes on the same carpet ride.
The solution he came up with was quite involved.
First, he went up to the cruiser and cloned
a bob-omb which he dropped to break the cork
box below. This simply frees up the space for
later. Then, he cloned another bob-omb,
which he released in such a way that it
would eventually fall down to the platform below,
but only after a bit of walking around. Finally,
he grabbed a third bob-omb, bloated this
time, and carried it hands free to the
warp. Meanwhile, the walking bob-omb
deactivates until Mario comes back.
Now, something interesting happens with bob-ombs
after a hands free teleport. When Mario does a
hands free teleport, the bob-omb actually doesn’t
follow him. It only does as soon as Mario enters
its activation radius, at which point it remembers
it needs to hover invisibly in front of him, so it
snaps to his position. In this case, it happens
that the warps are just a little bit further
apart than the activation radius. So, when Mario
warps, the bob-omb stays on the red coin maze, and
Pannen makes sure to stay out of its activation
radius until he’s ready to bring it back to Mario.
Once that bob-omb is positioned, he takes the
carpet ride. This time, as he passes under the
bob-omb on the bridge, it reactivates and falls
off below when he can retrieve it. He uses that
one to clip inside of the box that the lakitu
bounce used to clear. Once he reaches this point,
he performs VSC just before entering this
bob-omb’s activation range. He lets the
wall push him off the platform, since he can’t
punch to inch forward, and now, he’s ready to
regrab that bob-omb from limbo, clip through the
final box and save the last A press in this star.
After this madness, you’d think Pannenkoek
would take a break from Rainbow Ride for a bit.
Well, you’d be wrong. He tried to apply the
same bloated bob-omb hands free teleport
strategy to Tricky Triangles, but no matter
how hard he tried, he couldn’t quite reach the
star. During that process though, he needed
to get the Fly Guy in the perfect location,
and in doing so, he discovered a
new technique: Fly Guy manipulation.
This is a bit of a complex one, so let me try
and summarize it. Fly Guy has three states:
flying around, chasing Mario, and going back
to its home. Again, like for all enemies,
Fly Guy’s home is a point in space that it
will always try to fly back to when it strays
far away. If Fly Guy is currently far from
its home, then it will try to go back home,
unless Mario is low enough below it, in which
case it will chase Mario instead. This state
change only depends on the height difference,
regardless of lateral distance. On top of that,
Fly Guy’s state can still be influenced even
if Mario is outside of its activation radius.
Although it won’t move, it’s still able
to change states, rotate and gain vertical
speed, affecting how it’s gonna behave
whenever Mario enters its radius again.
The space below Fly Guy can be subdivided
in three zones: high, medium and low. For
it to start chasing Mario, Mario needs to be
in the low zone. Now, there’s a special case
that happens if it starts chasing Mario, and
shortly after, Mario is in the high zone. Fly
Guy will then lunge at Mario instead, and gain
significant vertical speed. If Mario activates
Fly Guy again at that time, it will lunge
up and ahead, then return to a normal state.
Sometimes, Fly Guy can also start to spin in
place while it’s in lunge mode. This behaviour
randomly occurs based on RNG, which can also be
manipulated. By strategically reentering the low
zone, and back to the high zone, it’s possible
to get Fly Guy to face any angle and lunge in
that direction when it’s activated again. With
all of this in mind, it’s theoretically possible
to make Fly Guy go anywhere we want.
Of course, provided that at all times,
there is an accessible point to manipulate its
state, and another accessible point to activate
and deactivate it at will. In short, Fly Guy
manipulation is possible, but it requires an
amount of planning and effort only matched thus
far by a handful of the most ludicrous strategies.
So, with this new tool in hand, Pannenkoek
was able to use a better way to reach the
Tricky Triangles star. He got the Fly Guy
to lunge all the way to this platform,
where he could bounce on it and twirl
directly to the star, saving an A press.
But now, there was an interesting question:
would it be possible to get Fly Guy so far,
and so high up, that it could be used to go
from the cruiser to the platform where the
Somewhere over the Rainbow star is? Was it
even possible to reach the platform with a
single twirl? Tyler Kehne and Pannenkoek set off
to answer that question. It took three weeks of
planning and testing and TASing, but they did
it. The resulting route is too complicated to
break down step by step. The luring itself is
a masterpiece - check out the notes for a link
to a video showing how it was done. Given the
rudimentary tools they had at their disposition,
it’s impossible to overstate how astronomical
the task to get Fly Guy across and up the entire
level was, while also juggling Lakitu
for that bounce to reach the cruiser.
And now, after all this work,
they had Fly Guy at the very
top of the cruiser’s mast. It was
time for the final tour de force.
And with this incredibly tight twirl,
one of the unlikeliest A presses
to ever be saved was now gone.
But Fly Guy manipulation wasn’t limited
to only Rainbow Ride. It turns out that
Snowman’s Land also has a Fly Guy, and that
level still had one pesky A press left,
in Snowman’s Big Head. Using shell hyperspeed,
Pannen was able to ascend steep slopes all the
way up to the ice bridge, and from there, a
carefully manipulated Fly Guy lunged into him,
sending him flying up to the star. Snowman’s
Land was now fully done in 0 A presses.
Meanwhile, Tyler Kehne and Plush were hard at
work to pull off another creative strategy,
in the volcano of Lethal Lava Land. Lava
boosting can be used to gain a great amount
of height at once, at the cost of 3 sectors
of health. So, while it is a very useful tool,
it can only be used twice, otherwise
it would kill Mario. However,
there’s one way to get around this limitation:
refilling Mario’s health midway. Spinning hearts
heal Mario when he runs through them.
The faster he runs through a heart,
the faster it will spin, which in turn refills
Mario’s health faster and for a longer time.
So, this is what they came up with: first, they
get some height to do a slidekick bounce into
the lava waterfall, in order to reach the high
bridge with two lava boosts. There’s nothing
funky going on here: Mario bouncing on lava with
a slidekick is purely intended behaviour. Then,
they go over to the spinning heart and dive
into it, touching it with roughly 48 speed. That
causes the heart to spin faster and longer than
usual, giving Mario a lot of health back. They
use that to get back up with higher health than
before, pick up coins to fill Mario’s health up,
and use another lava bounce to reach this higher
platform. But they’ll need better to get to
the star. So they slidekick bounce back to the
lava waterfall, picking up the last two coins,
and they now have just enough health for two more
lava bounces that give Mario barely enough height
and distance to cross the gap to the highest
platform in the volcano. That brought Hot-Foot-It
into the Volcano to 0 A presses, and Elevator
Tour in the Volcano from 2 down to 1 A press.
During that time, Pannenkoek was working on
Vanish Cap Under the Moat. While the other
special cap switches had features allowing
to get on top of them without jumping,
the blue switch was problematic, because there
was nothing to work with. On top of that,
even new discoveries didn’t seem to
help. There was no star to work with,
no nearby ledge to use VSC, and while
the switch did have a misalignment,
it was 247 units above the ground, too high
for a 207-unit misalignment dive recover. But,
Pannen still wanted to test it. And in doing
that, he found that the base of the switch also
has a misalignment at the same spot. So, by diving
into that misalignment, he could get up 72 units,
then dive recover and ascend the remaining
175 units using the second misalignment. All
special cap courses were now done in 0 A presses,
including the A presses needed to reach them.
March 2015. The A press count is already
down to 57, with two months to go until
the prediction’s deadline. At this rate,
it still looks like Tyler Kehne might
get close with his guess of 54. And
that’s when things took a wild turn.
Tyler was looking for a way to reach the piranha
plants platform from the Tiny island painting. You
see, the problem with Tiny-Huge Island is that
entering the huge painting takes an A press,
and entering the tiny painting leaves
you stranded in the starting area.
Figuring out a way to get out of there would
indirectly save an A press in the castle,
even if the star itself was
already possible in 0 A presses.
He found a way to get across both gaps using tiny
goombas. First, this one to bounce onto the middle
platform. And then, that one can fall off from
above, and a precise dive recover could hit it and
bounce Mario to the piranha plants. From there,
the pipe could be entered using a misalignment
on its outer corner, and the rest of the star was
trivial. Pannenkoek got to work and, after 4 hours
of goomba manipulation, he managed to pull it
off. One of the castle A presses had been saved.
But the story doesn’t end here. As it turns out,
from this platform, the rest of the island is
painfully close to be fully accessible. There’s
only this gap separating Mario from saving the
A press on every single Tiny-Huge Island stage
entry, which would be massive. Unfortunately,
no misalignments can be exploited, and VSC can’t
be used because the level geometry doesn’t allow
for it. There was one trick left in the bag of new
discoveries: the star dance clip. Theoretically,
it would be possible to get up if a star
was positioned perfectly in that gap. But
how do you get a 100-coin star here, of
all places, with only access to a tiny
fraction of the island? You can’t, of course.
Unless you’re Pannenkoek and Tyler Kehne.
Back in 2010, Pannen had already figured out a
way to get infinite coins in Tiny-Huge Island,
and that method involves the piranha plants!
If they are hit on the last possible frame as
they shrink back into the ground, piranha
plants can give goins again. This process
can be repeated infinitely many times.
However, once he did get to 99 coins,
Pannen still needed a way to get his
100th coin precisely in that corner.
Thankfully, when a plant dies, the coins spring
out in a direction and speed fully determined
by the RNG value. By manipulating
that to be exactly what he wanted,
Pannen could get the coin to fly out
directly to that corner. But this was
extremely precise. As it turns out, of the 65
thousand possible RNG values, only 17 of them
would provide sufficient speed and the correct
angle to make this possible. On top of that,
to milk all the extra distance he possibly could,
Pannen also abused object tangibility mechanics.
Objects like cork boxes, elevator platforms,
rotating platforms, seesaws and many others,
are only tangible if Mario is close enough to
them. That distance is surprisingly short. As
soon as Mario walks away just a bit, other
objects like coins or enemies will fall
through these platforms. If you pay close
attention, you can actually see the coin
start falling through between each box. That’s
Pannen using this mechanic so that the coin
would fall just enough to be pushed forward
by the outer wall of this cork box. Then,
he enters that cork box’s tangibility radius
just in time for it to catch the coin.
In the end, that was just enough to
get the coin in the right spot before
it disappeared. From there, Pannen could do
the star dance clip using the 100-coin star,
and he was now on the mainland in 0
A presses from the tiny painting. And
that saved 5 A presses, once for every star
in Tiny-Huge Island except the first one.
On the very same day, Pannen also found a way to
get up from this point of Tick Tock Clock, to this
point, in only one A press instead of two. He did
it by using a bob-omb to clone coins all the way
up to 99, then performing his usual shenanigans
to reach this point with a bob-omb at hand. He
collects the coin right here, spawning the 100
coin star, then uses VSC and a star dance clip to
get all the way up onto the ledge. From there, one
A press is required to jump off the pole, so an A
press was saved in three different Tick Tock Clock
stars, for a total of 8 A presses in a single day.
In the meantime, Pannenkoek was also very
committed to saving the A press for Top o’
the Town, but no matter how hard he tried,
no matter from what angle he looked at it,
he always hit a wall. He tried so
many different strategies, in fact,
that he came up with a list of ten different
actions. If even one single action from that
list could be done in 0 A presses, the
star would be solved. Here they are.
Enter the painting at the high water level. Return
from downtown on the low water level. Hold Chuckya
as a light object on its platform. Get Chuckya
onto the plank. Get past the wall hitbox of the
star platform with less than 50 speed. Have at
least 2 air frames while diving onto the spinning
platform at high speed. Have one more unit of room
on the star platform. Bring a flame or a flame
clone onto the star platform. Get one more unit
higher than a dive recover on the star platform,
and finally, be able to remotely open the star
block. Pannenkoek was so close, yet so far. And
that’s when Plush discovered that it is possible
to hold Chuckya as a light object on its platform.
Every object that can be carried around can
be either light or heavy. When Mario carries a
light object, he can walk around fairly quickly,
with the best animation in the entire game. If
the object is heavy, though, Mario’s movement is
extremely limited. Also, the game always expects
you to grab heavy objects with a punch grab.
You can’t dive grab Chuckya, and you would
never be expected to grab it in water either.
So, those two grab actions always default to
the light object holding state, regardless of the
weight of the actual object. But as it turns out,
you can, in fact, grab Chuckya in water. After
that, Mario will be walking around as if he
was holding a bob-omb or a box. Unfortunately,
for this star, that wasn’t quite useful enough.
The key new discovery was that it is possible to
dive grab Chuckya, but only if it’s done a couple
of frames after punching. This can be achieved
by standing right on the edge of a platform.
Shortly after punching, Mario starts falling
and dives on the same frame. That allows him to
grab Chuckya and land back on the platform at the
same time. Because he used the dive grab action,
Mario defaults to holding a light object, and he
can carry Chuckya around with much more freedom.
Pannen used this to get Chuckya up onto the plank,
and from there, he could carry it over to the
spinning platform, where he could get thrown into
the star. Another easy A press save in the books.
You know, it’s been a whole 3 days since
Pannenkoek last blew everybody’s mind with
a comically absurd, cryptic sequence
that somehow comes together into an
absolute masterpiece. How about we
go for a ride in Whomp’s Fortress?
The only A press left in that stage is
in To the Top of the Fortress. But first,
a quick stop in Bob-omb Battlefield to place
the HOLP in a convenient location. This is a
pretty high point, so a few goombas
clones are needed to do the trick.
Now in Whomp’s Fortress, Pannen first uses the
metal cap to perform the hat in hand glitch,
then collects some coins. The 100 coin star
will come in handy here. He also throws a box,
but wait, where does it go? Ah, there it is. And
there it goes again. Whoa, there it is! After
dropping it at the top of this slope, he finds
it over there. As you may have guessed by now,
the HOLP that was set in Bob-omb Battlefield
translates to a point high above this arrow
platform. Now, he uses that box to collect
the 100th coin right next to the tower.
But he needs one more piece of the
puzzle. He goes back down and gets
the other cork box in the stage. He plays
catch with Schrödinger’s box some more,
and brings the box to the top
as well. And now, don’t blink!
So, what just happened? As Mario threw the box,
it warped to the HOLP. Pannenkoek placed it at
this exact position so that the box would land
on the elevator platform at this precise angle.
Mario quickly gets into position with
a pause-buffered dive recover before
the box falls on top of him and pushes
him off the platform. He enters freefall
and ground pounds. Meanwhile, the box’s
bounce trajectory perfectly follows him,
pushing him forward for the entire duration of
the ground pound. This allows him to touch the
100 coin star much higher than would otherwise
be possible. And from there, a simple star dance
clip gets him up the rest of the way onto this
ledge, and the rest of the star is trivial.
This brought Whomp’s Fortress to 0 A presses,
and the total A press count down to 45,
completely eclipsing every single prediction
made by the ABC crew, with two months to spare.
But the next two months did not end up as
fruitful as January and March were. Most
members of the ABC crew were busy with college
and other responsibilities. Nonetheless,
a major advancement was made. This time,
they got outside help from a speedrunner.
Japanese runner honey was practicing Bowser
in the Sky, when he ran into this glitch by
complete accident. You can see the bob-omb
disappear, but if you pay close attention,
you can see that it reappears way off in the
distance. What could’ve possibly happened?
Soon enough, Tyler Kehne, Plush and
Pannenkoek were on the case. They
eventually managed to recreate
and understand what happened,
and that’s when they realized they had a shiny
new tool to break the game with: instant release.
The way this works is actually very simple. It has
to do with the fact that the held object’s last
position only updates if the held object needs
to be visually updated. With instant release,
Mario bonks into a wall on the same frame that
he grabs the object. Bonking automatically drops
the objet Mario is holding, so before the held
object has any time to be drawn in Mario’s hands,
it’s already gone. Because the object is
being dropped, it’s released at Mario’s
vertical position, but at the HOLP laterally.
This is what is being observed in honey’s clip:
the HOLP was somewhere on this line, and
the bob-omb was released at Mario’s height.
Now, this had important ramifications
for the A Button Challenge,
because it was now possible to remote drop
an object without the hat in hand glitch,
and without the massive restrictions of
transport cloning. The only restriction
this time was there had to be a way to grab the
object and bonk into a wall at the same time.
This new technique immediately found a use
in Tick Tock Clock. By setting up the HOLP
in Wet-Dry World beforehand, Pannen is able to use
instant release to warp a bob-omb out of bounds,
far enough away that Mario is out of its
activation radius. Then he uses the other
bob-omb to clone coins and gets all the way
to 97. Then, he places a flame clone under
the ledge. Of course, as he releases it,
he instantly gets burned, which uses up the
clone. But all he has to do is clone a new
flame and release it next to the first one,
just like he had done with goombas before,
and this second clone would be usable.
After that, he collects these coins, making sure
to clone one of them to collect it right under the
ledge, spawning the 100 coin star exactly where
he wants it to be. And now, everything is in place
for the magic to unfold. A dive recover into a
flame bounce into a star dance clip gets him all
the way up to the ledge. From there, dive recovers
get him up the cogs, where the bob-omb magically
appears. This is because as soon as Mario
enters the bob-omb’s radius, it’s reactivated,
but because it was dropped out of bounds, the
game puts it at Mario’s position as a failsafe.
And now, he gets across to the cage, and uses
VSC to reach the star, finally lowering Roll
into the Cage to 0 A presses, a feat that seemed
absolutely impossible not even two years before.
And Pannenkoek was not even done in Tick Tock
Clock. The red coin star, sitting at 0 A presses
for a while now, could obviously no longer
be improved. But that didn’t stop Pannen from
trying anyway. And that’s when he came up with
something truly incredible: negative A presses.
Okay, not really, but this is the next best thing.
Tick Tock Clock always takes one A press to
enter because the clock face is so high up.
But what if there was a way to collect a star in
such a way that once Mario returns to the castle,
he’s somehow able to reenter the stage without
the required A press? It seems impossible,
because changing maps like that
resets almost every variable and
strips control away from the player
until the celebration is over.
But there’s one glitch that can still affect
Mario despite all that: spawning displacement.
When Mario is standing on a moving platform
that suddenly disappears, the platform will
displace him for one additional frame despite
no longer existing. When the platform unloads
because of Mario exiting the level via the
pause menu, collecting a star or even dying,
this extra frame of displacement is applied
to Mario as he spawns in the castle.
Now, for a regular moving platform, this effect
is barely noticeable. But for a rotating platform,
displacement is applied as a rotation
from the platform’s center. As such,
objects are moved proportionally to
their distance to the center. And
that is precisely why this glitch can be useful.
Here’s what Pannenkoek did. He cloned the
red coin star using one of the bob-ombs,
and collected it while standing on the
moving spinner. The level unloads with
the spinner rotating clockwise and Mario still
standing on it. Now, when the castle loads,
it occupies the same coordinate system
as Tick Tock Clock, but in a completely
different way. The position of the spinner
in Tick Tock Clock ends up far enough away
from where Mario is spawned that the rotational
displacement is greatly magnified. As a result,
Mario is moved down significantly enough that
he ends up landing on the clock instead of
in front of it. One of the six A presses
to enter Tick Tock Clock had been saved.
There’s just one tiny caveat: this glitch
was fixed immediately after release, which
means that it is only present in the Japanese
version of the game. In every subsequent release,
including North American and PAL, this
glitch has been patched. Therefore,
this A press save came with an asterisk:
it had to be done on the Japanese Nintendo
64 version of the game. This is
as valid a version as any other,
so there was no inherent problem with it,
but it’s just something to keep in mind.
Another unfortunate detail is that while
this looked extremely promising at first,
it actually couldn’t be used for
any other Tick Tock Clock star,
because since they’re all already present from
stage load, they cannot be cloned. Collecting
a star on a moving platform, especially
with conditions as precise as they need
to be to save the re-entry A press, was
simply not possible for any other star.
May 2015. Bob-omb Battlefield had been
mostly solved for over four years now,
ever since the 20-star 0 A press TAS.
There was just one single A press left,
but it was a tough one. Mario Wings to the
Sky, with its coins high up in the air,
always looked like one of those stars that would
never be done in 0 A presses. It’s impossible for
Mario to start flying without a triple jump or
a cannon shot, both of which require an A press,
and while shell hyperspeed could be
used to reach the first three coins,
getting these two without flying was unthinkable.
There was the outside possibility of using goomba
clones to reach the coins, but because of the
exponential nature of goomba bridges, that was
quickly ruled out as impossible without a major
breakthrough. And a major breakthrough is exactly
what happened. Just one week after spawning
displacement, Pannenkoek shocked the world when
he put to use the latest advancements in goomba
engineering: the goomba cluster and goomba oasis.
I mentioned before that when Mario
throws an object, to help create a
seamless transition during Mario’s throwing
animation, the object is warped to the HOLP,
but not to its exact position. To be more precise,
the object is warped 32 units ahead of the HOLP,
in whichever direction Mario is facing.
This means that if two objects are thrown
remotely to the same HOLP while Mario is facing
different angles, the two objects will end up
at slightly different positions. Goombas
with partially overlapping hitboxes can
be interacted with one by one with the right
positioning. This is called a goomba cluster.
In the past, a goomba bridge had to be
built by placing the HOLP for every goomba,
causing the amount of goombas in a
bridge to increase exponentially with
its length. With this new key development,
multiple goombas could be released at the
same HOLP but at slightly different angles,
allowing the HOLP to be reused. Therefore,
the bridge could be built by placing the
HOLP only once for every step of the bridge.
Any given step of the bridge only required
one goomba clone for every step beyond it,
causing the amount of goombas in the bridge to
only increase quadratically with its length. So,
a bridge of length 8 that would have required
255 goombas in the past only required 36 now.
But 36 goombas is still a high enough
number that you can’t build two of those
bridges without crashing the game, so both
coins had to be collected in one go. Just
reaching the general area where the fourth
and fifth coins were located wasn’t enough:
there needed to be something there to
help Mario stay in the air long enough
to maneuver between the two coins. This is
where the goomba oasis came to save the day.
The idea is actually fairly simple. Transport
cloning moves the object to the halfway point
between its original position and the HOLP
laterally, but to the HOLP’s Y coordinate.
When the original object is a goomba, its original
position isn’t always the same. Like most enemies,
goombas have a radius around their home in
which they can run around freely. Therefore,
even if the HOLP is fixed, two goomba clones
released via transport cloning can end up in
different locations. In other words, for
any given HOLP and a goomba’s home circle,
transport cloning can move that goomba to
a circle half the size of the original,
and halfway between the goomba’s home and
the HOLP laterally, at the HOLP’s height.
More specifically, transport cloning could
allow any amount of goombas to be placed
anywhere inside of this circle, using
one single HOLP. This is a goomba oasis.
Here’s exactly what Pannen did. First, he needed
to place the HOLP here, at just about the fifth
coin’s height, so that the resulting transport
cloning zone would cover the space around the
fourth and fifth coins. He did so by using 28
goombas to build a goomba bridge of length 7 using
goomba clusters. Once the HOLP was set in the
correct spot, he could pause exit and reenter the
level to get rid of all of these goomba clones.
After collecting the first three coins with shell
hyperspeed, he could start cloning goombas again.
He built a goomba oasis in this zone by transport
cloning 7 goombas from this trio at various
positions. Those would help guide Mario between
the two highest coins. If you look closely,
you’ll notice that because of transport cloning’s
limitations, the goombas are all at the exact
same height, which is the HOLP’s Y coordinate.
Then, he built a goomba bridge of length 8 to
reach this point from the top of the mountain,
using 36 goombas. Once everything was in place,
he could finally pull off this masterpiece.
To reiterate, this A press save was made
possible by the ability of the goomba
cluster and the goomba oasis to reuse one HOLP
to place multiple goomba clones, which greatly
lowers the amount of clones needed to move
the HOLP and build complex goomba structures.
Meanwhile, a TASer by the name of Kyman showed
something interesting to the ABC crew: in Dire
Dire Docks, if you end up holding a whirlpool
clone and release it, Mario will spiral around
it and die. But if you release it right next to
the loading zone and Mario crosses the plane as
he’s spiraling, the whirlpool unloads and is
replaced with another object. Mario will then
spin around this new object. However, because most
of the time, this new object is very far away,
the rotation quickly flings Mario out of bounds,
killing him instantly. On paper, given an object
far out of bounds at just the right place, it
would be possible for Mario to spin into the
pole that leads to this boxed red coin. But in
reality, such a scenario simply wasn’t possible,
and so the idea, as promising as it was,
was shelved. For about a couple of days.
Kyman had one clip that Tyler Kehne
and Pannenkoek couldn’t make sense of,
where Mario ended up spinning wildly around
the first area of the level. What didn’t make
sense was that Mario seemingly warped across the
entire map before he started spinning. But then,
Pannen realized what was happening. The
glitch isn’t that Mario warps across the map:
it’s that he doesn’t when he should.
This is No translation loading.
Levels are always contained within a square
between negative and positive 8192 in both
directions. Dire Dire Docks is bigger than that:
this is why it’s cut up into two rooms with a
loading zone in between. The rooms occupy
the same space in the coordinate system,
so the end of the tunnel in the first room doesn’t
line up with the same point in the second room.
When Mario crosses the loading trigger and the
loaded area switches from one to the other,
he needs to be translated to the same
location in the new room. The offset
happens to be 8192 units, or half the size
of the map. This translation happens every
time Mario crosses the loading trigger
and it results in a seamless experience.
Now, if Mario is spinning around a
whirlpool clone, he can end up crossing
the loading zone in an unconventional way. The
whirlpool spins Mario towards out of bounds,
but he crosses the loading zone, so he
ends up in bounds in the new room. The
game tries to translate him to match the new
coordinate system, but doing so would place
him out of bounds. Unlike the rotation
from the whirlpool, which can send Mario
out of bounds, the loading zone translation
can’t put him out of bounds, so it chooses
not to move him at all. This is how he ends up
in the middle of the first room out of nowhere.
Once he understood the implications of this
discovery, Pannenkoek got to work and used
it to save the A press to reach the final red
coin. He ended up finding a set of conditions
that worked perfectly. First, he placed the HOLP
in the second room in a point that corresponds
to just outside of the tunnel in the first
room. Then, he remote released a whirlpool
clone using the hat in hand glitch. When Mario
gets caught in, he starts spinning towards out
of bounds. As he crosses the loading zone,
the translation failsafe is triggered and
so he ends up in the middle of this room. Now,
he would keep spinning around the whirlpool,
but it unloaded and was replaced by this cork
box. Therefore, he now spins around this box on
an arc that conveniently happens to pass right
on the corner of this platform. Fortunately,
Mario touching the floor interrupts the spin
- otherwise, he would keep spinning to his
eventual death. From there, he can reach the
final red coin with no additional A press.
Note that for Mario to be able to swim with the
shell and clone stuff, the A button needs to be
held throughout, so the star went from 1.5 to
0.5 A presses. Despite being well established
in the A Button Challenge, the half A press
notation never failed to confuse new viewers.
At the same time, in Jolly Roger Bay, Pannen and
Tyler were working on a way to pound the blue
coin box without an A press for the 100-coin star.
They knew that a goomba bounce would do the trick,
but these goombas’ homes were too far
from the box. Running into the goombas
could give a bit of extra distance, but
not enough to make it possible. Until
Tyler found a clever abuse of the goomba’s
mechanics called the goomba chase extension.
A goomba chasing after Mario will quit chasing him
if it moves too far from its home, if Mario moves
too far from its home, or if Mario moves too far
from the goomba itself. The goomba chases Mario
by setting its target angle towards him. However,
if the goomba walks into a ledge, a steep slope,
a wall or another goomba, it recalculates its
current target angle, which means it’s no longer
targeting Mario. After that, it turns until it
faces the new target angle, then stops chasing.
After carefully manipulating goombas, Pannen was
able to get a goomba to chase Mario, then run into
the rock, then into the wall, then into the other
goomba. So, before it has time to face its target
angle, it runs into a new obstacle that causes
it to recalculate its target angle and extend its
chase. Finally, it runs close enough to the box
that Mario can bounce on it and save an A press.
July 2015. The addition of Tyler Kehne to the ABC
crew had ushered the A Button challenge into a new
golden era. The introduction of vertical speed
conservation, misalignments and star dance clips
revolutionized the challenge like only Pannenkoek
had done before. In the past year and a half,
the A press count had been lowered by
an incredible 80%, from 208 to 40. While
Pannenkoek and Tyler were showing no signs of
stopping, each additional A press was becoming
harder and harder to save. Options were starting
to dry out. But Tyler Kehne hadn’t even made
his most legendary contribution yet. It was
time for Mario to enter parallel universes.
On July 11th, Tyler Kehne was looking for ways to
get even more speed than the 500 from repeatedly
sliding on this slope. He found this corner,
where the open gate created a ceiling barrier.
Because he’s walking uphill on a slippery slope,
Mario accelerates backwards, but he’s right up
against a ceiling. Unlike walls, ceilings don’t
push Mario sideways out of their hitbox. If Mario
is in the air and moves forward into a ceiling,
that will result in a bonk. As a quick aside,
ceiling hitboxes technically extend infinitely
upwards, unless there’s a floor above them. The
annoyance commonly referred to as invisible
walls is actually caused by exposed ceilings
that don’t have a floor directly above
them, usually due to imperfect geometry.
When Mario is on the ground and about to enter a
ceiling hitbox or out of bounds, he simply doesn’t
move at all. He still conserves his speed, but
he looks like he’s pushing up against something
and he stays in place. This is what Tyler uses to
accumulate hundreds of speed: the underside of the
gate is a ceiling that prevents Mario from moving
into it. Once Mario has enough speed to completely
bypass the ceiling, he breaks out of this spot
and zooms across the room into the water. Instead
of the 500 speed that Plush achieved using the
middle island, Mario now has 1700 speed. But then,
Tyler found that Mario could turn around to have
his back facing out of bounds. The ceiling had a
limit, but out of bounds is infinite. Tyler
Kehne had discovered infinite speed without
the A button. Immediately, this discovery
was used to improve Watch for Rolling Rocks.
This star had always had the problem
of requiring Mario to reach one of the
highest points in the entire level.
Despite the ABC crew’s best efforts,
the intended wall kick strategy was still optimal,
so it had been sitting at 2 A presses since the
dawn of time. But this was about to change. With
so much stored speed, Mario could simply do this.
How does that work? Well, again, it’s surprisingly
simple. Mario exits water on Dorrie’s slippery
back, reactivating the stored sliding speed.
Then, he enters freefall and lands on the path.
As he lands, he instantly jumps. I’ve mentioned
this before, but this is now critically relevant:
the vertical speed of Mario’s jump is a function
of his horizontal speed. The faster he goes,
the higher he jumps. With 1500 speed, one
jump gets him enough vertical speed to soar
to the upper limit of the stage. But if
he has so much speed, how come he jumps
straight up? Because he dives! Like I said
before, a dive increases Mario speed by 15,
up to a maximum of 48. Well, this 48 is a hard
cap. If Mario is moving at 33 speed or higher
and he dives, regardless of how fast he was
going, his speed will be set to exactly 48.
Even though Mario jumps and dives on the
same frame, the initial vertical speed of
his jump is calculated before the hard cap
of 48 is applied to his horizontal speed,
so he inherits this astronomical vertical speed
while stopping his horizontal momentum before
he smashes against the edge of the map. From
there, Mario can slowly navigate above the
level and fall onto the star, bringing down
this relic of the past to one single A press.
With this new tool in hand, Hazy Maze Cave
looked much more solvable than before. The
stage was down to three A presses, in Watch
for Rolling Rocks, A-Maze-ing Emergency Exit,
and the red coin star. In order to make this newly
found high speed in the cavern useful, though,
there needed to be a way to bring the speed up
the level without jumping. The answer was simple:
just take the elevator. But there was one
problem: when Mario has this much speed,
his next intended position is out of bounds, so
he can’t move. Mario ends up staying in place
while the elevator moves through him. Until Plush
and sonicpacker had something to say about it.
When Mario is about to go out of bounds,
only his horizontal displacement is canceled,
not his vertical movement. By kicking repeatedly,
Mario moves up and can stay on the elevator,
at the cost of a bit of speed and a half
A press. This allows Mario to go nearly
anywhere in the level with a very high
horizontal speed. Plush figured out a
route that would carry Mario all the
way up to A-Maze-ing Emergency exit,
but he ran out of speed a little too quickly and
couldn’t clip through the final door. Pannenkoek
took over and optimized it just enough to make it
possible and bring the star down to 0.5 A presses.
Meanwhile, the red coin star could get the same
treatment, but Pannen needed a tiny bit of height
to get past this gap and navigate to the red
coins room. It was time to ask his old friend the
scuttlebug for help. Up until now, every enemy’s
home has always been a fixed point. This is
true for Chuckya, Fly Guy, goombas, bob-ombs and
scuttlebugs alike. But there is an exception. If a
scuttlebug runs into Mario, its home will move to
its current position, effectively redefining the
zone it can move in. This can happen infinitely
many times, which means a scuttlebug can move
arbitrarily far, provided that Mario has enough
health to take a beating. Fortunately, there
is a spinning heart right here. Unfortunately,
scuttlebugs can’t travel across the entire level
at will. They can’t go through doors, so they’re
actually confined to their room. Here though,
it wasn’t necessary, because Pannen only needed
the scuttlebug to move close to the door. Then,
he gathered some speed, took the elevator
up, and bounced on the scuttlebug to cross
the gap and complete his trip to the red coin
room. Another star brought to 0.5 A presses.
The only star remaining was Watch for
Rolling Rocks. Getting it down to 1 A
press with hyperspeed had been relatively
simple, but the task of bringing it to
0.5 was something else entirely. Although this
platform could be reached like we saw earlier,
it could only be ledge grabbed, which kills
Mario’s momentum. It also wasn’t high enough:
the Watch for Rolling Rocks platform is
significantly higher. Pannenkoek wasn’t
deterred. He still had a few ideas to make
it work, including Tyler Kehne’s discovery
of infinite speed with hyperspeed walking.
It would require a lot more time and effort,
though, and so that star remained
at 1 A press for the time being­.
While it couldn’t quite be used
for Watch for Rolling Rocks,
infinite speed in Hazy Maze Cave turned
out to have an unexpected application. It
was used to solve one of very few remaining
trivial A presses of the entire challenge,
in what is perhaps the starkest contrast
between the complexity of the 1 A press
and the 0 A press strategy: entering the Secret
Aquarium. Buckle up because this is a big one.
First of all, how can speed in one level have
any effect on the castle interior? Again,
the key ingredient is sliding speed conservation.
Swimming is a situation where sliding speed and
horizontal speed no longer line up, but it’s
not the only one. During a stage transition,
like a death, a pause exit or entering a
pipe, the horizontal speed is reset to zero,
but the sliding speed isn’t. In almost every
case, though, the sliding speed is set to zero
immediately after the transition, so it makes
no difference. But in the case of a pause exit,
it’s possible for Mario to crouch on the
very first frame after the transition.
When Mario is crouching, he automatically
starts sliding if he has any momentum. So,
by crouching immediately after a
pause exit with stored sliding speed,
Mario can conserve that sliding
speed through the stage transition.
However, exiting a stage with stored sliding speed
is not as simple as it looks: Mario normally needs
to be considered idle for the exit level option to
be available in the first place. If Mario is idle,
then he’s by definition not moving. It is
nonetheless possible in a few specific cases where
either the sliding speed isn’t being updated, such
as when Mario is in water or holding onto a pole,
or it hasn’t had time to update, like on the
first frame of a ledge grab, landing from a twirl,
and a few others. Fortunately, Hazy Maze Cave
has the lake, so Mario is able to accumulate
some speed, then conserve it into the castle
lobby with a pause exit while he’s in the water.
But how much speed does he need? Well, the
answer is complicated. You see, the goal is
to reach the ledge of the Secret Aquarium entrance
without any vertical momentum to help. To do that,
Mario needs to be moving from a high
enough platform, but as it turns out,
this ledge is the highest platform in the entire
area. The only places high enough to be of any use
are the 1-up alcove across the room, the alcove
to the Princess’s Secret Slide, and the hallway
leading to Bowser in the Dark World. Between
these, the hallway to Bowser in the Dark World
is by far the easiest to reach, and everything
else is too low to attempt a ledge grab from.
Mario would need a very large amount of speed to
travel pretty much instantly between those points,
but it is technically possible. The problem now
is reaching this point with that amount of speed.
The only possible way of ascending up to
the Bowser in the Dark World hallway is to
go up the central stairs of the lobby. But with
this much speed, Mario can’t get up the stairs:
he either gets stuck in place as he’s trying
to move out of bounds, or he zips through
and into the hallway to the courtyard. Once
his speed is low enough to climb the stairs,
it can’t be brought back up to do the ledge grab.
This route looked impossible. So, Tyler Kehne and
Pannenkoek had to think outside the box. Actually,
not outside the box: outside the universe.
If you remember, a misalignment is a 1x1 unit
square on the corner of a platform that exists
because the floor detection function converts
Mario’s position from a 32-bit floating point
number by rounding it down to a 16-bit integer.
The limitations of 16-bit integers actually
go both ways: both in precision and in
scale. We’ve seen this with the water
level overflow in Wet-Dry World. If you add
one to an integer’s maximum value of 32767,
the variable wraps around to its
lowest possible value, -32768,
and vice versa. What happened with the water
level can also happen with Mario’s position.
But remember, this conversion is only made
specifically for the floor detection. Mario’s
actual position always remains a floating point
number, which can well exceed 32 thousand, up to
basically infinity. If Mario’s position exceeds
the integer limit, when it comes to detecting if
Mario has a floor under him, his position will be
truncated to a number within the integer limit.
Essentially, his real position and the floor
detection position become disjointed. If the
truncated integer position happens to line up
with a floor, no matter how far Mario’s actual
position is, the floor detection function will
say that yes, Mario is standing on a floor. But
instead of thinking about it in terms of Mario
having two different positions simultaneously,
it’s easier to think of it as there being
infinite copies of the entire map’s floors 65
thousand units away in every direction. It
doesn’t matter that there isn’t an actual
copy of the floor out there. So long
as the game believes there is a floor,
Mario will be able to stand there.
Functionally, there is no difference.
These so-called infinite copies of
the map are named parallel universes,
or PUs for short. Because only the floor detection
has this bug, parallel universes have no objects,
no water, no walls, no textures, only floors
and ceilings. The typical map size is roughly 16
thousand units, so only about one sixteenth of
the total space is filled - everything else is
considered out of bounds and inaccessible. The
only way to reach a parallel universe is to have
so much speed that Mario travels this distance
instantaneously, in a single frame. Once Mario
reaches a parallel universe, he must preserve
this speed, because if he loses it, there’s no
way to get it back and return to the main map.
But in fact, just having 65 thousand speed is
not enough to go to a parallel universe. This is
because of a quirk of Super Mario 64’s physics.
When Mario is trying to move, his movement is
subdivided in four steps called quartersteps.
For any given frame, the game will check at
each quarterstep of the way for any obstacles.
Walls push Mario to the edge of their hitbox and
allow him to keep moving, but ceilings and out of
bounds prevent Mario from moving altogether.
So, if Mario only has enough speed to reach
the first parallel universe, the game will
actually check one quarter of the way through
and only find out of bounds, so he will not be
moved. For Mario to be able to travel to a PU,
he needs each quarterstep to be on a valid floor.
Therefore, he needs four times the speed, or 262
thousand, and will travel through four PUs
in a single frame. This is called one QPU.
Now, if Mario has a speed that
is an exact multiple of 65536,
his floor detection position, which we’ll call
his relative position, stays exactly the same.
Pannenkoek called this the syncing speed,
as in the speed where his position syncs up
with the PUs. By deviating slightly from the
syncing speed, Mario can travel relatively
forwards and backwards. By turning ever so
slightly, he can move relatively sideways,
but even the tiniest angle changes end
up greatly magnified over PU distances.
This is the key to solving the movement
to the Bowser in the Dark World hallway.
If Mario achieves PU speed, he can have
a relative speed that allows him to move
slowly up the lobby staircase, then wait for
his speed to go down until it drops low enough
to travel in the main map, from the hallway
across to the ledge. But the reality is a bit
more complicated than that for two reasons.
First, when Mario is moving with PU speed,
he is traveling absurd distances. He needs
to somehow be able to navigate these parallel
universes in such a way that he is led back
to the main map at the end. This problem
can be solved with the right amount of planning,
which, as it turns out, is a shitton of planning.
But the second, more concerning problem, is the
staircase. Well actually, the problem is that this
is not a staircase. Because of the properties of
wall hitboxes, this staircase is too steep to be
a series of individual steps. It would end up as
a worse version of the staircase to the basement,
which already has some odd behaviour due to the
steps being too close to each other. Instead,
this is a slope, and like all slopes,
it changes Mario’s de facto speed.
As a quick refresher, the de facto speed is
the actual distance that Mario travels, which
is a factor of the horizontal component of the
slope he’s currently on. The steeper the slope,
the lower the de facto speed. Now, when Mario
steps on the slope with PU speed, his lower de
facto speed will cause him to attempt to move a
shorter distance which no longer syncs up with
a PU and leaves him stuck in place. In other
words, the syncing speed is not a fixed number:
it depends on the steepness of the slope that
Mario is standing on. The steeper the slope,
the higher the syncing speed needed to
keep the de facto speed constant. This
specific slope has a syncing speed of
381 thousand. So, now, Mario needs 262
thousand speed to move onto the staircase, then
381 thousand speed to move up the staircase,
and back down to 262 thousand to travel to the
Bowser hallway. Once Mario leaves the hyperspeed
walking spot, he can no longer gain any more
speed. Again, we’ve run into a dealbreaker.
The solution? Simply build up more speed!
Remember, hyperspeed walking allows Mario
to speed up slowly, but infinitely. So this
is what Pannenkoek did. He doubled up the
initial speed to 524 thousand, so that Mario
could travel two QPUs per frame instead. After
conserving that speed into the castle lobby,
he could reach the staircase, then lower his
speed down to 381 thousand, go up the slope,
lower his speed again to 262 thousand, and
move over to the Bowser hallway. Finally,
with the right speed, he could snap back to
reality right at the Secret Aquarium ledge,
and turn an incredibly simple A press into an
insane 25-hour marathon. Yes, you heard me right:
25 hours. Doesn’t matter, though, they saved an
A press. They saved an A press, right? Right?
Unfortunately, this strategy, which was obviously
done on an emulator, was not possible on a real
Nintendo 64. When Mario travels to a parallel
universe, the camera tries to follow him,
which crashes the console every time. Unless
you use the option to hold R to fix the camera
in place, in which case it is possible to
navigate to a PU without crashing. However,
you can’t fix the camera in the castle interior,
so even that couldn’t save them. Unlike everything
that had been done thus far, this strategy could
not be replicated on an physical Nintendo 64.
But what about Wii Virtual Console?
It is an official release, and it is
an emulator. As it turns out, Wii VC does
not crash when the camera moves to a PU,
so this amazing A press save
could technically live on,
so long as the challenge was to be done on
the Wii Virtual Console release of the game,
not on Nintendo 64. But there’s one little detail
I told you to keep in mind: spawning displacement,
used to save a re-entry A press in Tick Tock
Clock, is a Japanese exclusive glitch. Does
that mean the optimal A button challenge was now
limited to the Japanese VC release of the game?
Surprisingly, no. In 1997, Nintendo released an
updated Japanese version of the game with Rumble
Pak support called the Shindou version, where
Backwards Long Jumping was famously patched
and Mario’s voice ruined. This version also has
all of the North American and PAL version fixes,
including spawning displacement. The Japanese
VC release is the Shindou version. Since no VC
release can do spawning displacement, switching
to VC to save an A press lost the Tick Tock Clock
re-entry A press save, ultimately resulting
in no improvement. Therefore, despite this
technically constituting an A press save, it
did not end up lowering the A press count.
In the meantime, Pannenkoek’s YouTube channel
was starting to garner a lot of attention.
His most popular content wasn’t the A Button
Challenge, but unrelated, usually commentated
videos about interesting discoveries, like
collecting the fabled impossible coin,
or exploring the secrets of the Mystery
Goomba. He began to cement his place in
the YouTube sphere as an expert Super
Mario 64 scientist. But nothing he had
published before got as much press and public
attention than the Tick Tock Clock Upwarp.
The story goes like this: Kyman had stumbled upon
an old Twitch video from 2013 of a speedrunner
named DOTA_Teabag, who saw Mario inexplicably
warp significantly upwards in Tick Tock Clock.
This was potentially groundbreaking because
an upwarp of this magnitude that seemingly
didn’t require the A button could reshape
the future of the A Button Challenge,
particularly in Tick Tock Clock of all places.
The potential was so huge that Pannen decided
to put a 1000 dollar bounty for whoever
could replicate the glitch in an emulator
and provide an input file that could be
analyzed to make sense of this anomaly.
Money speaks, and so thousands of people, for the
most part completely inexperienced, haphazardly
smashed their face against the wall hoping for the
golden ticket to the top of the clock. There was
little information to go by other than a somewhat
mediocre quality video, but with such a revolution
right around the corner, the collective motivation
to crack the mystery was enormous. Countless news
articles were written about it. Even as recently
as 2021, Derek Muller from Veritasium covered the
subject in a video with over 17 million views.
But as time went on, with no one managing to
get anywhere close to replicating it, the ABC crew
realized that there had to be another explanation.
Years after the fact, the commonly accepted
explanation is a hardware malfunction causing
a bitflip at Mario’s vertical position.
Flipping a specific bit in the position
in similar conditions achieves just about the
exact same result as was observed back then.
The popular explanation is a cosmic ray, but the
exact cause behind the bitflip is impossible to
know for sure. As promising as it initially
looked, this discovery ended up shelved as
a one-off hardware issue that could not be
used in speedruns or the A Button Challenge.
Nonetheless, there was still one Tick Tock Clock
discovery that ended up crucial for the challenge:
the Pedro spot. Originally found in Cool, Cool
Mountain by Pedro Viktor in November 2014, a
Pedro spot is a point where a floor and a ceiling
meet in a very specific way. When Mario lands onto
a Pedro spot, he would snap up to the floor,
but that point is inside the ceiling hitbox,
which prevents him from moving. The landing action
happens before the collision with the ceiling,
so Mario doesn’t bonk on it. But since Mario
is prevented from moving, he stays suspended
in midair. From this odd double state, he
can both jump and ground pound. But also,
he can build up forwards speed without moving,
similarly to hyperspeed walking. This is limited
by the geometry around him: at high enough
speeds, he ends up breaking out of the spot.
With no ability to turn or otherwise redirect
Mario’s speed, Pedro spots are a bit limited
in what they can achieve. But when Tyler Kehne
found a Pedro spot here, in Tick Tock Clock,
he realized it had excellent potential to bring
Stomp on the Thwomp’s 7 A presses down. Mario
couldn’t get in position by himself: he needed
a bob-omb to push him in place. The clock also
had to be on the still setting, which meant that
the spinners typically used to travel up the clock
with a bob-omb in 0 A presses could not be used.
Instead, four A presses were required to jump up,
and instant release was used to place the
bob-omb out of bounds to be reactivated near
the cogs. At first glance, that seems terrible.
But what comes next more than makes up for it.
Mario uses the bob-omb to push himself into the
Pedro spot. Once he builds up over 800 speed,
he’s ready to do a jump dive. Again, with so much
speed, he jumps extremely high, but the dive caps
his speed at 48 instantly. That’s enough to get
all the way up to the top of the clock, where
one final A press gets him the star and brings
Stomp on the Thwomp from 7 down to 6 A presses.
In response to the ever increasing
interest for his commentated videos,
Pannenkoek decided that A Button Challenge
improvements should have accompanying
explanations with voice commentary, so
he made one for Stomp on the Thwomp. He
carefully broke down every element of the
strategy for casual viewers to understand:
the HOLP, instant release, the out
of bounds failsafe, the Pedro spot,
and the high speed jump dive. It was received with
high praise and excitement by his growing fanbase.
In June 2015, Pannenkoek was exploring
scuttlebug transportation and trying to
get a scuttlebug to go through a door.
His attempt proved mildly successful:
he was able to get one scuttlebug to clip
through a door, but then it was stuck next to
the door and would deactivate as soon as Mario
stepped away. While playing around with this,
Pannen found that he could get the
scuttlebug to jump up repeatedly
by running in and out of its activation
zone. He had discovered scuttlebug raising.
The way this works is similar to the
mechanics abused for the Chuckya drop and
Fly Guy manipulation. In levels with multiple
rooms, the inside of a room is only loaded
when Mario is in it, or when he’s standing
close to the door leading to it. Therefore,
a scuttlebug in one room gets deactivated
as soon as Mario steps away from the door
outside of that room. This was used
before in Metal Head Mario can Move!
Similarly to the Fly Guy and Chuckya, a scuttlebug
also has a limited range of actions when it’s
deactivated. Although it won’t move, it can
still turn and lunge at Mario if he enters
the radius around its home. Once the scuttlebug
is reactivated, it will perform that lunge. If
Mario deactivates the scuttlebug in the middle
of the lunge, it will stay in midair. Then,
another lunge can be triggered, and the
scuttlebug can jump again when reactivated.
This process can be repeated indefinitely, and
the scuttlebug can jump up arbitrarily high.
This development seems relatively
insignificant. It’s anything but
that. The final piece of the puzzle
was in place. The last Hazy Maze Cave
A press was ready to be taken off. Watch for
Rolling Rocks in 0.5 A Presses was possible.
The entire route is a culmination of every
discovery made in the past year. First,
scuttlebug transportation was used to move the
scuttlebug below the platform where the star
is. Then, scuttlebug raising was used to make it
jump up. The exact position of the scuttlebug’s
home is crucial here: the cylinder around its home
partially intersects with the area near the door
where the scuttlebug is activated. Mario can enter
the radius without activating the scuttlebug,
which triggers a delayed lunge. Then,
as Mario steps out of the home cylinder,
the scuttlebug turns back towards its home. When
Mario reactivates the scuttlebug, it lunges past
its home. When the process is repeated, the
scuttlebug now turns the other way to jump back
towards its home. As it jumps back and forth,
the result is it moving straight up over time.
Once the scuttlebug is in the correct position,
Pannenkoek moves on to the next part of the plan.
He goes to the lake and builds up speed with
hyperspeed walking, making sure to redirect it out
of bounds. He builds up speed for 12 hours, until
he has 479 thousand. Using the properties of de
facto speed, he’s able to navigate up the path to
the elevator using floor triangles with decreasing
steepnesses so that the syncing speed gradually
comes down over time. Remember: objects aren’t
present in parallel universes, so Mario needs
to return to the main map to board the elevator.
This was made complicated by QPU alignment:
in short, while Mario has enough speed
to travel four PUs in one frame, he doesn’t
necessarily complete all four quartersteps of his
movement action. Mario only moves up to the last
valid quarterstep in a frame. If a quarterstep
leads him out of bounds because the slope changed
or because he’s not quite at the syncing speed,
he can end up moving by a fraction of his total
speed. Doing so misaligns him with regular full
frame movements and he has to do another partial
movement to get back to the main map. The PU
navigation had to be painstakingly planned
out so that everything would line up in the
end. Just like last time, Mario uses repeated
kicks to activate and to stay on the elevator.
Once he reaches the height of the next
elevator, Mario quickly travels to a PU
and back to effectively warp across the map. This
second elevator takes him up to the highest point
he can reach. Pannenkoek sets up his position
in parallel universes in preparation for the
final move, and then, he returns to the main map
on the scuttlebug that he previously positioned
so that he can bounce on it. This actually still
isn’t enough to reach the platform, so he places
himself in a unit-precise spot and ground pounds
into a misalignment at the corner of the platform.
And this is Watch for Rolling Rocks in 0.5 A
presses, the final A press in Hazy Maze Cave gone.
As soon as Pannenkoek pieced everything together
for this A press save, he knew that it had
incredible potential for a detailed explanation
with commentary and visuals. However, college was
taking up his time, and so, despite figuring
out all the steps to do the star in October,
he didn’t actually work on the project
until the holidays. When Christmas came,
he realized that while planning and TASing such
a complex star already was a time-consuming
and energy draining process, creating this
behemoth of a video explanation turned out
to be even more taxing. But the project
had already been shelved for two months,
so with college starting again in
two weeks, he decided to press on.
He pressed on. He had to get it done. He worked
tirelessly, day in, day out. But in the end,
he pressed himself too hard. Pannenkoek was
in a terrible mental space. He was struggling
through issues in his personal life, and
working on this video was not an escape:
it was a purgatory. In the end, what should
have been a passion project turned out
to be the canalization of his own mental
suffering. He completed the entire TAS and
the accompanying video in about 140 hours over
two short weeks. He should have been immensely
proud of his work. He didn’t feel pride. He
didn’t feel accomplished. He felt nothing.
Pannen was used to his videos going viral, but
nothing could prepare him for what would become
of Watch for Rolling Rocks. As it went viral,
it instantly exposed the A Button Challenge to
hundreds of thousands of people for the first time
in their lives. These viewers’ first impression of
the A Button Challenge was this. The incredibly
thorough 24-minute piece was approachable, yet
utterly unbelievable. It was so many levels beyond
what anything these people had ever seen that they
couldn’t help but laugh at the absurdity of it
all. Scuttlebug transportation. Half A presses.
Building speed for 12 hours. Parallel universes.
QPU alignment. Every single concept of the video
seemed like made up nonsense in some over-the-top
absurdist humor. Yet all of it was real.
Watch for Rolling Rocks in 0.5 A
presses rapidly became not just a meme,
but a family of memes that played on
the chasm between casual gameplay and
top-level speedruns or tool-assisted runs.
The ABC crew members were not just geniuses,
they were the gods of Super Mario 64. To this
day, the video has over 4 million views and
the memes that stemmed from it made their way
into unexpectedly far reaches of the Internet.
Meanwhile, Pannenkoek spent the winter
semester mentally recovering from his
breakdown during the holidays. Part of that
recovery process was establishing that the
pressure he was putting on himself to
always improve the production value
of his channel was destructive. He realized
that this mindset would ultimately lead him
into a spiral of ever increasing workloads
until nothing would ever get done again.
With the unprecedented success of the latest ABC
video, public pressure on him to keep creating
similar content was mounting. Memes about half A
presses and scuttlebug jamborees were parroted in
every comment section of not just his videos,
but pretty much every Super Mario 64 video out
there. Pannenkoek was being reminded of the
video and its nightmarish production cycle
at just about every corner. His mental scars
were still fresh, so he knew there was no way
he would make anything of the scale of Watch
for Rolling Rocks until he would actually feel
ready to undertake the project. It’s widely
believed that the memes were the reason
Pannenkoek quit making commentated videos, but
they actually were a tiny factor in the equation.
The main reason behind it is quite simply that
he doesn’t enjoy making voice commentary, and
making such videos represented too much tedious
work unless they were exceptionally worth it.
So, after releasing that video, he decided
to switch his mindset. A Button Challenge
videos would go on his secondary channel,
which he renamed UncommentatedPannen,
and where he felt zero pressure to make
high-effort content. The first step was
to release a bunch of ABC improvements he
had been holding onto since the discovery
of scuttlebug raising in October, until
he could get around to making commentated
explanations. So, on January 13th, 2016,
he dumped five improvements at once,
then went relatively inactive in the A Button
Challenge for the better part of the year,
instead focusing on glitch documentation and
explanation videos on his secondary channel.
Every improvement from Pannen’s backlog stemmed
from the discovery of scuttlebug raising. It
helped eliminate the half A press left in the two
other Hazy Maze Cave stars that used hyperspeed
and elevators. First, A-Maze-ing Emergency Exit,
solved by raising a scuttlebug for half an hour
until it would jump into the right spot for
Mario to bounce across to the star, and second,
the red coin star. For this one, Pannen needed
to get the scuttlebug from the red coins room
high up in the air. He could manipulate it from
the first room, but only if the scuttlebug was in
the perfect position. To get it in the perfect
spot, he had to go down in the red coins room.
To go back to the first room, he needed to
cross this gap in no A presses. Thankfully,
two scuttlebugs could be transported over and
Mario could bounce on them both to go back to
the red coins room. From there, just one hour
of scuttlebug raising was sufficient to have
the scuttlebug fall on Mario to dismount
the pole, saving another half A press.
The other applications of scuttlebug raising
were in Big Boo’s Haunt, and they were a bit
more involved. Here, one A press was left
to grab the star in the Merry-go-Round,
and one was required to reach the top
floor of the mansion for both Big Boo’s
Balcony and Eye-to-Eye in the Secret Room.
Let’s start with Big Boo’s Merry-go-Round.
Pannen got a scuttlebug into a specific spot
against the side of the mansion with scuttlebug
transportation. Then, by alternating between going
near the scuttlebug to get it to turn around,
and activating it by standing by the front door,
Pannen was able to raise the scuttlebug. How much
does he raise it, do you ask? Well, only about
ten times - sorry - ten hours. After ten hours,
the scuttlebug is so high up that it has
entered a vertical parallel universe.
Vertical parallel universes, or VPUs for short,
function slightly differently than regular
PUs do. Here, it’s the vertical position that
overflows rather than the horizontal position.
The result is different for Mario than it is
for enemies, so let’s look at what happens
specifically to the scuttlebug when it reaches
a VPU. When the position initially overflows,
the scuttlebug’s floor detection
doesn’t find any floor under itself,
so its behaviour becomes a big more erratic.
Instead of turning towards Mario, it spins in
place. Pannen can still keep raising it just fine
despite that limitation. Once it gets even higher,
it reaches the mansion relatively in the VPU,
but floors and ceilings are not solid. So,
it can keep raising through and above the virtual
map. Once it’s high enough, Pannen reactivates the
scuttlebug and it jumps down. Again, because
floors and ceilings are not solid in VPUs,
the scuttlebug goes through the level and into
the basement, where it collides with the wall.
Contrarily to regular PUs, VPUs do have solid
walls, and they have a peculiar property: when
the scuttlebug collides with the wall, it gets
snapped to the wall’s height, in the main map.
To summarize, the scuttlebug is raised for
10 hours until it enters a vertical parallel
universe so it can fall through the floor and
reach a position relative to the merry-go-round in
the basement. Then, it collides with a wall that
snaps it back to the main map. At the same time,
Mario leaves the scuttlebug’s activation range,
so it stops moving there. When Mario enters the
Merry-go-round, the scuttlebug remains deactivated
because it’s hardcoded to belong to the outside
of the mansion, no matter where it actually
is. Despite being deactivated and invisible,
the scuttlebug is still tangible, so
Mario can bounce on it and reach the star.
The other application of scuttlebug raising was
to reach the highest floor of the mansion. The
idea is quite similar, but instead, three
different scuttlebugs are moved to roughly
the same location and simultaneously raised for
13 hours into a VPU. After reactivating them,
Pannenkoek precisely guides them into the room
leading to the top floor, where they collide
with a wall that snaps them back to the main map.
After a little bit of additional manipulation,
he’s able to stagger them in a staircase leading
to the upper ledge. Again, because the scuttlebugs
belong to the exterior, when he goes near
them, they are invisible and stuck in mid-air,
but they are still tangible. Instead of
a sideflip and two bookends, Pannenkoek
uses one bookend to get up on this step, then the
other bookend and the three carefully positioned
scuttlebugs to reach the top floor and save
the two final A presses in Big Boo’s Haunt.
During 2016, despite the relative inactivity of
the ABC crew, thanks to the universal acclaim
of Watch for Rolling Rocks, the A Button
Challenge saw a large influx of fans eager
to contribute to new strategy developments. The
crew grew larger and larger. But so much work
had already been done that it would take
a long time for newcomers to start making
any meaningful progress. Or maybe all it took
was just to look at a star with a fresh pair
of eyes. I’ve left the best improvement
for last: Wing Mario over the Rainbow.
This star was famously used by Pannenkoek as an
example to demonstrate the half A press notation.
Two A presses were very clearly needed to shoot
the cannon twice in order to get all the red
coins, but in order to reach the first cannon, a
half A press was also required so that Mario would
fall down slower to the cannon platform. Until
Super Mario 64 expert sm64expert found this.
Yep, that’s it. Instead of just running up,
if you do a dive recover before the slidekick,
you have just enough speed to
make it without the slower fall.
Near the end of 2016, what used to be just
a small group of friends calling themselves
the ABC crew was now a full blown community.
Millions of people had heard of the A Button
Challenge. Pannenkoek was a superstar. Tens of
thousands were following developments closely,
celebrating each new upload, even if it was all
on his secondary channel by then. But soon enough,
the wave of newcomers realized something:
the task at hand was monumental. The A Press
count was now at 32. Exactly half of
those were for Tick Tock Clock alone,
and the other half for the rest of the entire
game. This was the dawn of the Modern Era.
An era defined by the seemingly hopeless
uphill battle of solving Tick Tock Clock.
Pannenkoek was still in a period of relative
inactivity. Despite some developments being
made in 2016, nothing was released until
November, when he put out a pair of
improvements that had been discovered months
prior. The first one was in Jolly Roger Bay.
The side wall of the ship is actually not always
a wall. This is because the status of floor,
wall or ceiling is not an inherent property of
a given triangle. It depends on its orientation.
A triangle that is facing generally upwards is a
floor, one that is facing downwards is a ceiling,
and any triangle facing sideways
is a wall. But as it turns out,
for a triangle to be treated as a wall, it
needs to be nearly perfectly vertical. As
soon as it tilts just a little bit,
it becomes a floor or a ceiling.
As the ship sways to one side, this wall
temporarily becomes a floor for just long
enough that Mario can framewalk up. It was
refreshing for the ABC crew to stumble upon
a relatively simple A press save. Little did
they know that this would be the final one.
The other development came in Tick Tock Clock.
While in the past, the ABC had done its fair
share of RNG manipulation when dealing with
Chuckya, goombas and moving coins, these baby
steps paled in comparison to the most advanced
form of RNG abuse yet: pendulum manipulation.
On the random setting, the clock’s moving parts
rely heavily on the RNG value to determine
their pattern. The pendulum is one of them.
However, its behaviour is pretty barebones:
at the end of each swing, it calls the
RNG function. Two thirds of the time,
it swings slowly. One third of the time, it swings
faster. The pendulum accelerates until its angle
goes beyond zero, at which point it slows down
at the same speed, ending up at roughly the
same angle on the other side. No matter if it
swings fast or slow, this fact doesn’t change:
the pendulum always has the same, somewhat narrow
range of motion. Until something strange happens.
Because the pendulum accelerates until its angle
goes beyond zero, if it somehow passes directly
at zero, it will accelerate on that frame
and start slowing down on the next. However,
when it comes back the other way, if it passes
at zero again, it will also keep accelerating
for one more frame. Effectively, if the pendulum
is on either side, it will experience a force
pulling towards the center. But if it’s
exactly in the center, it will experience
a force in the same direction as its movement,
resulting in a net increase in total energy.
The pendulum’s range of motion therefore keeps
increasing for each swing passing through zero.
Now, two questions remain: how does the pendulum
suddenly start passing through angle zero,
and how can it keep passing through angle
zero repeatedly? Well, those are really just
the same question: how can we manipulate
the pendulum to do exactly what we want?
When the pendulum chooses a fast or a slow
swing, the option it chooses slightly changes
where it will cross the middle point, and
therefore where it will stop on the other
side. If the acceleration was a fixed value,
like on the slow, fast and still settings,
the pendulum would always swing between the same
two points. In fact, whenever the random pendulum
chooses the same speed twice in a row, it returns
precisely to the same point after two swings. But
if it chooses a different speed on every swing,
the slight variation in where it crosses the
middle point causes the pendulum to never quite
return to the same position every time. Similarly,
the point where the pendulum crosses the center
slightly oscilates around the middle. All that’s
left is to keep alternating speeds until the
pendulum happens to line up exactly at angle zero.
It takes 291 swings to get there. Once it gets
there, what you want is the opposite. Now,
you want the pendulum to keep crossing
angle zero on every swing. So,
the pendulum has to choose the same speed
on every swing to keep gaining momentum.
The actual manipulation part is pretty simple,
if only a bit tedious. The RNG function is a
complex operation that basically takes a
number from 0 to 65535 and spits out a new,
seemingly unrelated number. It iterates upon
itself, which means that the output from one
call becomes the input for the next call. A given
input always yields the same output: for example,
2044 always yields 129, which always returns
15937, and so on. Therefore, the RNG function
is a closed loop: once an output is the same
as a previous input, the loop is closed and the
values cycle in the same exact order. The full
loop starts at 0 and contains 65114 numbers.
Every time the function is called, the value
advances one step through the loop. This can
happen multiple times in a single frame,
depending on how many objects are calling
RNG at any given time. Thankfully, there’s one
simple way for Mario to call RNG on demand:
kicking up dust. To determine their exact
position, dust clouds call the RNG function.
Therefore, by choosing to generate dust,
Mario has direct control over the RNG to
a certain degree. Because the pendulum only
calls the function at the end of each swing,
there’s plenty of time in-between to
manipulate RNG to a desired value.
This is what Pannenkoek does. Once up on
this platform, he kicks up dust to get
the pendulum to cycle through the 291 swings
until it crosses angle 0 and starts gaining
momentum. Now that pendulum manipulation is
in full swing, the pendulum’s range of motion
keeps increasing until it swings through
the ceiling and onto the next floor. Then,
Mario rides that swinging pendulum up and brings
down Timed Jumps on Moving Bars from 4 down to 3
A presses. Unfortunately, pendulum manipulation
ended up only being useful in this spot, since
other pendulums couldn’t provide any meaningful
help from swinging outside of their usual range.
In June 2016, a TASer by the name
of Z1mb0bw4y posted a comment on
Pannenkoek’s video about The Pit and
the Pendulums in 2 A presses. She said:
“Can this be done on the random setting?
It’s possible to do a kick off the wall while
grabbing the star and fall all the way down to
the red coin platforms. I think this could save
an A press.” That comment got lost in the sea
of empty claims Pannen was subject to all the
time. He couldn’t replicate what this comment
was talking about, so he dismissed the idea,
just like the hundreds of other empty claims that
came before and since. It took until November for
Plush to look into the matter. But when he did,
he found out that Z1mb0bw4y was absolutely right.
She had found a way to save one more A press,
using a trick called kick recoil momentum.
Thanks to a convenient pendulum, Mario is
able to kick the wall and pick up the star
simultaneously. Normally, picking up a star zeroes
out Mario’s horizontal speed, but kicking the wall
gives him a lot of backwards momentum. He then
falls down with the star with that momentum,
which is just barely enough to reach the lowest
spinner and end the stage on a rotating platform.
Spawning displacement does the rest of the work
and a second Tick Tock Clock re-entry A press
was saved. This also broke the tie between the
Japanese Nintendo 64 version and the VC version,
returning the original release to the spot of
single best version for the A button challenge.
2017 was a transitional year. Even though
the community was bubbling with activity,
the actual challenge itself had its
most quiet year since 2012. Instead,
people were busy learning more about the
game and developing new tools. Specifically,
danebou and pannenkoek, along with
a few occasional other contributors,
created the Super Mario 64 Technical Runtime
Observer and Object Processor: STROOP.
STROOP is basically RAM watch on steroids. It
runs alongside the emulator and keeps track of
every useful piece of memory. It also has
the ability to hack in arbitrary values,
and every way of visualizing data under the sun.
It took years of shaping up to make STROOP such
a robust and versatile tool, but the result is
worth the investment. From this point onwards,
the Super Mario 64 TASing community as a whole
benefited from the incredible work of danebou,
pannenkoek and everyone else who worked
on STROOP. So, by the end of the year,
the ABC community was fully ready to
tackle the remaining 28 A presses.
I say 28 A presses, because 2017 did have
one single improvement by Iwer Sonsch on
Stomp on the Thwomp. The Pedro spot 6 A
press method had to use an extra jump at
the end because the angle Mario was coming
at was not good enough to reach the star
directly. Iwer Sonsch simply found a better
position and angle for the Pedro spot that
did allow for a direct jump to the star,
and that was the improvement of the year.
But while 2017 was dry for the ABC, it also saw an
unlikely resurgence: the return of real-time runs.
Ever since bobmario’s flamboyant entrance
in 2007, the interest for real-time ABC had
fallen drastically, in favour of tool-assisted
superplays. The ABC was seen more as a puzzle
than a test of skill. That changed when bad_boot
took on the task of beating the game with 70
stars in a single segment in as few A presses as
possible. This had never been attempted before;
the only thing that came close was Chris
Oldfield’s 10 stars in no A presses,
16 years earlier, which was only marginally beaten
by Japanese runner Altair with 12 stars in 2011.
So much had improved since then, but on the other
hand, so many techniques were incredibly precise
and could never be replicated with human hands
and a controller. Misalignments that require
lining up with a 1x1 unit square. Cloning, which
requires tons of object slot manipulation and
precision. RNG and enemy manipulation, and any
kind of hyperspeed technique, which were all
decidedly off limits. The task was monumental.
But bad_boot was up to it. On September 24th,
2017, he sat down and gave it his best. He
pressed on for over five hours. As always,
time was very much a secondary concern. When
bad_boot defeated the final Bowser and collected
the giant star, his total A press count read
46. He made a few mistakes along the way:
he used 38 planned A presses and 8 to
retry sections where he fell. But overall,
this was a surprisingly good first attempt
and a very high bar for others to clear.
A month later, bad_boot gave it another solid
shot. This time, he had refined his strategy a
little bit: he got his planned A press count
down to 34 before the run. And it went even
better than last time: he made zero mistakes
in the entire run. He did choose to add one A
press for Scale the Mountain, instead of having
to resort to the cloning strategy with a preset
HOLP in Tiny-Huge Island, for his own sake.
So, after a bit less than five hours this time,
bad_boot had beaten Super Mario 64
with 70 stars in only 35 A presses.
This record was incredibly good. Although it
obviously didn’t include the most advanced
TAS-only solutions, it still made use of
cloning, star dance clip, framewalking,
and plenty of crazy tricks. The run was so good
that it stood as the 70-star record for years.
Meanwhile, other players were interested in
the individual star approach. The starting
point was nearly ten years old and well over
200 A presses. The strategies had evolved
beyond recognition in that time. With all this
modern knowledge at hand, runners BillyWAR,
Lord SNEK, Th3_Re4l, Zyon, Ivan178 and a
few others, including Pannenkoek himself,
started chipping away at the count. They
crossed the 200 mark in November 2019. 2020
saw the most activity, with the total dropping
from 180 in March to 116 in November. Finally,
the 100 barrier was broken on July 27th,
2021, and the most recent improvement,
from as recently as December 12th,
2022, brought the A press count to 78.
In the process, some truly incredible achievements
were done, like The Pit and the Pendulums in only
3 A presses using super precise platforming to
climb up the clock and to grab the star. Somehow,
this is not even the most impressive
part of the run. To get off this pole,
BillyWAR sent a bob-omb to a preset
HOLP high up in the air so it would
reactivate and fall on top of
him, knocking him off the pole.
Another impressive feat was pulling off
the hyperspeed walking and jump dive in
real time to get Watch for Rolling
Rocks and A-Maze-ing Emergency Exit
in one A press each, done by BillyWAR and Ivan178.
And perhaps even crazier is Big
Boo’s Merry-go-Round in 0 A presses,
something that even TASers only managed in 2015
using 10 hours of scuttlebug raising. It was done
in real-time in August 2021 by BillyWAR using
just a couple of minutes of scuttlebug raising,
and running into the scuttlebug with a
crazy box. Taking damage while holding
a crazy box acts like instant release - it
transports the box to the HOLP laterally,
but at Mario’s height. Using the hat in
hand glitch prevents the crazy box from
rendering and updating the HOLP. By setting
the HOLP at the right location beforehand,
BillyWAR sent the crazy box above the
Merry-go-round, where it deactivated.
After spawning the star, he reactivated the crazy
box and managed to grab it before it would fall
to the ground and break. He then bounced into
the star, which completed the 0 A press run.
Sometimes, the real time ABC crew got very
creative and found much simpler solutions
than what Pannenkoek had done years before. In
the Deep Freeze was solved by bad_boot when,
to replace the TAS-only shell hyperspeed strategy,
he simply lured a spindrift and bounced on it.
As far as full-game runs go, the real-time
ABC needed a bit of extra motivation. So,
Pannenkoek announced a bounty in October 2020
for people to beat bad_boot’s 35. Pannen was
giving out $50 per A press saved over the
standing world record, until the end of 2020.
In the next couple of months, three players
scrambled to get their A press count lower.
First came brqm. On November 7th, he fired up a
run with a route that would ideally get him 26
A presses. After a few minor mistakes along
the way, he ended up in Bowser in the Sky,
9 hours into the run, with 24 A presses. If
he closed it out perfectly, he could edge out
the record by three. But he couldn’t handle
the pressure. All it took was one bad fall.
Sadly, one fall turned into many, and frustration
took over. He finished the run with 55.
The next day, BillyWAR, strong from his work on
individual stars, also set out to beat the record.
His run went exceedingly well. He entered Bowser
in the Sky after only 11 A presses. He didn’t
choke in the most stressful part of the run.
He closed it out in just 21 total A presses.
Actually, not quite. After failing the star dance
clip to enter Hazy Maze Cave, he had to reset to
retry it, causing his A press counter to lose 8 A
presses. His real total was actually 29. Still, he
had beaten the record by 6 A presses and achieved
pretty much exactly what he had set out to do.
At the end of November, a new runner by the
name of PurpleJuiceBox entered the field.
After a 9-hour long effort, he managed to beat
the record by another 3 A presses. Again, the A
press counter is wrong because of a reset, this
time due to technical difficulties. In December,
PurpleJuiceBox continued to refine his strategies
until the very end of the month. Meanwhile,
brqm was back with a vengeance. On December 27th,
he did a run with an incredibly demanding 17 A
press route. He lost six along the way, but
he was in Bowser in the Sky on a 23 A press
pace. But disaster struck again, and the
record slipped from his hands once more.
brqm finished his run with 28 A
presses, just shy of the record.
With less than 48 hours to go, on December 30th,
PurpleJuiceBox was ready to take on another
run, this time with a 21 A press route.
He executed it near flawlessly.
PurpleJuiceBox beat Super Mario
64 in 4 and a half hours using 22
A presses. One single extra A press
was used at the start of Bowser in the Sky.
And that is where the record stands today.
The 120-star category was deemed a
bit too daunting by the real-time
ABC runners. It took until October 2021 for
BillyWAR to take on the challenge. He put
together a route that would ideally get 163
A presses. He ended up scoring 53 over that,
finishing out with 216. This record still stands.
Finally, another category held the attention
of real-time runners: Max stars in 0 A presses.
Since Chris Oldfield’s 10 in 2001 and Altair’s
12 in 2011, so much had changed. Technically,
up to 25 stars were now possible
without Bowser in the Dark World,
which was still TAS only. Players battled in
2020 to get as close as possible to the maximum,
a battle that was ultimately won
by Zyon, on January 12th, 2021,
when he got all 25 possible stars and put
this category to rest. Or so he thought.
On February 16th, 2022, Ivan178 completed Bowser
in the Dark World with red coins in 0 A presses
in real-time. Yes, that star with the VSC.
Yes, that star with the misalignment. Yes,
that star with the framewalking up the
seesaw platform. A month and a half later,
he would get 34 stars in 0 A presses, thanks to
the extra stars in the basement. To this day,
Ivan178 is still the only player to complete
Bowser in the Dark World in 0 A presses in
real-time, and he has sole control over this
record as a result. And this is where the
real-time A Button Challenge is today. After
being dormant for 10 years, a small community
formed around it, and its members are still
lowering the A press count on a regular basis.
March 2018. The first improvement of the year
came in Jolly Roger Bay and was the result of
slow incremental progress over many years by
Pannenkoek, Tyler Kehne and Maria Nicolae. First,
Mario framewalks up the pole to quickly gain a
lot of sliding speed. Then, he gains a little
bit more on the bottom of the pole using a
new technique called hyperspeed punching.
Normally, if Mario is moving fast enough,
pressing B will make him dive, but Mario can
still punch at high speeds by using a slight
control stick tilt on the frame he punches,
instead of a full tilt. During the punching
action, Mario experiences a lower friction
than usual. If he’s standing on a steep enough
slope, the downwards acceleration can overpower
this unusually low friction, causing him to gain
speed. Thanks to sliding speed conservation,
he can reactivate that speed to quickly slide
up the pole. Tyler Kehne had the idea of using
another punch to lose less speed while sliding
up. The extra speed at the top of the pole,
combined with a precise dive, proved to be just
enough to reach the platform and save the A press.
Then, two months went by without any
improvements. Time and effort were
being poured into complex A press saves, but
nothing came to fruition for a while. Until
the fateful night of May 26th, 2018, when an
unsuspecting speedrunner by the name of Andru,
after practicing movement in Bowser
in the Fire Sea, decided to go to bed
while leaving his console on overnight. The
next morning, he found something strange.
The platforms had risen from the lava
significantly. Over the next week,
a mad dash ensued as the community tried
to understand and replicate this. Everyone
fired up their game and impatiently waited for
something to happen in Bowser in the Fire Sea.
Andru was playing on Wii Virtual Console,
which was immediately suspected as being
relevant. It quickly became apparent
that the suspicions were correct:
whatever caused the platforms to rise from
the lava seemed to be unique to the Wii VC
release. This made testing more inconvenient,
because emulators could not replicate the issue.
Within just a few hours, bad_boot had pinpointed
the cause of the glitch. The Nintendo 64
console and emulators, when performing
a specific operation on float numbers,
round the result towards the nearest float
number, whereas Wii VC truncates the float,
effectively rounding the result towards zero.
Because the platforms are at a negative Y value,
as they bob up and down, their height ever
so slightly drifts upwards. The problem is,
for them to rise up enough to become useful
for the A button challenge, that rounding error
needs to happen roughly 8 million times.
This takes about three days of real time.
Multiple excited community members such as
Emilia, Barry, 1ted59 and SwitchPalaceCorner
began livestreaming on Twitch as they left their
Wii on for days, watching the platforms rise
up like grass growing. Despite both technical
and skill issues leading to multiple failures,
one thing became very clear: this
new glitch worked. The rest of the
stage was a bit different now that the other
sinking platforms, also drifting towards zero,
had sunk completely through the floor, leaving
a very inhospitable fire sea. But Pannen had
no issue navigating that thanks to the safe
zone on the edges. The very last A press in
70 star was finally solved. Super Mario 64
was beatable without using the A button.
The solution to get off the pole in Bowser in
the Fire Sea was to bypass the pole entirely.
After just a couple of days, danebou made a
modified version of Mupen 64 that replicated the
rounding error found in Wii VC, so Pannenkoek was
able to make a proper TAS. To get the red coins,
he simply entered the Bowser fight to
reset the platforms back to normal,
then used the regular strategy found in 2014.
Of course, this A press save came with a massive
caveat: again, it was exclusive to Wii. The
achievement of solving the A Button Challenge
completely for 70 star felt a little hollow,
because it was abusing a glitch only
present in an inaccurate emulated
rerelease. This also brought Wii VC back on
par with Japanese Nintendo 64 for 120 star,
since there were now two different A press
saves unique to each version that canceled out.
But the tie wouldn’t last very
long. Just three weeks later,
with help from bad_boot to figure things
out, and from Pannenkoek to string everything
together, Tyler Kehne unveiled the most
off-the-wall insane ABC achievement yet:
entering the Secret Aquarium in 0 A
presses without parallel universes.
Before we begin, I want to mention that
this next section is heavily based on
the excellent video on bad_boot’s
channel about this A press save.
The known strategy to enter the Secret Aquarium
had one simple problem: to get from here to there,
Mario needs more speed than he can possibly
have and still be able to get from here to
here. With PU speed not being an option,
there had to be another solution. That
solution was the glitchy ledgegrab. No,
not that glitchy ledgegrab. The other kind.
If you remember, to determine if Mario should grab
a ledge, the game checks for a wall at two points:
30 units and 150 units above Mario’s position.
On the staircase leading to Bowser in the Sky,
there are two ledges next to each other: the
game checked for a wall at the lower ledge,
then checked for a floor at the higher ledge. This
type of glitchy ledgegrab is a bit different. The
wall below the ledge to the Secret Aquarium
is ever so slightly tilted. Between the points
at 30 and 150 units, the wall tilts away
from Mario by one quarter of a unit. So,
there’s a gap of the same size where
the wall check finds a wall at 30 units,
but not at 150 units, which triggers the floor
check for a ledge grab. Like we’ve seen before,
this check can find a floor all the way
up to 238 units above Mario’s position,
allowing Mario to grab the ledge from a lower
height. But how much lower? Well, enough to
make coming in from this location viable. And
that was all they needed to solve the puzzle.
Well, not quite. There was
just one simple problem. Sure,
Mario could get from here to there with a
lower speed than before, but there’s no way
to accurately guide Mario directly to the right
spot below the ledge with such high speed. The
angle required is simply unattainable
with that amount of speed. Thankfully,
sitting right there is the perfect way to
redirect Mario to an arbitrary angle: a textbox.
Textboxes preserve Mario’s speed,
but once the text is cleared,
he can turn to face any angle instantly,
redirecting that speed to the new angle. This,
along with precise speed and positioning
in front of the door, does allow Mario to
grab the ledge. But there was one simple
problem. This textbox is only there if
Mario doesn’t have enough stars to open the
door. Therefore, Mario must have zero stars.
It turns out this simple problem is a major
issue, because it rules out hyperspeed walking
in Hazy Maze Cave. The method to enter Hazy
Maze Cave requires getting a star from MIPS,
which also only shows up if Mario already has
15 stars. If Mario can’t enter Hazy Maze Cave,
he can’t carry infinite speed into the
castle lobby. What other level could be used?
Well, not many. With zero stars, only Bob-omb
Battlefield is accessible. There’s also a way
to reach Vanish Cap under the Moat, but that one
turns out not to be very helpful. Within Bob-omb
Battlefield, shell hyperspeed immediately comes
to mind. But there’s just one simple problem:
the shell isn’t available until after
getting stars 1 and 2 in the level,
so it can’t be used. Instead,
C-up sliding saves the day.
As a refresher, when C-up is pressed on a
downwards slope, Mario slides to a stop, but
the slope overpowers the friction from sliding,
resulting in a net acceleration. This is enough
for Mario to gain over 200 speed. From there,
Tyler Kehne was able to bounce Mario to a tree
and pause exit, which conserves Mario’s sliding
speed. However, 230 speed is nowhere near the 900
or so required for Secret Aquarium. Instead,
it’s used to send Mario to Bowser in the Dark
World without the required 8 stars. The first key
can be obtained, and the basement is now unlocked.
In the basement, two more levels are accessible:
Lethal Lava Land and Shifting Sand Land. Let’s
turn our attention towards the latter. In
here, shell hyperspeed could generate a
few hundred speed, but again, it’s not enough.
This time, hyperspeed punching saves the day.
In this corner of Shifting Sand Land, the visual
geometry doesn’t match the actual level geometry:
everything in this zone is out of bounds.
When Mario stands here and punches,
he accelerates forwards, but stays in place
because he’s attempting to move out of bounds.
So long as he punches frame perfectly, he
can build up infinite speed in this corner.
However, there’s one simple problem: as soon as
Mario stops punching, he immediately and instantly
loses all but 32 speed. Thankfully, by pressing Z
at the right time, Mario starts sliding instead,
which does conserve his speed. For one frame,
at least. After one frame, Mario’s sliding
speed is capped to 100. But sliding also
turns Mario slightly. With the right angle,
this can turn Mario towards a valid position
in bounds. After one frame, Mario ends up in
the corner of the level, which happens to have a
lower floor than the hyperspeed punching spot. So,
Mario enters freefall and gets to keep his high
speed. And now, he gets to face several problems.
First of all, with 45 thousand speed, Mario is
going way too fast. The target speed here is on
the order of 2 thousand. Secondly, he’s also
headed face first towards out of bounds while
in the air, so he’s about to bonk. Last but not
least, even if he could get out of this spot,
Mario needs a way to conserve his sliding
speed into the castle lobby through a pause
exit. Solving all three problems was a stroke
of pure genius from Tyler Kehne and bad_boot.
The first problem was solved with a koopa
shell clone. A shell clone functions like
a normal shell, except that the clone stays in
place and Mario rides an invisible shell. It
can also be reused; in fact, it’s used three
different times in this level. The shell was
used here for an important property: if Z
is pressed while Mario is riding a shell,
he starts crouch sliding. Again, there’s one
small problem. This doesn’t work if Mario is
airborne. But thankfully, on the first frame
where Mario is on the shell, the game doesn’t
check for that condition and Mario can press
Z to crouch slide despite being in the air.
So, with one extra frame of sliding, another
trick could be used to bring the speed down to
a workable value: the 10k glitch. When the
control stick is pulled back while Mario is
sliding, a multiplier is applied to his
speed to slow him down. The multiplier
is meant to slow Mario down slightly more
drastically the faster he’s moving, so it
follows this formula. More specifically,
for every 10 thousand speed Mario has,
the multiplier goes down by one. So, if Mario
has a speed in the tens of thousands or higher,
this formula can yield very interesting results.
Here, by tilting the joystick ever so slightly
backwards, it’s used to instantly bring Mario’s
speed from 45 thousand down to only 2 thousand.
But there is, you guessed it, one simple
problem. For Mario to land on the Koopa shell,
he needs to fall down on it. Although he’s in
freefall, he hasn’t started falling down yet.
But if he spends one more frame in the air,
he will bonk instead. Mario needs something
to fall without bonking. Enter the fire
clone. When Mario is burning in the air
and moving towards out of bounds, he keeps his
speed, but falls straight down. From there,
he can land on the shell clone, crouch to start
sliding, pull the control stick back to activate
the 10k glitch and bring his speed down to 2
thousand, but then what? He still has no way
of conserving that speed through a pause exit,
and by the way, he’s still headed face first
into out of bounds. This is where the final
piece of this puzzle comes in: a fly guy.
With this lower speed, Mario can move for
one quarterstep before bonking. On the frame
that he bonks, his speed doesn’t get killed
immediately; only on the next frame does it
get set to -16. However, the bonk is canceled by
landing on the fly guy before the speed is capped,
so Mario’s speed ends up being conserved and he
starts twirling. After that, he can wait until the
perfect moment to land and pause exit on the first
frame to conserve his speed into the castle lobby.
But there’s one simple problem. How do you
get all this stuff in the corner like that?
The short answer is cloning and Fly guy
manipulation. Now for the long answer.
The Fly guy is nothing we haven’t seen before.
The annoying ones are the fire clone and the
koopa shell. The shell can be found in this block,
which would be easy to reach with a tornado. But
it only shows up after getting star 3, so on
zero stars, there is no tornado here. Instead,
the only method to get the shell is to
open the box remotely and clone the shell.
This can be done with a preset HOLP from
another level, namely Bob-omb Battlefield.
It just so happens that the perfect
location for this is on the floating island,
so to get the HOLP there, Mario needs to clone
a goomba and use the bloated bob-omb glitch.
No big deal so far. After placing the HOLP,
Mario can then fall onto the slippery slope,
get 200 speed, and clip into Bowser
in the Dark World with a preset HOLP.
Now, an issue: when Mario fights Bowser for the
key, he needs to grab Bowser, which automatically
updates the HOLP. There’s no such thing as hat in
hand here, and instant release, while seemingly
promising at first glance, doesn’t actually work
in this case. But remember: the HOLP updates when
the game needs to draw the object Mario is
holding. If we can’t make Bowser invisible,
what if we made Mario invisible? It turns out
that we can, using pause-buffered hitstun.
After taking damage, Mario is invincible for 30
frames, or until he’s no longer colliding with
a source of damage. This blinking during those
invincibility frames is determined by the global
timer, a timer that simply goes up by one on
every frame from power on. If this timer is even,
Mario will be visible, and if it’s odd, Mario will
be invisible. The global timer doesn’t stop when
the game is paused, so it is possible to only
unpause the game while the global timer is odd,
causing Mario to remain invisible during the
invincibility frames. In that short time,
he can grab and release objects without updating
the HOLP. This is pause-buffered hitstun.
After all this work, Mario enters Shifting
Sand Land with the HOLP intact. Again,
the hat in hand glitch is unavailable because the
wing cap requires 10 stars and Klepto is too busy
carrying a star around to steal Mario’s hat.
So, pause-buffered hitstun has to be used to
perform the remote releases. First, a bob-omb is
thrown to the HOLP, where it deactivates. Then,
another bob-omb is used for cloning.
When Mario gets near the high bob-omb,
it falls down and breaks the box, spawning
the koopa shell which Mario clones. He walks
all the way to this spot to release
it, and uses it to get around faster.
Then, this Fly guy is manipulated while the
other Fly guy is lured into spitting fire for
Mario to clone. Pause-buffered hitstun
had to be used extensively here. Mario
stays inside of the Pokey to extend his
invincibility period until he can walk up
the slope. When the Fly Guy spits fire, Mario
clones it and drops it at the HOLP laterally,
but at Mario’s height, which places the fire
clone just above the koopa shell clone. Then,
Pannenkoek finishes the Fly guy manipulation and
every piece is now in place. He heads over to the
hyperspeed punching spot and builds up speed for
40 minutes. Then, he pulls off this masterpiece.
Mario crouches which turns him. He gets burned so
not to bonk, lands on the shell to start sliding
again, and the stick is pulled slightly backwards
to trigger the 10k glitch and instantly bring
Mario speed to 2 thousand. He bonks but cancels
that bonk before his speed is capped, sending
him into a twirl at 2300 speed. He lands with the
right speed and angle and into the lobby he goes.
Now that Mario is in the lobby with 2000 speed,
here comes the easy part. Just kidding! It’s
actually the hard part. First, one thing to
keep in mind is that high speed movement is
very limited. Mario can only turn by up
to 1/32nd of a turn, or about 11 degrees,
in a single frame. This severely hinders movement
options. Unlike when traveling at PU speed,
where most of the possible positions would be
out of bounds anyway, Mario doesn’t have the
liberty of choosing which angle he wants to move
in next. He sort of always has to hug the walls.
The other major limitation is floor hitboxes,
which only extend 78 units below the floors.
This means that in any single quarterstep, Mario
can only ever move up to 78 units upwards. That’s
why he can’t just go up the central staircase
normally. For the final glitchy ledgegrab to work,
Mario needs about 920 speed, but to get
up the central staircase, he can have at
most about 500 speed. Instead, he will need to
come at it sideways, from as high as possible.
The lobby movement, again solved by Tyler Kehne,
can be subdivided into five main sections:
entering the Jolly Roger Bay room, landing on
this pillar, reaching the 8-star door, reaching
the 1-star door, and finally, grabbing the Secret
Aquarium ledge. Let’s go through them one by one.
The first part is reaching the Jolly Roger
Bay room, which is quite a bit higher. First,
Mario’s stored speed sends him into the Whomp’s
Fortress room, where he has to carefully turn
around and navigate back to the main
lobby. After reaching this staircase,
Mario needs to zigzag up to gain height
in small enough increments. The geometry
of this area just barely allows it to
work. If the stairs had one more step
or if Mario needed slightly more speed, going
up this staircase would have been impossible.
Once in the Jolly Roger Bay room, Mario is now at
the highest point he can be before heading towards
the central staircase. However, he can’t go
directly to the staircase because at this angle,
he would shoot past it and into the Bob-omb
Battlefield room. Instead, he has to aim at
the pillar next to the staircase. The pillar is 77
units higher than the floor Mario is currently on,
so he has a grand total of one and a
half frames to reach it. This is why,
despite only needing 900 speed at the end,
Mario needs to have 1700 speed at this point.
In order to reach the pillar, Tyler aimed
Mario towards the railing. On this frame,
Mario’s next intended position after one
quarterstep is right here, less than one
unit inside of it. The railing is 51 units wide,
so there is a one unit gap where only the outside
wall affects Mario, allowing him to get pushed by
it. He gets pushed into the pillar’s wall hitbox,
but the wall check is over, so he doesn’t get
affected by it right away. Then, because Mario
is inside the floor hitbox, he gets pushed up
to it and lands. This sequence works because
the game treats collision checks in the order of
walls first, floors second, and ceilings last.
Tyler dives here and does a dive recover
on the pillar for a very specific reason:
when Mario lands from that dive recover, he can
instantly turn. By turning in this direction,
he now tries to move into a ceiling, which leaves
him stuck in place, allowing him to let his speed
come down to 1100 for the next section. But during
the dive recover, he needs something to keep him
in place. That thing is the other railing. Mario’s
first quarterstep leads him in the railing,
which has two overlapping opposite wall
hitboxes that cancel each other out. So,
after this double wall push, Mario’s position
is inside of a ceiling, which not only prevents
him from moving there, but also negates
his vertical speed. If he did get vertical
speed from the dive recover, Mario would’ve
caught the top of the railing and fallen off.
Once Mario’s speed drops down to 1100, he’s
ready to head to the 8-star door. He spends
one frame on the staircase, which lowers
his de facto speed just enough to avoid
falling off. Then, he manages to turn
towards the star door and trigger the
text as far left as possible. This
is important for the next section.
After closing the text, Mario can now redirect his
speed in any direction. Because he’s on the left
side of the door, he has a near direct line to
the 1-star door, which he reaches in three frames.
He needs to trigger that text with a very precise
speed and position, so he waits some speed
out and then clips inside of the Princess’s
Secret Slide room to realign himself. Then,
Tyler makes use of a neat high speed trick to
redirect Mario towards the door. If Mario is
pushing up against a wall and C-up is pressed,
Mario will instantly face directly at the wall.
With high negative speed, this causes him
to shoot away from the wall perpendicularly,
no matter his prior facing angle. This
leads him into the door’s textbox.
Again, after closing it out, Mario can redirect
his speed, this time towards the Secret Aquarium
entrance. All that’s left is to perfectly aim at
the quarter unit gap and do a glitchy ledge grab.
And there it was. Entering the
Secret Aquarium in zero A presses,
compatible with the Nintendo 64 console.
After this enormous achievement, the A button
challenge community could sit back and relax. For
a while, nothing really happened. Alright, that’s
enough. What if we saved two A presses this time?
This new development was a joint effort by
bad_boot, Sidney and Tyler Kehne. It makes use
of a trick discovered in February by bad_boot
and Sidney: Hyperspeed grinding. It requires
a specific spot where a bit of steep floor is
next to a gap in the floor and a wall. Mario
runs off the steep floor, making him airborne.
On the next frame, the wall pushes him back,
and the stick is held back towards the floor,
so he lands. This cycle is repeated for as long
as needed. Because of the landing frame, Mario’s
speed is normally kept in check by friction and
he can’t accelerate beyond the normal speed
cap of 32. But if the floor is steep enough,
Mario has no friction when landing, so he
can build up speed to a certain degree.
Because of limitations with geometry, this method
can be used to build up to roughly 400 speed at
best. Despite that, it could still prove useful,
so long as there existed a spot that filled all
the requirements in Tick Tock Clock. This is
where Sidney came in and found the edge of this
treadmill. Here, it works slightly differently:
Mario is getting a push from two wall hitboxes
at once, which combine to send him back on the
treadmill where he lands. After gathering enough
speed, Mario can do a hyperspeed jump dive and
reach the next level in a single A press instead
of two. Finally, Tyler Kehne executed the strategy
to save the A press, and Pannenkoek, as always,
strung everything together. He published The Pit
and the Pendulums in one A press, and Timed Jumps
on Moving Bars from 3 down to 2 A presses. Stomp
on the Thwomp, the only other star higher than
this, still used the Pedro spot strategy, so no
other A press could be saved with this new trick.
As soon as hyperspeed grinding
was proven possible, though,
an alternate strategy for Timed
Jumps on Moving Bars was revisited.
Over the years, many alternate methods were
found that completed stars in the same amount
of A presses, but with wildly different
routes, sometimes faster, sometimes not.
One of these was for Timed Jumps on Moving
Bars. Instead of using a bob-omb to reach
the Roll into the Cage star and then two
A presses to get up to the timed bars,
one could instead use three A presses to reach the
timed bars, and repurpose the bob-omb to clip into
the final cage instead of jumping to it. A way to
get up the cogs without the bob-omb was theorized,
but never actually accomplished, because both
amounted to 4 A presses in total, or 3 with
pendulum manipulation. But with the discovery
of hyperspeed grinding, suddenly, where the
original route saved one A press, the alternate
route saved two. So, the alternate method became
the main one. But first, they had to actually
get up these cogs, not just think about it.
The problem actually doesn’t lie within the
cogs themselves, but with this platform,
which is slightly too high to just dive
recover to, given that it’s not oriented
properly for a misalignment to exist.
But, with enough conserved vertical speed,
it would be possible to grab the ledge. They
just needed to land on the cog with positive
vertical speed, and get pushed off at the right
time to reactivate that speed. Piece of cake.
On the random setting, cogs spin back and forth
like this. As they rotate, their wall hitboxes
move around as well, creating openings on the
corners from time to time. More specifically,
there is a misalignment on the corner found in
this region of the cog, because this section
points away from the origin. This is both a
blessing and a curse. It’s a blessing because
a misalignment makes it possible for Mario to
land on the cog with positive vertical speed.
It’s a curse because this spot seemed just out
of reach. It wasn’t just that Mario needed to
land there, he needed to get there with enough
vertical speed to grab the ledge afterwards.
Using mathematical models and calculations,
DeRockProject and Sidney ended up finding
that yes, this strategy was indeed just barely
possible. The cog’s wall on the previous frame
could be used to help Mario get increased distance
to reach the misalignment. Using their guidance,
Pannenkoek was able to TAS it, and the route was
complete. The rest stayed relatively unchanged
until the end: hyperspeed grinding to get up
here in one A press, then pendulum manipulation
to save another. But then, the bob-omb they
repurposed falls down from way above, and
Mario grabs it bloated to clip into the cage. The
HOLP was placed in Bowser in the Sky beforehand,
and the bob-omb was released at the HOLP using
pause-buffered hitstun. Just two weeks after
being brought to 2 A presses, Timed Jumps
on Moving Bars was already down to just one.
Two months later, on September 26th, 2018, Stomp
on the Thwomp underwent a revolution when a new
Pedro spot was found here. Well, actually, the
Pedro spot itself was already known to exist,
but no one knew how to get Mario lodged in
there like that. Until ds273 found a way
to knock Mario into the Pedro spot without an A
press, using pendulum manipulation and a bob-omb.
The old 5 A press route, the one with 4 A
presses at the start and one hyperspeed jump
dive, went flying out of the window.
Instead, it was replaced with this.
The beginning is basically the same as
The Pit and the Pendulums in 1 A press;
only the HOLP is in a slightly different position.
Then, two different RNG manipulations are done at
the same time: pendulum manipulation, and the
rotating clock hand at the top of the stage.
Pendulum manipulation is used to make
the pendulum end a spin here. This is
actually nearly a full rotation, so when it
swings back, it swings upwards to return to
angle zero. This lodges Mario in the
ceiling and reactivates the bob-omb,
which falls on top of him and knocks him
onto the pendulum’s box. This allows Mario
to turn towards a suitable angle for what
comes next. When the pendulum swings back
around, the shaft pushes Mario off the
pendulum box and into the Pedro spot.
Once Mario is in the Pedro spot, he builds up
to over 600 speed and jumps out of the spot,
instantly landing on the floor above.
To preserve his vertical speed,
he instantly pushes C-up to enter first
person. Otherwise, the landing would instantly
bring his speed to zero. Then, he punches
repeatedly until he leaves this platform,
where the conserved speed sends him flying
upwards. He lands directly on the clock hand.
This is why RNG was being manipulated before.
After getting on the hand in 2 A presses,
all that was needed was to wait for it to make
three quarters of a turn, and jump on the thwomp
to get the star in three. This saved two A presses
at once for the second time in a couple of months.
After completing this run, Pannenkoek and
crew were not satisfied. The Pedro spot could,
on paper, give enough vertical speed to Mario to
reach all the way up to the star. The problem,
though, was how disjointed the Pedro spot
was from the Thwomp. While Mario could
jump all the way up to the star, he couldn’t
cross the horizontal distance in that time,
since having to resort to VSC to get past
this platform killed all of his forward
momentum. The solution they found was double VSC.
The route is mostly the same up to this point.
This time, Mario builds up almost 700 speed,
which gives him a little bit more vertical
momentum. Once he shoots off this platform,
he lands on the clock hand by having it turn
under him. Pressing C-up on the frame Mario lands
preserves his vertical speed, on top of stopping
him on a dime. Then, the hand rotates towards the
thwomp, and Mario releases the remaining vertical
speed to land on it and save yet another A press.
The highest star in the toughest stage for the A
button challenge was down to only two A presses.
But hold on. Clock hands are
supposed to move clockwise.
That’s quite literally the definition of
clockwise. How does the hand turn backwards
like that? The answer is RNG manipulation,
and a lot of it. The problem, though,
is that once Mario enters the Pedro spot,
there is no longer a way to manipulate RNG.
So, before getting into the Pedro spot, Pannenkoek
spent an extra 9 minutes manipulating the hand so
it would turn counterclockwise by a third of
a turn. Despite being on the random setting,
the clock hands still favor moving clockwise. If
you let the clock run without interference long
enough though, the clock hand will eventually
turn by this much counterclockwise. The only
problem is it typically takes on the
order of weeks. That’s… not ideal.
So, Pannenkoek wrote a program that
simulated the clock on a random setting,
and used it to calculate a way to
affect the RNG so that 12 minutes later,
the clock hand would move exactly the way he
wanted. His script found dozens of solutions,
and Pannen simply picked one
of the more convenient ones.
2018 turned into 2019. The community was as active
and dedicated as ever to find A press saves,
but they were getting exponentially harder to
come by. Even Tick Tock Clock, which was still
responsible for 17 A presses not that long ago,
had seriously dried up and was down to only 8.
It was time to think outside the box. What if,
instead of trying to remove A presses from the
total, they started adding them back? This
is Get a Hand, up from 0 to 0.5 A presses.
If you’ve been following, you might
know where this is going. First,
adding a half A press in Tick Tock Clock doesn’t
hurt. It’s assumed that the star would come
after entering the level for the first time, an
action that still incurred an A press. Second,
the half A press is useful here because it
allows Mario to kick, which in turn lets
him fall down with backwards momentum. This
sets things up for spawning displacement.
There is one major issue though. The previous
spawning displacement was achieved on The Pit
and the Pendulums, which is directly above,
and very much above, Get a Hand. Despite that,
Mario has barely enough speed to land on the
lowest of the spinners. If Mario were to kick
the wall and get this star, he’d be way short
of the spinners. This one was solved by ds273.
The problem with kick recoil momentum is that
the speed Mario inherits is a fixed negative
48. But the ABC crew figured out that while
it’s true that Mario’s speed can’t be changed,
speed isn’t the only way to move Mario:
he can also get pushed by walls. If Mario
finds himself inside a wall hitbox, because
the hitbox is 50 units wide on each side,
he can theoretically get pushed by double that,
or 100 units perpendicularly to that wall.
Now, because the ABC experts were trying to push
Mario in the same direction as his movement,
that proved to be a bit tricky,
because Mario would need to enter
the wall from behind for this to work.
But thanks to pendulum manipulation,
it was possible to have the wall itself move
into Mario instead. Unfortunately, even that
wall push ended up being too weak to move Mario
enough to reach the spinners - by a factor of 10.
That idea was not gonna work. It was tough
enough to get Mario to get pushed by a wall
in the right direction once, let alone
ten times. Until ds273 had a new idea.
The pendulum is made up of many tiny
triangles to give the illusion of a
round shape. As it turns out, in this specific
spot, many different triangles converge into
a single point. Theoretically, if Mario ended
up exactly on that point, he could technically
be inside of all of these triangles’ wall
hitboxes at once. Like we’ve seen before,
when Mario is in multiple wall hitboxes
at the same time, he receives a combined
push from all of them. So, if Mario ended up
inside of all of these walls, he could get a
wall push from each of these triangles. And
how many triangles is that? Ten triangles.
The path forward was clear. The goal was to
get Mario in this point in the star fall action
with kick recoil momentum. Then, he would
get a massive push from ten walls at once,
and move just barely far enough to
star dance clip onto the spinner. Now,
the question was: how do you get Mario in there?
Well, the answer was not easy. Unlike floors,
wall collisions do use floating point numbers,
so the point where these ten triangles
converge is one single floating point number,
or 0.000025 units wide. Also, for all ten
triangles to be walls at the same time,
the pendulum needs to be at a very specific
angle, so extensive manipulation was also
required. The point itself was also a little
bit too high; Mario somehow needed to kick the
wall from slightly higher than this platform.
That wasn’t enough to discourage ds273. Here’s
the route that he came up with, and that
Pannenkoek successfully TASed afterwards.
First, there needs to be a carefully preset
HOLP. Tall Tall Mountain can be used do to
just that. Next, Pannen uses instant release
to send two bob-ombs at the HOLP laterally,
but at slightly different heights. This is
so they can be reactivated later in very
specific positions. Then, after climbing up
to the turning hand, Pannen manipulates the
pendulum for 18 minutes until it starts making
full rotations. He reactivates the first bob-omb,
which he wants to grab. Since he
has to hold A to kick later on,
he can’t just grab it normally, so he has
to use the ledge to dive grab it instead.
He grabs it slightly bloated, which
gives Mario a weak backwards push.
Then, he reactivates the second bob-omb so
that it snaps to Mario’s position and explodes,
pushing him through the wall. He normally wouldn’t
be able to stand in there, but here, he can for
two reasons. First, objects like bob-ombs can push
Mario into positions that he normally wouldn’t be
able to reach by himself, like inside ceilings
or out of bounds. We’ve seen this twice before
in Stomp on the Thwomp. Second, this area is
not out of bounds, because there is a floor
directly below. It’s inside of a ceiling, which
traps Mario in mid-air, but doesn’t immediately
kill him like out of bounds would. The swinging
pendulum passes by, and Mario can walk on it,
which ever so slightly moves him upwards to the
correct vertical position for the float precise
wall push. Then, he keeps moving inside of the
ceiling thanks to the bob-omb pushing him around,
until he gets to a fraction of a unit behind
the wall, the perfect spot for the final part.
The inputs and RNG to get to this point required
brute forcing to reach the exact values needed.
Now, all Pannen can do is wait. When the pendulum
is about to turn into the exact angle that yields
the float precise ten triangle overlap, Mario
kicks and starts moving backwards. He enters
the wall hitbox and gets clipped back in bounds.
His kick collides with the wall on the same frame
that he touches the star. Then, he inherits
-48 speed and the pendulum turns into him.
He enters the float precise point where ten
wall hitboxes coincide. In a single frame,
he gets pushed one thousand units backwards,
which happens to be just barely enough to star
dance clip at the very bottom of the
spinner. Finally, one small bit of RNG
manipulation before this whole ordeal ensured
at at this precise moment, the spinner would
start spinning clockwise and provide spawning
displacement to save the re-entry A press.
All 120 stars were now obtainable in nineteen
A presses. The ABC crew had done it: the whole
game was under 20. The A Button Challenge had
completed its twenty-two-year transition from
a fun little distraction in the corner of an IRC
chat, to the most convoluted and well-researched
video game puzzle of all time. As complex and
difficult the new A press saves had become,
it was worth the effort. With a community as
large as ever filled with talented experts working
together tirelessly, the sky was the limit.
But despite so many technical advancements,
no discovery that came after this ever directly
helped. The A press count remained frozen at 19.
Months became years. Ultimately, still
sitting at 7 A presses by itself,
Tick Tock Clock had won. In 2022,
the A press count is still 19.
The date is July 6th, 2022. The ABC
community finally unveils not one,
not two, but three A press saves at the
same time, all of them in Tick Tock Clock.
Of the hundreds of A presses once needed
to collect all the stars, only 16 remain.
Though it seemed that the ABC had been
dormant for a while, the new developments
in Tick Tock Clock actually had been in the
making for years. In fact, ever since 2016,
there was one leading idea to lower Stomp on the
Thwomp to only one A press. At its inception,
it could save up to 8 A presses on three
different stars. It was a very simple idea,
with just one small problem. How
small? About the scale of the universe.
The idea involved the old Pedro spot
strategy. That method was stunted by
having to enter the level while the clock is
still, which made reaching the Pedro spot so
much more inconvenient than what a moving
clock could provide. So, what if, instead,
the Pedro spot could be used while the clock
was on the random setting? Theoretically,
through the magic of RNG manipulation, the cog
could stay in place for long enough that Mario
could build up all the speed he needed to
jump straight up to the Thwomp at the top
of the clock. But here’s the small
problem: to stay still for so long,
assuming purely random conditions, the cog
needed to roll a one in seven chance, 1200
times. Simply finding a solution that worked would
take longer than the heat death of the universe.
There were a few redeeming elements that
made the actual odds slightly better.
Iwer Sonsch made a detailed analysis of the
probabilities with a more optimistic outlook
and found that the odds were much better than
Pannenkoek’s initial calculation. Specifically,
he found that once Mario has enough speed,
the cog can turn by some tiny amount without
breaking the Pedro spot. But regardless of how
you spin it, the improbability of the strategy
outscaled the number of possibilities that could
be tested by dozens of orders of magnitude.
So, while the Random Cog Pedro Spot
idea was alluring in its simplicity,
it was impossibly intimidating in its execution.
It remained in limbo for over six years,
waiting for something to be found that would make
it computable. But that never happened. Instead,
it was its competing idea, a much
more complex one on the surface,
that prevailed in July 2022 and
saved three A presses at once.
To get some context on the discoveries that
led to the improvements, we need to step all
the way back to March of 2018. Tyler Kehne
and bad_boot were brainstorming strategies
to get past the pole in Bowser in the Fire
Sea on console. During their research, they
found a promising and peculiar trick that stems
from a very obscure interaction: squish cancel.
When a ceiling and a floor are close together,
Mario can’t quite fit in that spot. This is the
mechanic that makes Pedro spots what they are.
However, if at least one of them is dynamic,
in other words if it belongs to an
object, Mario will get squished instead.
Now, if at least one of the surfaces involved
in the squish happens to be very slanted,
by more than 60º, as Mario is getting
squished, he also gets pushed off by
10 units. If that push happens to be
enough to take him off the floor he’s on,
then he suddenly finds himself squished
by nothing, in mid-air. To prevent that,
on the next quarterstep, his action state is
set to idle instead. Finally, on the next frame,
Mario can either do an action like a jump
from that state, or he simply enters freefall.
The reason this was so promising is that
squish cancel happens to preserve Mario’s
horizontal speed while it resets his
action back to idle. But there’s also
an unexpectedly useful side-effect: it also
zeroes out Mario’s vertical speed. Ultimately,
the goal was to use this in combination
with high speed collisions with bullies,
but there were missing pieces to the puzzle and,
despite all their best efforts for years and
years, this idea could never be fully realized.
A few months later, though, in August 2018,
a TASer by the name of Super Watermelon 64
was playing around in Jolly Roger Bay
when he encountered a very odd glitch:
Mario could dive twice for seemingly no reason.
This turned out to be the accidental
discovery of remote squish cancel.
If you remember, ceilings extend up infinitely
until there’s a floor above them. Sometimes,
due to imperfect geometry or rounding
errors, a ceiling that’s supposed to have
a floor above it has a tiny sliver that
doesn’t. This exposed ceiling stretches
infinitely upward and causes what’s
commonly called an invisible wall.
If the ceiling happens to have a floor immediately
under it and one of them is part of an object,
then all the requirements are met to squish Mario,
even though he’s far higher than the game would
expect him to be. When Mario is squished, he
instantly downwarps to the floor below him.
But if there’s a steep slope and Mario gets pushed
out, his action is set to idle instead. From that
point, he can jump or enter freefall again while
preserving his speed. Because all of this happens
way above the place that would actually squish
Mario, this is known as remote squish cancel.
Immediately, bad_boot found
that under perfect conditions,
the pendulums in Tick Tock Clock could
fulfill the requirements to enable Mario
to perform a remote squish cancel. At
the time, nothing concrete was found
to have it directly save an A press,
but it was one more tool in the box.
The other trick that was found during that time,
though, was much more evidently groundbreaking.
On May 1st, 2021, ds273 published the
discovery of Behind Camera Anywhere.
Behind Camera Anywhere, or BCA for short, is a
surprisingly simple trick. At any given time,
the camera has a focus point. Now you would
think that focus point should be Mario,
but as it turns out, that would look
a bit odd and annoying. Instead,
the camera is looking at a constantly
evolving point that’s roughly this
much ahead of where Mario is looking.
Now, if you lock the camera in place,
the focus point will still behave as normal. If
Mario goes really close to the camera, the focus
point in front of him can end up on the other
side. The camera always looks at the focus point;
therefore, Mario can end up behind the camera,
so long as he’s looking in the right direction.
To save on resources, anything that
isn’t in the current field of view
of the camera isn’t being rendered, because
it wouldn’t be on screen anyway. That’s true
even of Mario himself. If he’s
far enough behind the camera,
then he no longer gets rendered. And you know
what that means? If Mario isn’t being rendered,
then whatever he’s holding also isn’t being
rendered, so the HOLP does not get updated!
That’s right: Behind Camera Anywhere is
yet another HOLP preservation method,
adding to the Hat in Hand glitch, instant
release, and pause-buffered hitstun. Of course,
it comes with its own set of challenges. Mario
needs to grab and release an object all while
keeping himself behind and his focus point in
front of the static camera. That’s a pretty
restrictive situation that effectively
prevents moving around with the object,
and also limits Mario’s facing angle during the
trick. Nonetheless, Behind Camera Anywhere would
prove extremely useful to streamline a lot of
existing cloning strategies, and it even found
its way into real-time ABC. But most importantly,
BCA enabled new possibilities for crazy routes
in Tick Tock Clock. Combined with remote squish
cancel and a few thousand hours of working out,
this discovery led to the three A press saves
in Tick Tock Clock, fourteen months later.
The idea boils down to solving one problem:
getting past this section of the level in no A
presses. The stars The Pit and the Pendulums,
Timed Jumps on Moving Bars and Stomp on the
Thwomp all rely on clearing this section. The
existing method bypassed the whole thing in one
A press with hyperspeed grinding. To go from
one to none, though, a completely different
strategy was needed. It can be broken down
into three steps. First, crossing this gap,
which has been solved for years using a
bloated bob-omb. Second, getting up to here,
which can be done with a dive recover into a
fire clone and a star dance clip. And finally,
dismounting the pole, which can be solved with
another conveniently placed fire clone. And that’s
it! With just these three steps, the whole section
is cleared in no A presses. Actually, not quite.
It’s easy to look at each individual problem
within a level and find a solution that misses
the bigger picture. This is one of those. The
star dance clip looks like a great solution,
but it actually isn’t. It’s all because this
gap already uses a star dance clip. You can
only spawn one 100-coin star at once, but
here, you would somehow need two. One of
them has to go. This is where ds273 came up with
an absolutely crazy plan that could, in theory,
get rid of this star dance clip. But it was a bit
of a lunatic idea that had no business actually
being possible. Until a newcomer, SJMHRP, jumped
into the problem head first. She created various
programs to search for the one perfect alignment
of stars that allowed ds’s insane plan to work.
This task was astronomical. But after a thousand
hours of work over eight months, and after over
ten thousand computational hours to search through
billions of permutations of conditions, she found
a solution. And this is where the strategy goes
from pretty complex to mindbendingly complex. Sit
down, buckle up, and put your helmet on.
Let’s get it out of the way right off the
bat. Mario rides a pendulum into the ceiling,
he gets squished and burned, then repeatedly
ground pounds to gain height, all the way up until
he grabs the ledge at the top. Finally, he pulls
a bob-omb out of his pocket and uses it to cross
the gap. That’s it, that’s how it’s done, and now
we need to spend twenty minutes understanding why.
The first step of this ordeal is to manipulate the
pendulum. It needs to reach a very specific state,
so a total of 61 minutes of manipulation is
required to do so. After this much manipulation,
it’s now spinning so fast that it does
50 full rotations per swing. But it’s
not just the speed that’s important:
it’s also the exact angles that the
pendulum will be taking at various
times a couple dozen frames apart.
Next, Mario rides the pendulum up into the
ceiling. Normally, he should get squished,
but there’s a 10-unit gap where Mario is stuck
in the ceiling without being squished. So long
as Mario keeps walking, he stays stuck in that
ceiling. If he stops walking, he falls down. So,
after a few minutes of waiting for the
pendulum to reach the correct state,
Mario falls back down and gets carried up into
the ceiling. This happens because collisions
are processed in the order of walls, floors
and ceilings. Mario snaps up to the pendulum
before the ceiling has anything to say about it.
Also, Mario doesn’t take damage because he goes
from being lightly squished straight to being
fully inside of the ceiling in a single frame.
Now, Mario shouldn’t be able to move around
in here, but the pendulum provides a floor for
him to stand on. But to be able to reach
the higher section, Mario needs a fire
bounce from a fire clone. For now, we’ll skip
explaining why Mario clips inside the pendulum,
and how the clone got there. We’ll get
back to that later. After more precise
mid-air walking and waiting, the conditions
are finally perfect for the magic trick.
Mario turns until he faces out. He ever so
slightly enters the back of the wall hitbox,
clipping him back out. Then, he ground pounds. As
the pendulum rotates, it enters a position where,
because of imperfect geometry, an
exposed ceiling squishes Mario,
canceling the ground pound and resetting his
vertical speed back to zero. On the same frame,
he’s pushed out of the exposed ceiling. On the
next frame, he enters freefall. From there, he can
move into the next spot that will have an exposed
ceiling, and ground pound again to gain height.
In total, this trick is repeated seven times.
This is why the pendulum manipulation was so
crucial. The pendulum needs to create seven squish
cancel spots at regular intervals of about 7 to 10
frames, with no exposed ceilings in between. Mario
can only move by a tiny amount between each ground
pound, so all seven squish cancel spots need
to be very close to each other. At the start,
the pendulum needs to stay below Mario,
otherwise he’d bonk into it. And finally,
because the pendulum is only tangible if Mario
is close enough to it, as Mario goes higher,
the angle range the pendulum can take gets smaller
and smaller. When Mario is at the very top,
he’s too far from the pendulum to do any more
squish cancels, but he’s still too low to grab
the ledge. Thankfully, ds273 had one last
trick up his sleeve: a glitchy ledge grab.
This wall is made up of two sections that
seamlessly combine to create one surface. But as
it turns out, due to some floating point rounding
nonsense, each section has an ever so slightly
different normal vector. As a result, there is a
float precise position where Mario’s 30-unit check
finds the lower wall, but the 150-unit check does
not find the higher wall, and he grabs the ledge
from way below. This glitchy ledge grab was found
on November 14th, 2020, and it was the last piece
of the puzzle ds273 needed to devise his master
plan. Once on this spot, Mario could use a bob-omb
to cross the gap, a star dance clip to get up
the elevator, and a fire clone to dismount the
pole. But hold on: how do you get all this stuff
here in the first place? We need to rewind a bit.
The last one is the simplest: this fire clone
is placed at the beginning of the stage using
a preset HOLP from Tall, Tall Mountain and Behind
Camera Anywhere. But despite being the simplest,
it’s not that simple, because Mario
needs one of these bob-ombs for cloning,
yet the object he’s cloning is all the
way up here. He needs to find a way to
carry an object for an extended time without
updating the HOLP at any step of the process.
First, Mario makes both bob-ombs explode one frame
apart. He grabs one of them. Just as he grabs it,
the other bob-omb is unloaded. This causes the
bob-omb’s spawner to load into Mario’s hands.
Like we’ve seen before, a spawner is an invisible
object. Because it’s invisible, it doesn’t need
to be rendered, which in turn doesn’t update the
HOLP. Mario then carries that invisible object
up until it also unloads and can be replaced.
At the exact moment when it’s replaced with the
newly loaded fire object, Mario is now behind
the camera, so again, the HOLP is not updated.
Mario throws the fire clone to the HOLP, where it
sits waiting to burn Mario off the pole later on.
The clones on the elevator are more interesting,
but we’ll get to those later. I did promise that
I would explain how these fire clones
got here. There are three of them:
one has to be used as a sacrifice to prevent
Mario from activating the useful fire clones
too early. The clones were placed
by setting the HOLP under this spot,
then using BCA to drop them at the HOLP laterally,
but at Mario’s height. The range of usable heights
for the fire clones was pretty restricted, which
made the whole strategy harder to pull off.
And now, we take a look at how the bob-omb
magically appears in this spot. It uses
a known trick, the out of bounds failsafe
mechanism, but in a new way. In the past,
the bob-omb was placed using a preset HOLP from
another level that happened to be out of bounds
in Tick Tock Clock. But here, the preset HOLP
is already in use, and there can only be one.
There needs to be a way to place a bob-omb out
of bounds from within the level. Of course,
Mario normally can’t go out of bounds. On the rare
occasion that he does find himself out of bounds,
he dies immediately. Needless to say,
this proved to be quite a challenge for
ds273 to solve. The solution he came
up with is nothing short of amazing.
Here’s how the HOLP can be set out of bounds. Just
below this treadmill, 31 units below to be exact,
there is a wall overlap. When Mario dives with a
bob-omb onto the edge, the moving treadmill moves
Mario off, which does two things. First, Mario
enters a hands free holding state, and second,
his vertical speed of -24 is conserved. After
one frame of falling, Mario’s speed is now
-28. On the second frame’s first quarterstep,
Mario moves down by a quarter of that speed,
or 7 units. He precisely enters the wall
overlap and gets moved outside of the level.
But wait! That’s out of bounds! How can Mario
be out of bounds without instantly dying? Well,
he actually isn’t. Even outside of the walls of
the level, Mario isn’t immediately out of bounds.
As it turns out, the floor at the very bottom of
the clock extends a little bit outside the walls.
Mario is only treated as out of bounds if there
is no floor under him, so technically, he is still
in bounds. After falling for a bit, Mario dives,
which he can do while hands free holding. He hits
the actual out of bounds and bonks, which releases
the bob-omb and knocks him back into the level.
Meanwhile, the HOLP, which is in front of Mario’s
position when he’s diving, ends up out of bounds.
Now, a bob-omb needs to be released
there with some remote release method:
either pause-buffered hitstun, behind camera
anywhere, or instant release. This turns out
to be more challenging than it seems because
of the 4000-unit activation radius. For the
failsafe to trigger, Mario needs to
enter the bob-omb’s activation radius,
which is this sphere. But the HOLP is too
low for that radius to intersect this ledge,
so the bob-omb needs to be released at the HOLP
laterally, at about this height instead. However,
at the moment when the bob-omb is released, Mario
needs to be outside of this zone. Otherwise,
the failsafe would be triggered immediately
and the bob-omb would snap to Mario’s position.
This creates a bit of a problem, considering the
bob-ombs are right here. But what if they weren’t?
Prior to setting this HOLP, Mario clones one
of the bob-ombs by reloading it from above
the spinners. He uses that bomb to clip through
the wall on the moving bar. Again, despite being
outside the walls, the moving bar provides a floor
for Mario to stand on. He releases the bomb here,
setting the HOLP in this weird semi-out of
bounds spot. Then, he clones another bob-omb,
making sure to avoid updating the HOLP. Using
BCA, he throws it out of bounds. Something weird
happens: the bob-omb goes to the HOLP, but
gets stuck in a weird mid-air oscillation.
This sparks a few questions. Why does it
do that? Because it’s out of bounds. When
a bob-omb tries to move out of bounds, its
movement is reversed, which normally should
send it back towards the map. But when
that new position is also out of bounds,
it runs into the same issue on the next frame.
The net result is the bob-omb oscillates between
two out of bounds positions, reversing its
movement on every frame. But why is it out
of bounds if it it’s just above the moving bar?
Because just like any other object with collision,
moving bars are only tangible if Mario
is close to them. Because he’s not,
there’s no floor here and the bob-omb is indeed
out of bounds. But if it’s out of bounds,
why doesn’t it snap to Mario? Because the
failsafe only triggers when Mario drops a
bob-omb. When he throws a bob-omb, it goes to
the HOLP, regardless of if it’s in bounds or not.
So, Mario throws the bob-omb out of bounds,
where it remains until he goes right next to
the moving bar to make it tangible. During that
time, he sets up the out of bounds HOLP using
the treadmill for the next part. When he comes
back to the moving bar, the bob-omb falls on it
and clips back in bounds. Just as it’s about
to explode, Mario dives and performs instant
release on the bloated bob-omb. This sends it
to the HOLP laterally, but at Mario’s height,
far enough away that it deactivates
until Mario enters its radius. But also,
the radius happens to intersect this ledge. We’ve
finally got the bob-omb where it needs to be.
This, however, creates a new problem. Remember,
Mario cannot enter the bob-omb’s activation
radius until the exact moment when he’s ready to
use it. The radius intersects the destination,
sure, but it also passes right through the
section where Mario rides the pendulum into
the ceiling. To avoid reactivating the
bob-omb early, Mario actually needs to
clip inside the pendulum as he’s going up.
Thankfully, there happens to be a tiny,
one unit wide sliver of floor inside the
pendulum for Mario to stand on. He gets
squished by the pendulum and finds himself on
that one unit slice of ground. He gets burned
while narrowly avoiding the walls and the
bob-omb’s activation radius, and he reaches
the top of the pendulum with one sector of health
remaining. At last, after the whole squish cancel
ground pound chain sequence, Mario can enter
the radius and snap the bob-omb next to him.
One more detail. Because the bob-omb is bloated
at its maximum size, when it snaps to Mario’s
position, it pushes Mario out through
the wall and inside the cage. But also,
because the bob-omb is so big, it
touches the cage’s wall hitboxes;
both the outside wall and the inside wall. The
outside wall doesn’t push it any further out,
but the inside wall pushes it all the way
inside the cage, so it clips in alongside Mario.
Finally, Mario can grab it and use it
to cross the gap towards the elevator.
And that’s when we finally get to these two
clones. How did they get here? Remember,
they can’t use their own preset HOLP because there
can only be one. The solution is very simple:
you take all of the steps needed to reach this
spot, the entire thing, and you do it twice. The
first time, after crossing the gap with the
bob-omb, you use that bob-omb to place the
HOLP here. Then, you go back down and use BCA
to release a coin and a fire clone. Finally,
you do all of this again and get back
up, this time with all the right tools
to climb the rest of the way. After all of this
work, Mario gets past the pole in 0 A presses.
If only it were that simple. Remember, the pole
isn’t the end here! Several challenges remain.
First of all, because there are three instances
of spawning displacement to re-enter the clock,
the level can only be entered with a preset
HOLP a total of three times. Get a Hand needs
a preset HOLP, which leaves only two uses of
a preset HOLP for three stars that need it.
The second problem is that the Pedro spot
VSC strategy for the end of Stomp on the
Thwomp required a different preset HOLP to
send a bob-omb high above Mario. The third
problem is that Timed Jumps on Moving Bars also
required its own preset HOLP for the bob-omb
clip at the end. How could all of these extra
bob-ombs and preset HOLPs ever be reconciled?
Well, the third one was actually solved in
September of 2018 by ds273. It turns out the
overuse of preset HOLPs with limited opportunities
to enter Tick Tock Clock from anywhere in the
castle was spotted as a potential issue back then
as well. In an effort to cut preset HOLPs out,
ds273 figured out Timed Jumps on Moving
Bars without the bob-omb at the end.
The solution he came up with was the first
use of squish cancel in the ABC. It made
use of both pendulums for the ending
instead of just one. The far one was
used to get some height and dive to
this moving bar, and the second was
used to squish cancel a dive recover to allow
Mario to enter freefall. From a dive recover,
Mario can’t grab onto ledges, but from
freefall, he can. This lets him grab
this ledge and reach the star in no A presses
with no bob-omb, and therefore, no preset HOLP.
Now for the other two problems. Luckily, both
of them can be solved the same way. Unluckily,
that way adds to the solution to get past the
pole one extra thick layer of madness. Remember,
the bloated bob-omb used to cross the gap is one
of the two bob-ombs found at the very bottom of
the stage. The solution to the two problems
is to bring the other bob-omb past the pole.
The general idea of the route stays roughly
the same, until it’s time to make the final
ascent. That’s when even more steps
are needed to bring not just one,
but two bob-ombs up. First, there are
a few explosion clones that need to be
set up for what’s coming up. Explosion
clones function like you would expect:
when Mario collides with them, they knock him
back and damage him, then they become intangible,
just like most other clones. Mario places
one explosion clone over there, using BCA,
and three more right here. The first clone is a
sacrifice so that the other two can be used later.
With that done, the HOLP is set up
out of bounds on the moving bar,
and the first bob-omb is thrown there using
BCA, where it will be held in place safely,
much to our convenience. Next, the HOLP
is moved out of bounds using the clip
below the treadmill. This HOLP will be
used to move both bob-ombs up the clock.
Now, Mario wants to grab the second bob-omb.
Here, however, there is no other bob-omb whose
spawner can be conveniently used to bypass
updating the HOLP. This is where the explosion
clones come into play: they allow the use of
pause-buffered hitstun until a new invisible
object is able to be loaded into Mario’s hands:
a star particle spawner. This takes a while,
which is why two active clones were needed:
the first one to knock Mario back, and the
second one to extend his invincibility frames
long enough to load the star particle spawner.
That spawner quickly unloads, so now, Mario is
holding a vacant slot. Therefore, he needs to be
careful not to generate too much dust particles
and other temporary objects that could load into
his hands and update the HOLP. Nonetheless, he
climbs up the spinners and reaches these cubes.
He loads the bob-omb and drops it at the HOLP with
BCA, just outside of the activation radius. This,
however, is an awkward position: it’s too
low to be useful for the rest of the climb,
and too high to be worked with and dropped higher
up. So, it needs to be lowered first. To do that,
Mario goes down to this walkway
and enters the activation radius,
snapping the bob-omb to him. Then, he does a
breakdance kick to get the bob-omb to explode,
and does instant release on it while
it’s bloated at its maximum size. This
sends the bob-omb back to the HOLP, but
this time, a bit lower, and a bit bigger.
The next step is to climb up to the moving hand
but without reactivating the bob-omb. To do that,
Mario can simply ride the wild pendulum up
to the hand. This climb just barely works:
Mario is less than one unit from clipping through
the pendulum because it’s rising too fast. From
there, the other explosion clone comes in handy,
to setup another pause-buffered hitstun. Mario
enters the bob-omb’s activation radius, grabs
the bloated bomb and gets pushed off the hand,
where he drops it back to the HOLP,
still bloated, but much higher this time.
Then, it’s back to the first bob-omb!
Again, it’s dropped to the HOLP,
bloated as well, using instant release. The
two bob-ombs end up very close together,
the first one slightly lower and
the second one slightly higher.
After the squish cancel ground pound chain,
it’s time to reactivate one bob-omb. The two
radii are very close together, and as it turns
out, because it’s higher, the second bob-omb’s
radius is the one that Mario enters first.
Therefore, that’s the one that gets reactivated,
and the other one is kept in place for now.
This proves to be quite the problem, though,
because the range of motion is extremely limited.
This time, when the bob-omb snaps to Mario, it
pushes him not completely inside the cage, because
that would load the other bob-omb. Instead,
it pushes him between the two walls, where
their combined push cancels out. While in there,
Mario has two frames where he’s able to move out
of the way, until he exits the outside wall hitbox
and he completes the clip into the cage. At this
point, he’s within one single unit of activating
the other bob-omb. Finally, he’s able to grab the
bloated bob-omb and do the rest of the sequence.
After getting past the pole, he can retrieve the
first bob-omb by entering its activation radius.
We’re almost done. From here, the bomb has two
separate purposes. In The Pit and the Pendulums,
it’s used to replace the HOLP at the top of the
pole before collecting the star, so that after
re-entering the clock, another star that gets
past the pole can be done right away. The last
detail to consider for that star is that because
it’s now down to 0 A presses, Mario can’t kick the
wall to recoil into the star and setup spawning
displacement. So, a punch is used instead.
The principle is the same, but the execution
proved to be a lot more difficult and precise.
In order to receive the recoil speed and touch
the star on the same frame, a very specific
sequence of events needs to happen. First, Mario
punches from on top of the pendulum’s shaft. Then,
he snaps down to the head. This is possible
because when Mario is on the ground, he can
move from a higher floor to a lower floor by up
to a hundred units at once. On the next frame,
Mario is on a float-precise seam between
two walls, so he gets pushed by both.
This sends him next to the star and his
punch connects with the wall. Finally,
he receives recoil and touches the star one frame
later, and he falls with backwards momentum.
This specific set of conditions turned out
to be nearly impossible. After making and
running a brute forcer to figure
out a configuration that worked,
Pannenkoek found nothing. His closest attempt
was just two units short of touching the star.
But after brainstorming new options with
ds273, he finally found one single solution
that required a dive roll from the other
pendulum to punch the wall with enough
speed. Note that the hand also needs to be in
this precise spot to stop Mario from doing a
star dance clip on this platform instead,
which would ruin the spawning displacement.
For Stomp on the Thwomp, the bob-omb is
used, along with a slightly more complex
pendulum manipulation, to send Mario to the
Pedro spot. This was the combined work of
ds273 and Pannenkoek. First, Mario goes
up to the platform above the pendulums,
where he manipulates both of them at once.
Then, he falls on top of the first pendulum,
reactivating the bob-omb. It pushes Mario into
a spot just a little bit inside the ceiling,
like we’ve seen before. Mario walks in mid-air,
stuck in the ceiling, and he’s moved around by the
bob-omb pushing him back. Once he gets into the
Pedro spot, the rest of the strategy is very much
like the last Stomp on the Thwomp improvement. He
gathers nearly 700 speed, then uses a double VSC
to reach all the way to the Thwomp and collect
the star in a single A press. And this is how
Tick Tock Clock went from seven A presses down to
only four, three of which are to enter the stage.
But this wouldn’t hold for very long. A new face
in the community was concocting unusual plans.
He had been around for a few years, even
contributing to the latest A press saves,
but nothing on the scale of what he was about
to achieve. The complexity level was about to
get from the stratosphere to outer space
thanks to one man. His name was Marbler.
On August 21st, Pannenkoek and Marbler
completed their project of the past
couple of months. Together, they saved the
final A press of Lethal Lava Land. They got
Elevator Tour in the Volcano in zero A
presses, bringing the total count to 15.
First of all, why is this star problematic?
Well, because of the final boss of the A
button challenge: a pole. There’s no way to
get off this pole without falling down or
jumping. While it is possible to reach the
other star in the volcano in no A presses,
the two platforms are too far apart and a
long jump is required to cross that gap.
Instead, Mario will gain height another way, using
a familiar method in a completely new context.
Let’s reminisce the mechanics
of spawning displacement.
The reason it works is because Mario’s
displacement by a moving platform is based
on its state at the end of the previous frame,
effectively causing platforms to move Mario
for one extra frame after they should. If that
displacement is rotational, when the new map loads
and the platform gets replaced with a new object,
because Mario is very far from that new object,
the rotation is applied over a much longer
distance and Mario is moved significantly.
Here, the concept is exactly the same, except that
instead of a map transition creating a large gap,
Mario himself moves really far away in a single
frame. Then, when the displacement is applied, the
rotation is very small, but the radius is so large
that Mario is moved upwards substantially. Enough,
in fact, to end up above the star platform. In a
parallel universe, that is. Because for Mario to
get displaced so much, he needs to have PU speed
and move into a PU. Now the question becomes:
how can Mario be on a rotating platform on
one frame, and in a PU on the next? This is
where things get complicated. To get our answer,
let’s break down the 26-hour TAS step by step.
Mario begins by pushing a bully into the lava
and running into it. This interrupts the death
animation of the bully, which leaves it stuck
below the floor. Since there’s no more floor
under this, the bully is out of bounds.
Just like the bob-omb in Tick Tock Clock,
it gets stuck alternating between
two positions. As a sidenote,
for visual clarity, the bully will often
be represented in a superposition. Just
keep in mind this isn’t actually the case: the
bully is merely alternating between the two.
This state is particularly interesting because it
keeps the bully’s speed frozen. Even though the
bully itself is out of bounds, its hitbox sticks
out of the lava just enough that Mario can still
collide with it. If Mario runs into the bully
perpendicularly to its movement, he transfers some
of his momentum to the bully, adding a tiny bit
to its speed. This is called slow bully battery.
After doing this a few times, and by a few, I
mean 31000 over 21 hours, the bully now has 4000
speed. We can do something with that,
but first, we need to wait a few minutes.
In Super Mario 64, one full turn is 2 to the
16, or 65536 angle units. So when the bully
is trying to move out of bounds and its movement
is reversed, the game adds exactly half of that:
32767. Wait, 67? Yep! As it turns out, the angle
added is one two-hundredth of a degree shy of half
a turn. This discrepancy is obviously completely
meaningless. Unless you’re the ABC community.
While the bully is alternating between
two positions, the angle at which it moves
slowly drifts over time. So slowly, in fact,
that it takes over 36 minutes to do a full
rotation. Coincidentally, it’s also exactly
the time it takes for the displacement angle
to exceed the 32-bit integer limit
and overflow, causing a game crash.
But there’s an additional quirk that makes
this even more interesting. When calculating
the displacement, the game truncates
the angle to the nearest multiple of 16,
using what’s called hexadecimal angle units.
Therefore, in practice, as the angle drifts,
the actual displacement only changes once every
16 frames. Because 16 frames is an even number,
the angle change always happens while the bully is
in one of its two possible positions. As a result,
this position acts as a pivot around which
the other position rotates extremely slowly.
Choosing one position to act as the pivot is
fairly simple: after colliding with Mario,
if the bully’s angle is even, its current
position will be the pivot. If it’s odd, the
pivot will be the opposite. This means that while
Pannenkoek was building up the bully’s speed,
every single one of the 31000 collisions had to
result in an even angle. Using these pivots and
a lot of patience, you can get the bully to
move into any convenient location you want.
Marbler uses this to get the bully into a nice
spot for the next part, but first, he needs Mario
to be in a bit of a better shape. To climb the
volcano up to the spinning heart, he gets some
coins for a lava boost, then gets this bully stuck
in a corner and uses a dive roll knockback to
clear this ledge. This method will be used a few
times to refill Mario’s health throughout the run.
When the bully has rotated
around the pivot enough,
Mario runs into it so this position becomes
the new pivot. This causes the other position
to start moving. The process is repeated a
couple of times to move the bully around,
which takes about an hour. Now, Mario activates
the elevator and rides it until it falls into
the lava. And on this frame, the first
of many magic tricks: the bully appears.
Because the elevator is partly under the lava,
this creates a floor for the bully to move
onto. So, instead of turning around, the bully
does move to the elevator. On the next frame,
it moves onto the rock on the other side of
the stage. Now, the bully is back in bounds,
but it’s going so fast that its next
position is out of bounds. Again,
this reverses its direction and freezes its speed.
On the next frame, the same thing happens and the
bully reverses back to its previous position. The
result is therefore exactly the same as before,
even though the bully is now in bounds.
Regardless of the bully’s current position,
so long as its next position would be
out of bounds, it will behave this way.
Ten minutes of pivoting later, the
bully is now in a perfect position
for the next part. You know, slow
bully battery seems to imply the
existence of a fast bully battery. What
does that look like? Well, don’t blink!
The bully now has over 6000 speed. What happened?
This time, Mario isn’t bullying the bully; the
bully is bullying Mario. The collision angles are
reversed: the bully is mostly perpendicular and
Mario is parallel to the collision tangent. In
this scenario, the bully actually transfers three
times its momentum to Mario. This isn’t a bug,
it’s an intentional feature to give bullies a
bit more punch to their attack. Normally, this
wouldn’t be an issue because Mario’s knockback
speed is capped to 32, but, as you may have
guessed, this isn’t a normal scenario. This is
the original textbook use case for squish cancel.
The edge of the elevator has an exposed ceiling
because of a rounding error, and it’s a dynamic
surface. Mario enters the bully’s hitbox
to get knocked back. On the next frame,
first, the elevator displaces Mario into the
exposed slanted ceiling, squishing him. Then,
the bully collision moves Mario out and gives him
triple the bully’s momentum, or just shy of 10000
speed. Before the game processes the knockback
speed cap, the squish push, now disjointed
because of the bully collision, moves Mario
here, where he ends the frame. Since he left
the ceiling and the elevator, the squish cancel
is complete. Mario still has his high speed,
but he’s no longer being knocked back; he’s
now idle. Therefore, the speed is preserved.
On the next frame, the elevator moves back under
Mario, so instead of entering freefall, Mario is
still on the ground. At the same time, Mario moves
for one single quarterstep to the other end of
the stage. Because he’s still on the ground, he
can snap down to a floor up to 100 units lower;
82 units in this case. This is important because
when Mario tries to move out of bounds, his speed
is only conserved if he’s on the ground. If he’s
in the air, the speed is immediately set to 0.
Meanwhile, the bully, after this collision,
does lose a significant amount of its speed,
but it still has 1100. This is low enough to
actually move inside the level. Over the next
few frames, it bounces around, skipping over
Mario and bouncing back on out of bounds until
Mario hits it again. That transfers Mario’s
new speed back to the bully. The important
element of this interaction is the momentum
being tripled when the bully knocks Mario
away. This breaks the usual conservation
of energy. Just before the collision,
the bully had 2500 speed. A third of it was lost
during the two frames the bully spent moving
in bounds earlier. After Mario transfers
his speed back, the bully now has 6600.
The only caveat of this trick
is that it’s impossibly precise:
the elevator needs to send Mario into
a unit precise exposed ceiling and
the bully needs to somehow collide with
Mario again soon after. In other words,
Marbler was trying to hit a pea with a pool shot
where the balls are moving at escape velocity.
Nonetheless, fast bully batteries can be
chained together, allowing Mario and the
bully to exchange exponentially large speeds to
each other. After the first one, though, things do
get a bit simpler. First, the bully collides with
Mario at 6000 speed. This leaves Mario with 20000
speed, conserved using squish cancel, and the
bully with 4000 speed and an odd angle. Therefore,
the pivot is far out of bounds and
the bully slowly rotates back into
Mario. Mario transfers all of his speed
again, leaving the bully with 15000 speed.
This process is done a total of 6 times, roughly
tripling the speeds involved each time. However,
because the collision angles need to be somewhat
precise and their positions extremely precise,
this turned out to be a very complex logistical
problem. After one fast bully battery,
the bully often needs to rotate to a completely
different angle for the next one. Sometimes,
the bully itself needs to be moved using
alternating pivots to set up a viable position
for squish cancel. Marbler had to figure out
a way to move the bully around at PU speeds,
but never letting it cross a valid position
in a parallel universe. Doing that would
lose the bully into the void forever. He
carefully planned out a series of speeds
and rotations that would never cross
a PU throughout the entire process.
At PU speeds, when the pivot is tens of thousands
of units away, what used to be an imperceptible
rotation is now pretty obvious. This actually
becomes a problem at even higher speeds.
Moving the bully using a pivot becomes impractical
because the in-bounds position moves too fast for
Mario to keep up with it, and you can’t simply
wait out a full rotation when that would crash
the game. The last three fast bully batteries all
need to be done without moving the bully. Also,
the second to last one has to be done
within 5 frames or Mario would get
squished by another exposed ceiling, which
was another nightmare for Marbler to solve.
In this three-hour ordeal, the bully comes
dangerously close to a PU more times than
we can count, and ultimately runs into
Mario at 847000 speed. This gives Mario
3.4 million speed. And now, Mario is ready
to take an elevator ride out of this world.
But this is actually a bit more complex. For the
elevator to keep affecting Mario for a frame,
Mario needs to actually be on it. Not only does
Mario need to go to a PU in a single frame,
he needs to trick the elevator into thinking
he hasn’t moved at all! How does he do that?
Simple: by moving to a point in a PU that
corresponds to the elevator in the real map.
Except it wasn’t simple, it was actually a
total nightmare with a million workarounds
that barely work for all these reasons
that you can pause to read if you want.
Finally, after Mario moves from the elevator in
the main map to the same elevator but in a PU,
on the next frame, the elevator still thinks Mario
is standing on it and rotates ever so slightly.
This rotational displacement, when magnified
over a distance of 52 parallel universes,
sends Mario almost 4000 units
upwards, well above the star platform.
The conditions for this are quite precise,
considering Mario needs to stay in bounds. The
maximum vertical displacement achievable when
the elevator is in this state is quite small,
which is why Pannen and Marbler had
to settle for an insane distance to
magnify it over. This causes the horizontal
displacement to be problematic. There was no
way to have the elevator move Mario up far
enough without also flinging him far out of
bounds. They solved this problem by making
the elevator move Mario an entire PU over.
Now, Mario is a bit too high: about 500 units
above the star platform. To correct that,
after a bit of speed adjustment, Pannenkoek had
to make Mario fall down quite a bit. That fall
takes 20 frames and moves Mario by 975 parallel
universes. And now, all that’s left is to navigate
back in bounds. Pannenkoek moves 624 PUs in the
X axis and 96 on the Z axis, and finally, 352 PUs
X and 44 PUs Z, back to the main map. Collecting
the star is trivial. Reaching the star… was not.
Let’s back up a bit on the timeline, to April
19th, 2022. Tick Tock Clock’s triple A press save
was being heavily worked on, and it was looking
more and more likely by the day. On that night,
ds273 and Marbler were in a voice chat.
The subject of Stomp on the Thwomp soon
being down to a single A press came up. What
about saving that last A press? Marbler and
ds273 were laughing at even suggesting such a
thing. First of all, that jump is probably the
single A press that gets the most work done. It
skips going up these boxes, these treadmills,
and of course, the thwomp itself. They had
no star dance clip left, no preset HOLP,
no pendulums, and one bob-omb from all the way
at the bottom of the clock. Needless to say,
it was never going to happen and
they had a good laugh about it.
The next day, Marbler set out to demonstrate how
infeasible this idea was by going through each
step and showing precisely why it couldn’t be
done. He came to the conclusion that in total,
there were eight problematic points. Two
here, two here, three here, and finally,
getting on top of the thwomp. Most of these could
theoretically be solved with a star dance clip,
but proving that is useless; you
can’t just spawn seven 100-coin stars.
But then, Marbler looked closer at each
failure point, and the closer he looked,
the more answers he found. First, the pole
platform, which uses the only available
star dance clip. This in itself is a problem,
because it means the method to get past the pole,
with its use of a star and a fire clone, is a one
time use. For a 0 A press strategy to have any
kind of a chance of being possible, there would
need to be a way to climb up and down the pole to
set up HOLPs for cloning. It was time for Mario
to do away with non-renewable height sources.
This is the crux of the issue. With the
amount of obstacles on the way up the clock,
the problem becomes very similar to
what Bowser in the Sky used to be:
a very long deconstructed goomba bridge. Except,
this time, it was bob-ombs, coins and fire clones,
and this time, instead of casually walking around
Bowser in the Sky, every single step involved
repeating the madness-inducing nonsense to get
past the pole in no A presses. Every single time.
The elevator platform could theoretically
be reached from below using a dive recover,
a fire bounce and a misalignment. Unfortunately,
despite this wall having an open corner, it’s not
pointing away from the origin, therefore
no misalignment exists. But if instead,
a bloated bob-omb could snap to Mario’s
position and push him into that corner,
it could possibly push him completely through
the wall hitboxes and into the floor beyond.
This diagonal is 141 units. A maximum size
bloated bob-omb pushes Mario by 149 units.
On paper, this could actually work. In
practice, well, that’s another story.
Where would that bob-omb that magically
snaps to Mario’s position even come from?
The 4000-unit sphere would need to
intersect this minuscule spot in a
way that Mario can enter it here without
touching it at any earlier time. But also,
what bob-omb would that even be? Currently,
the only two bob-ombs are already in use. Well,
it turns out both of these questions can be
answered at once using pause-buffered hitstun.
When Mario grabs a bob-omb, it’s always placed 100
units in front of Mario, regardless of where the
HOLP is. This allows Mario to do a bob-omb glide
despite the HOLP still being disjointed. This
comes within one frame of failing, but it does
get Mario across without updating the HOLP. Then,
the bob-omb is released back to the HOLP, which,
remember, is out of bounds across the clock.
By some absolute miracle, with a very slight
modification to its exact position, the same
HOLP used to cross this gap and to retrieve
the bob-omb past the pole can also perfectly
intersect this open corner. This lets Mario
reuse the same bob-omb to get pushed completely
past the wall hitboxes and into the floor
hitbox, bypassing the use of star dance clip.
This groundbreaking discovery had two huge
implications: first, the star dance clip
was freed up to be used somewhere else,
higher up in the clock. But crucially,
there was now nothing preventing Mario from
making multiple trips up and down the pole.
Well, almost nothing. There were
just five little hurdles to get over.
First, Mario also needs a repeatable
way of getting off the pole. Thankfully,
after the first trip up, he can lure this Heave
Ho to get stuck in just the right spot to have
it fling Mario from the pole directly
onto the elevator above. How convenient!
Now for the second problem. The setup to clip
this corner was extremely precise and required
a fire clone, but remember, fire clones can only
be interacted with once. Each trip up the pole
adds one more fire clone, and they all need to
be in different positions for Mario to be able
to touch them individually. Contrarily to goombas
which can be as close to each other as possible,
fire clones need to be at least 37 units
away from each other to be usable. The
elevator can only take up a limited set
of positions, so the possible heights
Mario could achieve were also limited
in the same way. All things considered,
a maximum of 21 trips up the pole were
theoretically possible with this method.
The third issue was between he HOLP and the
squish cancel ground pound chain. Remember,
the old position was just barely far enough away
to allow for the strategy to be possible in the
first place. Sadly, this new required HOLP was
incompatible. It prompted SJMHRP to revisit the
squish cancel ground pound chain and find a
completely new method. And the one she found
was not only compatible with the new HOLP, it
was also a lot simpler to set up and repeat.
The fourth headache was between the HOLP and
the instant release at the moving bar. The new
HOLP was also incompatible with this part, since
it barely overlapped with the entire moving bar.
This one was fixed with a clever use of BCA
right at the edge of the activation radius.
Finally, the thing with fire clones is that
while they can give Mario additional height,
they do so at the cost of his health. As of
now, getting all the way up to the pole cost
Mario 11 health sectors, way above the maximum
survivable damage of 7. While theoretically,
coin clones could be used along the way to refill
some of that missing health, they would need at
least 4 per trip, which would be unbelievably
annoying to set up. But SJMHRP’s improvement
to the squish cancel ground pound chain also
took down the damage Mario takes from 6 to 2,
meaning that Mario could live through this
climb without a single coin for extra health.
Now, the bob-omb used past the pole
in Stomp on the Thwomp’s 1 A press
strategy could be repurposed for other
things higher up in the clock. However,
at its current height, the 4000-unit
radius ends up short. So, the bob-omb
needs to be moved up while staying
out of bounds. But here’s a problem:
Mario needs to enter the activation radius to
snap the bob-omb to him, then he needs to be
out of the 4000-unit cylinder to release the
bob-omb back to the HOLP at this new height.
How can he go all the way from here to there?
Certainly not with Behind Camera Anywhere, but
maybe with pause-buffered hitstun. But even PBH
ends up way too short. Enter the Hitstun Highway.
This series of explosion clones creates
a path for Mario to extend his hitstun
timer all the way across the clock and exit the
activation radius before releasing the bob-omb
without ever updating the HOLP. Another problem
solved. And now a new problem is created. To get
from the elevator to Timed Jumps on Moving Bars,
usually, a Heave Ho flip bypassed the whole thing.
But if it has to be stuck here, Mario needs a
new way to get from here to there. Thankfully,
a simple misalignment on the corner of this
platform gets the job done. Except it doesn’t,
because that would reactivate the
bob-omb we’ve just moved. Instead,
another fire clone has to be used. For
multiple trips, a string of fire clones.
The next failure point was these cubes, which
were decidedly too far apart to ascend. However,
there is an alternative to navigating those:
reaching the top of this cage and diving
across. Unfortunately, that’s not easy either,
but it is possible with fire bounces. Oh, and
a second chain of squish cancel ground pounds
on this pendulum that comes within a single unit
of reactivating the bob-omb early. No big deal.
The final ground pound is actually pretty
significant. While Mario is in the ascending
part of the ground pound, quarterstep collisions
are not calculated, which is how he can clip
through platforms sometimes. Regardless, another
collision check is also made at the start of the
frame. But there’s a key difference in the hitbox
shape used for those checks: instead of using the
air movement hitboxes, it uses the ground movement
hitbox, which is narrower at the top. Because it’s
narrower, it happens to miss Mario on this frame.
On the next frame, because the moving bar is
springing out fast enough, the hitbox skips over
Mario entirely. As Mario starts to fall back down,
he meets the side of the moving bar, which pushes
him out. But because that would push him into a
ceiling, the movement is canceled and Mario stays
put. After collisions with walls are handled,
collisions with floors are next on the list,
so Mario lands on top of the moving bar.
To get up on this walkway though, there was no
misalignment. It wasn’t anywhere near the bob-omb
activation radius. There was nothing to work with.
This is where the star dance clip would have to
be used. Which means, everything further up can
only be accessed once, so better make it count.
And make it count, Marbler did. The first
treadmill step can be approached in two
different ways. The first is somehow getting
324 units of height to reach a misalignment,
which can only be done with a star dance clip. The
second is to reach it from the walkway instead,
which is just a little bit too far away to
be possible. But what about this bob-omb
that we placed out of bounds at around
the height of the pole? You guessed it:
its activation radius just so happens to now be
perfectly placed to snap the bob-omb back to Mario
right here, which pushes him into the one unit
misalignment and snaps him up to the treadmill.
Then, Mario does a quick turn. When the stick
is held in a direction different than the one
Mario is looking in, he slowly turns until
he matches that new angle. But if instead,
Mario is walking and comes to a complete stop,
he can then turn in any direction instantly. So,
this is what happens: Mario lands
with the stick at a neutral position,
which stops his momentum. Then, he walks
at the minimum stick range for one frame,
comes to a stop, and instantly turns around.
This allows him to turn around in only 4 frames,
instead of up to 16, which in turn lets him grab
the bob-omb before it falls out of his grasp.
Now for the final treadmill, which again, is
simply too high. To have any chance of getting up,
Marbler had to think outside the box, where he
found one sliver of hope: the spinners. The height
difference from here to there is just barely
within reason, but could this gap be cleared?
Well, of course it can, with a bob-omb glide! The
problem, though, is that the bob-omb is so bloated
that Mario ends up completely overshooting it.
The spinner is also still a bit too high to reach
without the extra help from stored vertical speed.
So, instead, Marbler waits out the fuse timer,
then regrabs the bob-omb as it’s about to
explode, when it’s slightly less bloated.
This turned out to be a bit of a tricky maneuver.
First, Mario gets pushed off the treadmill, so he
dives back on. On the next frame, he does a dive
recover, which has to be pause buffered because
it’s another B press on two consecutive frames.
Because the end of the treadmill is so steep,
after one quarterstep, Mario immediately lands
again, which stores a vertical speed of 26. On
the next frame, he does a standing punch, which
also has to be pause buffered because it’s yet
another B press. This establishes the bob-omb as
the target of a grab, but because it’s a standing
punch, Mario doesn’t quite grab the bob-omb yet.
At the same time, he gets pushed back off the
treadmill by the now expanding bob-omb, which
reactivates his conserved 26 vertical speed.
On the next frame, Mario does a pause buffered
dive, the fourth B press on consecutive frames.
This makes him grab the bob-omb instantly, because
it’s already the target of a grab, and also makes
him land on the treadmill again, this time with 22
vertical speed. At this point, the bob-omb pushes
Mario back off the treadmill, where he enters
freefall while hands free holding. His stored
vertical speed carries him up and a ground pound
covers the rest. But it’s just not quite enough
to land square on the spinner. That’s a handful
of units too far to reach, because the side wall
of the spinner prevents landing on the corner. At
least, it would, except there’s a sliver of floor
one unit wide sticking out of the wall hitbox,
which allows Mario to land safely on the spinner.
Staying on the spinner is also a
bit tricky, but it is doable thanks
to the bob-omb still pushing Mario back and
keeping him on the steep slope long enough.
After this section, the rest is
a piece of cake until the Thwomp.
Here, the bob-omb is used to get a fire
clone by the Thwomp using BCA. Thankfully,
there is another fire spitter
right at the top of the clock,
so no need to go all the way down for it.
Besides, remember, there’s no turning back
after using the star dance clip. But the real
problem here is that the flame clone needs
to be higher than the highest point where
Mario can set the HOLP or release a clone.
This was solved by ds273 and Marbler using a wild
combination of object slot manipulation magic and
the jagged diagonal of the treadmill’s floor to
get in a hands free holding state. That still
wasn’t enough, because while they could get Mario
a bit higher up with a ground pound, he couldn’t
release an object, and therefore place the HOLP,
until after he landed. That is until ds273 had the
idea of using BCA not just to release the clone,
but to set the HOLP itself. By forcing Mario to go
off camera during the ground pound, the HOLP stops
updating at this point, so it remains up there.
And finally, the last magic trick: a dive
recover VSC into a ground pound squish
cancel fire bounce to reach a misalignment
on the corner of the Thwomp. This is not
like a regular misalignment. Instead,
it exists because the wall is ever so
slightly slanted sideways, creating a one
unit gap in its corner at certain heights.
Now, repeatedly burning Mario to clear gaps
takes its toll on the poor plumber. Thankfully,
there are two spinning hearts in Tick-Tock Clock,
but despite all the best efforts to minimize the
burning damage, Mario comes within one sixteenth
of a sector of health of dying. On top of that,
four coin clones are used to refill
some health. Setting all of this up
requires multiple trips up and down the clock
to place all of these clones. How many, exactly?
Five trips to set up enough fire clones at this
elevator for the rest of the route. Two trips
to set up the explosion clones for the bob-omb
glide under pause-buffered hitstun. Two trips
to set up the explosion clones for the hitstun
highway. Two trips for the flame clones to get
off this elevator. Two trips for the flame clones
needed to get up on this cage, and coin clones to
refill Mario’s health. One trip for the flame
and coin clones on top of the cage. One trip to
set up a coin and a fire clone for the star dance
clip. One more trip to set up a flame clone here,
because the way the bob-omb is sent to the out
of bounds HOLP for the last time prevents Mario
from manipulating the Heave Ho into throwing
him directly on the elevator. It’s possible
to get on the elevator with at least 128 units
of height, excluding 128. A dive recover gives
Mario precisely 128 units of height, so it’s not
enough, hence the use of one more fire clone.
And finally, a seventeenth trip up the clock
where Mario sets up two bob-ombs out of bounds.
He climbs up with a squish cancel ground pound
chain. He snaps one bob-omb to his position and
crosses the gap under pause buffered hitstun
to avoid updating the HOLP. He climbs up to
the pole by snapping that same bob-omb to him
again and clipping into the floor of the pole
platform. He snaps the other bob-omb to him and
uses a pause-buffered hitstun highway to carry it
across the map without updating the out of bounds
HOLP. He gets flung next to the elevator and flame
bounces onto it. He hits another fire clone to
cross this gap. He rides this pendulum up, does
a final squish cancel ground pound chain up to the
cage, flame bounces up to the top. He star dance
clips to this walkway. Snaps the bob-omb to him
one last time to get on the treadmill, then glides
into a misalignment on this spinner. He carries
that bob-omb all the way to the top, where,
using hands free holding and BCA, he sets up the
HOLP for one last little bit of cloning. Finally,
he completes the star with VSC, a ground pound
squish cancel, a fire bounce and a misalignment to
get on top of the Thwomp. At last, Tick Tock Clock
is A press free. Tick Tock Clock is conquered.
At least, on paper. Every piece of the puzzle
has been figured out and proven possible, but
an A press save is only truly proven when there
is a proper TAS that pieces it all together in
one fluid motion. This unbelievably complex task
is, as always, given to pannenkoek2012. This time,
though, he isn’t doing it all alone:
SJMHRP and Marbler join him as well.
SJMHRP’s specialty was the 17 squish cancel
ground pound chains on the lower pendulum.
Pannenkoek dealt with everything in the lower
part of the clock, which came out to be most of
the work. Marbler took care of the upper section,
taking over after SJMHRP, and handing back the TAS
to Pannenkoek whenever Mario had to go back down
to set up more clones. Very little of the TASing
process could be automated. Aside from pendulum
manipulation and a couple of repeated processes,
nearly all of this 6-hour TAS was painstakingly
created frame by frame, which took in the ballpark
of 180 hours and over 160,000 rerecords. The
team ran into an issue with the preset HOLP that
threatened nearly the entire first half of the
work, but they managed to miraculously salvage it.
The theorycrafting of the route was done
in parallel to the work on the three A
press saves from July. Work on the TAS began
soon after Lethal Lava Land was finished,
in mid-September. It was finally completed on
October 27th, and published two weeks later,
on November 13th, 2022. As of today, there
are 14 A presses left in Super Mario 64.
So, what are those 14 A presses and how could
we save them? First, let’s look at the famous
A presses to enter Tick Tock Clock. With three
spawning displacement strategies allowing for
a re-entry without using A, Tick Tock Clock now
needs to be entered three times from the floor.
The prospect of adding more spawning displacements
is quite grim. It just does not seem possible. But
even if it was, Tick Tock Clock already requires
three different preset HOLPs that can’t be set
within the stage itself. Each entry that requires
an A press sets the HOLP somewhere else before
entering the stage, so adding another spawning
displacement would disrupt this fine balance.
So, what other options are there? Well, in
this room of the castle, not that many. The
level entrance is pretty high up, so there’s no
hope to ever get up directly from the floor to
the clock in no A presses. That’s not even
close. The only possible avenue would be to
reach it from the path to Bowser in the Sky.
Unfortunately, to have any chance of that,
Mario would need at least about 90 speed. With
nothing useful to work with, that’s well beyond
the maximum speed attainable. For now, these
three A presses are looking pretty solid.
Similarly, also in this room is a pair of
twin A presses: one to go to Rainbow Ride,
and one to go to Wing Mario over the
Rainbow. Again, the outlook is bleak:
90 speed would suffice, but it’s
still nowhere near feasible.
The next A press left is in Jolly Roger Bay,
to collect the star Treasure of the Ocean
Cave. This A press, as trivial as it is,
has been a total nightmare to try and save
for over a decade. The star is 24 units too
high to be collected with a dive recover.
The chests look like the obvious solution,
but they’re simple objects with a hitbox and no
actual geometry. Mario can’t stand or bounce on
them. The star is at one of the highest points in
the room, so it’s tricky to approach it otherwise.
It was found that given enough speed, Mario
could in theory collect the star. Unfortunately,
this method requires about 260 speed, whereas the
maximum speed that has been proven possible to
gain in the level is only about 180, using these
pillars. Multiple ideas to build up more speed
were examined, but none of them were successful.
The floating ship doesn’t have the right surface
for C-up sliding nor the right conditions for
hyperspeed punching. This rock has a lot of
potential, but the conditions aren’t perfectly
right to allow for hyperspeed of some kind.
Research is still ongoing to try
to find new ways to build up speed,
or to try and lower the 260 requirement. No
significant progress has been made in years.
Princess’s Secret Slide is in a similar
boat, but much worse. While the star
you get for finishing the slide under 21
seconds is low enough for a dive recover,
the star inside the box isn’t. The box itself can
be broken with a dive recover, but then the star
is 31 units too high. There’s very little hope
because the geometry of the room is so barren
that there simply isn’t anything to work with. If
the star had been closer to the back of the room,
then it would have been reachable with
VSC and a ground pound. Other than that,
there are a few pipe dreams like spawning
displacement in the title screen demo,
but none of that is remotely close to work. In
fact, the demo in Princess’s Secret Slide never
presses any buttons, so it couldn’t even
break the box even if it had the chance.
Next up is Tiny-Huge Island. Here, the one
star with remaining A presses is Wiggler’s
red coins. This, in fact, is one of two stars
left in the game that requires two A presses
to get. The first one to clear this gap,
and the second one to get on these pillars.
I’m repeating myself here, but again, this
room just doesn’t have much to work with:
isolated platforms with large height
disparities, no way to clone anything,
and just this one fire spitter.
However, there is the floor above.
Here, you can find Wiggler running around and some
coins. It’s not much better, but it’s something.
And, as it turns out, it is possible to use
Wiggler to set up hyperspeed. Unfortunately,
no way was ever found to clip down into the red
coins room, so that high speed is useless. Crazier
strategies were also looked at. Having Wiggler
itself come down seems impossible and not even
helpful. A star dance clip could be good, if not
for the only available coins being in unhelpful
locations, the need for a flame clone which is
impossible, and for the 100-coin star already
being required to reach the mainland in the first
place. Using sliding speed conservation to carry
hyperspeed into the red coins room seemed
quite promising, but unlike a pause exit,
this map transition doesn’t preserve sliding
speed. Ultimately, the search turned up fruitless.
The second star with two remaining A presses
is Wing Mario over the Rainbow. And here,
we’ve got the most solid A press in the
entire game. You can’t fly without an A
press. Mario can start flying in only three
ways: with a triple jump, a cannon shot, or,
in this one specific exception, if he
starts the level already flying. Due to
the nature of this level, collecting all the
red coins without flying is unimaginable. So,
of the 14 A presses left, this is by far the one
that’s the most absolutely sure to never be saved.
With that in mind, though, there have been
some ideas thrown around to at least reduce
the star to a single cannon shot instead
of two. The problem here is pretty simple:
from the start of the stage, you need to
go to the bottom of the level to talk to
the pink bob-omb and activate the cannons. The
lowest cannon is too low and too weak to shoot
Mario all the way up to the top of the stage, so
one shot from the high cannon is also required,
for a total of two A presses. Note that entering
the level takes one A press by itself, so you
can’t open the cannons and re-enter the stage.
The only way would be by dying, but there’s no
way to take damage without an A press from this
spot. Even assuming you could re-enter the stage
with the cannons already open, only the lowest
cannon is accessible without an A press anyway.
There’s one more glimmer of hope. When
Mario is flying against the edge of the map,
he’s actually able to build up speed.
Unfortunately, the speed at which Mario
accelerates with this method is much too slow, and
the wing cap has a limited timer. On top of that,
the timer can’t be refreshed because Mario
can’t break boxes while flying unless he’s
flying very slowly. Therefore, there’s
no way to build up meaningful speed,
because you’d constantly need to give up
all that speed to refresh your flying timer.
Another level with two A presses is
Shifting Sand Land. Here, though,
it’s just one A press, but repeated on
two different stars: to get out of the
elevator for Inside the Ancient Pyramid and
Pyramid Puzzle. The elevator is particularly
annoying because its walls are just 7 units
too high for a dive recover to clear them.
There’s also the option of climbing the
entire pyramid, which sounds terrible,
but surprisingly doesn’t look too bad. After
a precise knockback bounce to warp past this
pole and a star dance clip to get up to
here, things are looking up. But then,
all hope is lost when Mario faces
another pole. With no warp available,
no helpful knockback source, and no way to
clone anything, this A press seems unavoidable.
Specifically for Inside the Ancient Pyramid,
things look even worse. A second A press is needed
to reach the star, although a star dance clip has
been shown to work. Of course, you can only have
one star dance clip at once. The pole A press also
serves to get on top of this grindel and clear the
next ledge. Without that jump, this little step
just barely too high for a dive recover would
have to be cleared using an amp clip. These
amps are unique: instead of going in a circle,
they chase Mario. This corner is just barely close
enough to make an amp appear. With a clever lure,
it shocks Mario and he grabs the ledge,
just like a star dance clip. Theoretically,
an amp clip could also get Mario up to the star,
but it doesn’t work. In short, the amp might not
go that high up, and it won’t stay this far from
its home long enough for a double amp clip. But
regardless, the problem is the pole. Without
a way to get past the pole, nothing matters.
There is, however, one remote possibility
involving Eyeroks. If an Eyerok is about to
pound the ground but it starts its movement
while already touching the ground, it can
shoot upwards into infinity. This idea has some
potential, but outside of hacking its position,
the Eyerok has never been made to
enter this state. Even if it did,
though, it rises so fast that Mario would
clip through it instead of being carried up.
Last but not least, this is perhaps
the most infamous A press of them all:
the pole in Bowser in the Fire Sea. From the very
beginning, Tyler Kehne’s primary focus was to
make a 70-star run in 0 A presses a reality. For
over 7 years, this one A press has been the only
barrier between him and his goal. Even worse,
it is actually possible to get past the pole,
but only on the Wii Virtual Console. But
the fact that it’s an emulated re-release,
and its incompatibility with the
Japanese N64 exclusive glitches,
have always tarnished the 0 A press full game run
in the minds of Tyler Kehne and the ABC community.
A blueprint to make it possible on Nintendo
64 has been in the works for years and years,
but several hurdles remain. The idea
is actually similar to the Lethal Lava
Land strategy. It consists of supplying
thousands of speed to one or more bullies,
then using squish cancel and the rotational
displacement of one of these platforms to send
Mario up as he travels to a parallel universe.
When he comes back, he’s now past the pole.
The setup is a bit more complex than
in Lethal Lava Land. Here’s a rundown
of how it works - I’ll give you time to
read it. It boils down to this problem:
the platform rotates because of
Mario’s weight on it. As such,
the rotational displacement applied to
Mario is almost always going to be negative.
Getting a positive displacement from this
platform requires a sudden burst of speed that
isn’t possible to achieve with normal movement.
The only currently known way to do it would
need three different bullies, all hovering at
ludicrous speeds and pinpoint precise positions.
Only, there’s a single bully down here, so this
cannot work. This theoretical solution was created
after years of work by Tyler Kehne. He did it by
hacking the speed and position of each bully, and
its purpose is to serve as a demonstration that
the idea of a PU speed squish cancel upwarp in
Bowser in the Fire Sea can work on paper given the
right conditions. This wishful thinking would take
a massive leap towards reality if it was shown
to be possible using only one hyperspeed bully.
And in fact, that’s exactly what happened just a
week ago, when SpudY2K showed off a route using
the 10k glitch that would theoretically require a
single bully. But despite the creation of multiple
different bruteforcers to try and find favourable
conditions there’s still a lot of work to be done
to bring this idea to reality. This is the brick
wall the ABC community needs to break through. The
actual bully battery is thought to be relatively
trivial in comparison to this massive problem,
although it could take significantly longer
than the mere 26 hours of Lethal Lava Land.
There are also four half A presses remaining in
the run: one for Watch for Rolling Rocks to use
elevators with PU speed, two in Dire Dire
Docks to swim with the shell for cloning,
and one for Get a Hand to kick the wall
to set up spawning displacement. With
so many other A presses left, it seems
very unlikely that we’ll ever run into
a situation where these half A presses
become a problem for the 120-star run.
Here’s my own judgement of how likely each A press
is to ever be saved. It’s entirely subjective,
and while I believe the gist of it is generally
agreed on, the exact ordering is pure speculation.
Of all these A presses, the most likely to be
saved is definitely Bowser in the Fire Sea. A
long way behind would be Jolly Roger Bay, then
Shifting Sand Land and the second cannon of Wing
Mario over the Rainbow. Even less likely would
be one of the two A presses in Tiny-Huge Island,
followed by all of the stage entries, with
a slight favour towards Tick Tock Clock.
At rock bottom, you can find saving
both A presses in Tiny-Huge Island,
the Princess Secret Slide box, and finally, the
first cannon in Wing Mario over the Rainbow.
The final, perfectly optimized A press
count might very well be 13. If we’re
slightly more optimistic, maybe 10
or 11. If we’re wildly optimistic,
it could get down to about a handful.
I see no possible scenario where the
entire game could ever get down to zero. But
regardless of the final frontier of the ABC,
there will always be the endless secondary
challenge of making the run faster and more
efficient. Over the years, countless improvements
have been made that cut dozens of hours from the
total run time. A full 70-star run in 0 A
presses has been in the works for years,
but it’s stuck waiting for Bowser in the Fire
Sea to be solved on Nintendo 64. Meanwhile,
the estimated time for a 120-star run in 14 A
presses is now 58 hours and 47 minutes. Over
two thirds of that can be attributed to Elevator
Tour in the Volcano and Tick Tock Clock combined.
Over twenty-two years, the A Button Challenge has
become the most fascinating video game endeavour
of all time. In 2000, when Alex Penev posed
this challenge to a handful of friends on IRC,
he couldn’t even begin to imagine what would
become of it. Neither would Curtis Bright,
who tried to turn it into a new form of
competition on his website. His vision and
forward thinking to allow tool-assisted speedruns
to compete on his board paved the way for the
revolutionary work of bobmario511, who set the
baseline for years to come. At the same time,
Thiago Trujillo attacked the real-time version
of the challenge almost all on his own,
an achievement that, to this day, is
still underrated. But by all means,
this amazing adventure would have never happened
without the now legendary pannenkoek2012.
His incredible work on the A Button
Challenge inspired multiple generations,
coming in waves over the next 9 years. First
came Plush, Gaehne D. and sonicpacker who
supplemented Pannen’s work with novel ideas.
Then Tyler Kehne, whose fresh outlook brought
three major trick discoveries that shaved
off dozens of A presses, and bad_boot,
who not only made key discoveries, but also
rekindled the real-time ABC. In recent years,
Marbler took the complexity level to a new
galaxy, helped by the involvement of talented
and dedicated problem solvers like Iwer Sonsch,
ds273, and SJMHRP. The team has evolved so much,
but at its core, the infallible Pannenkoek remains
the captain of the mission. His commitment to the
journey and his undying resilience continue to
amaze hundreds of thousands of people to this day.
The legacy left by Pannenkoek and the A Button
Challenge cannot be overstated. It inspired
so many other game communities to do the same.
Just to name a few, pretty much all of the Mario
games. The 2D Mario games would seem boring at a
glance, but they’re actually full of surprises.
Super Mario World is especially interesting,
considering that all 96 exits can be done
in only 24 A or B presses. More recently, the
New Super Mario Bros. Wii jumpless challenge,
done by Adeal, is getting a lot of attention.
Super Mario Sunshine and both Galaxy games have
to waste hundreds of A presses in menus, but they
are quite optimized in terms of actual gameplay.
Most 3D Sonic games also have
an A Button Challenge - in fact,
Shadow the Hedgehog was beaten entirely in 0
A presses by RingRush. The Donkey Kong 64 ABC,
which is also led by RingRush, is absolutely
full of clever solutions and goofy tricks. Its
sister games Banjo-Kazooie and Banjo-Tooie both
have A Button Challenges of their own as well.
The Super Mario 64 ABC also inspired a myriad
of more or less loosely related challenges,
such as the B and Z button challenges,
the no buttons challenge and the no
joystick challenge. Even in other games
like Ocarina of Time and Majora’s Mask,
any% low pauses or All Dungeons no doors,
beating Sonic 3 without pressing right,
and half of Ceave Gaming’s YouTube
channel. The list is absolutely endless.
So, this is it. This is the current state of the
A button challenge. 14 A presses remain. Dozens
of blueprints exist to try and save them. One of
them is being actively worked on and is thought
to be possible. Only one. After all these years,
the community has finally hit a wall. With all
its dead ends, the current outlook for the
future of the A Button Challenge does look
a bit grim. But the community around it keeps
growing. Over the years, the entire Super Mario
64 code was fully decompiled. Countless
simulators were written to investigate
billions and billions of possibilities. There’s
still work ahead of us. There might always be.
Mount Everest wasn’t designed to be climbable.
Mountains don’t care if anyone manages to reach
the top or not. Super Mario 64 was never
designed to be beaten with zero A presses.
The game doesn’t care if it’s possible. We do.
And until we reach the top, we will keep climbing.